<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The amorous travellers, or, The night-adventures written originally in Spanish by a person of honour. Translated into French by the exquisite pen of the Sieur Deganes, and into English by J.B.</title>
            <title>Engaños deste siglo y historia sucedida en nuestros tiempos. English</title>
            <author>Loubayssin de Lamarca, Francisco.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 250 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 113 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01370</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3021AB</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224365</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52211669</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52211669</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01370)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2732:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The amorous travellers, or, The night-adventures written originally in Spanish by a person of honour. Translated into French by the exquisite pen of the Sieur Deganes, and into English by J.B.</title>
                  <title>Engaños deste siglo y historia sucedida en nuestros tiempos. English</title>
                  <author>Loubayssin de Lamarca, Francisco.</author>
                  <author>Bulteel, John, fl. 1683.</author>
                  <author>Ganes, sieur de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 214 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.C. for Ambrose Isted at the Golden Anchor against S. Dunstan's Church in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Engaños deste siglo y historia sucedida en nuestros tiempos.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Texas, Austin Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175400:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175400:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE AMOROUS TRAVELLERS, OR, <hi>The Night-Adventures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written Originally in <hi>Spaniſh</hi> By a Perſon of
Honour.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated into <hi>French</hi> By the Exquiſite Pen of the
<hi>Sieur DEGANES:</hi> And into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>J. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <q> 
               <p>Voluptas non eſt voluptas, quae cum malâ famâ,
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lâque conſcientiâ conjuncta
eſt.</p>
               <bibl>Eraſm.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q> 
               <l>Noctu latent Mendae.</l> 
               <l>Amor &amp; melle &amp; felle eſt
foecundiſſimus.</l>
               <bibl>Plaut.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. C.</hi> for <hi>Ambroſe
Iſted</hi> at the <hi>Golden Anchor</hi> againſt S. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s
Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:175400:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175400:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Fertile Age of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it happens as in War, where
great Armies are in the Field, many Robbers pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the High-ways, where
thoſe that are not valiant enough to purchaſe a Prey by ſtorming a
Fortified Town, or beating an Armed Enemy, can eaſily plunder a ſmall
Countrey-Village, or rob a naked Traveller: So now adays thoſe who either are
fearful or unable to try their Fortune in the World with their own
Compoſures, dare boldly do it with thoſe of others. Hence it comes that our
Stages are ſo crowded with<pb facs="tcp:175400:3"/>private Thefts, or owned Tranſlations
out of <hi>Molier</hi> and the <hi>Corneilles,</hi> and our Preſſes with
<hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh Novels:</hi> the laſt of which (I mean
<hi>Novels</hi>) being nearer our Phraſe, are leſs ſubject to ſpoiling;
but the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, whoſe Elegance conſiſts more in the Language, are for
the moſt part brought over in ſuch ſhallow or leakie Veſſels, that
they are ſo damaged by the way, that we may ſay emphatically, <hi>Le Jeu ne
vaut pas la Chandelle,</hi> The Play's not worth the Candle, much leſs a
three Hours Attendance, unleſs of thoſe that have more time than they know
how to diſpoſe of better. And our Tranſlating Poets, blind to
themſelves, can ſtretch their Spleens, as well as Throats, at the
ridiculous <hi>French</hi> Dreſs with which they diſguiſe an
<hi>Engliſh</hi> Player; but in the mean time admire for a Magnificent Habit
that notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly<pb facs="tcp:175400:3"/>Mimick one with which they clothe a
<hi>French</hi> Play. In this Vanity our witty Emperours of
<hi>Parnaſſus</hi> imitate the perſecuting ones of <hi>Rome,</hi> that
firſt wrapped the Primitive Chriſtians in Skins of Beaſts, and then
worried them, exploding a Religion which they thought Heterodox, and
maintaining one which any Rational Man would bluſh to own.</p>
            <p>Now after a Reflection upon others Faults, thou maiſt chance
expect from me an Apologie for my own; but to deal plainly with thee, Reader, I
muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint thee, that I am ſo far from fearing thy Frowns, that it were
a folly for me to court thy Smiles: For to what purpoſe ſhould I beg
Applauſe from them whom I never intend to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble any more, no more than I
had done now, if I had not thought what was ſo extremely diverting to me
might be ſo to<pb facs="tcp:175400:4"/>another? For this is onely the Off-ſpring of
ſome leiſure-Hours, and therefore can ſcarce be expected to be good,
ſince it ſprung from ſo bad a Root as Idleneſs; in which vacant time,
having been wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with better Studies, I was tumbling over ſome of this
kind, to find one the most divertive: I light on this, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and
Compoſure of which has been by better Judgments than mine account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not much
inferiour to moſt of that kind. It was written Originally in
<hi>Spaniſh</hi> by an Honourable Perſonage, who though he yielded to the
importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſome Friends (as the Publiſher tell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) to let it be made Publick, yet how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever excellent in
its kind, he thought it unworthy of bearing his Name. It was no ſooner
publiſh'd, but it was received with ſo general an applauſe in
<hi>Spaniſh,</hi> that an ingenious <hi>Frenchman</hi> thought it worthy not
onely of his Tranſlation,<pb facs="tcp:175400:4"/>but alſo many Learned Annotations upon
ſeveral Particulars of it, with Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from many of the beſt Authors
both Ancient and Modern, which I have here omitted, as (I think) too ſerious
for the Subject. I am confident thou wilt find it very perfectly pleaſant as
to the ſubſtance, however thou diſlikeſt the meanneſs of my Style.
But if thou findeſt it not ingenious enough to pleaſe thee, I hope thou
maiſt find cauſe to laugh at me for ſpending my time ſo badly; and ſo
either way I have my end.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:175400:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175400:5"/>
            <head>THE AMOROUS TRAVELLERS, OR THE
<hi>Night-Adventures.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>PART I.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He pleaſant Month of <hi>April</hi> had already en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched
the ſpacious Plains with ſo flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing a Tapeſtry, that the Earth
(like a half-ſtarved Beggar, grown proud by new Preferment) being now freed
from a rigorous Winter, ſeemed to vie Glory with the Heavens themſelves,
whether the multitudes of Stars of the one, or the abundance of Violets,
Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlips,<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175400:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Jeſſamins, and other
various-coloured Flowers of the Seaſon, of the other, ſhould caſt the
more delightful lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre: And however the Stars might chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge a greater
glory by night, yet in this the Earth had by day a greater advantage over their
nocturnal beauty, that to her o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rarities, ſhe had uſually though not
ſo many Stars as the Heavens, yet to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal eyes thoſe that were far more
fair; I mean the ſparkling Eyes of thoſe Troops of Ladies that daily
frequented the Fields, attended by their Lovers, for the pleaſure of the
Walks. The Chryſtal Rivulets (enamel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with thouſands of delightful
Flowers that overſpread the Banks) ſeemed to ſtop their courſes to
enjoy the delightful Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick of the Nightingal, and the agreeable Harmony of
other little Birds. Already <hi>Flora,</hi> and ſhe to whom the
<hi>Romans</hi> attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted the <hi>Cornucopia,</hi> had gilded and paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with admirable induſtry the Plains and Gardens, the Fruit-trees and Orchards,
and that with a greater variety of Colours than ever adorned the Landſchape
of the skilfulleſt Painter; When one day as the dawning begun to adviſe the
ſluggiſh Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller that the Light which entred his<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175400:6"/>Chamber proceeded from the approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sun, and not from the declining
Moon, there parted from <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>beda,</hi> a Town of that part of the ſo
fertile and renowned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Betica</hi> which is now called
<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daluzia,</hi> a Cavalier, the moſt ſignal of that Town, to go to the
Court of <hi>Philip</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond at <hi>Madrid,</hi> to receive the Order
of the Golden Fleece, to which the Merits and Services of his Anceſtors had
intitled him, reſolving not to leave the Court without that honourable Badge:
And knowing that Court-pretenſions are uſually accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with tedious
delays, he thought it would conduce to the paſſing more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly the
time which he muſt needs beſtow on that purſuit, to carry along his Wife
and Family with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> (ſo was this Cavalier cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) had
not yet attained the 25 year of his age; a man of ſo excellent a Meen, and
every way ſo compleat in all the Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments that render a Cavalier
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, that had he not been too much inclined to the <hi>Cyprian</hi>
ſports, his ſevereſt Enemies could ſcarce have found in him one ſole
default, or the leaſt defect.</p>
               <p>All theſe Graces and rare Perfections,<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175400:7"/>joyned
to an ample Revenue, which his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents (lately deceaſed) had left him,
quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put him in poſſeſſion of a Wife, for Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments,
Riches, and Noble Deſcent every way his equal. Beſides, <hi>Donna
Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gareta</hi> (ſo was ſhe called) was Miſtris of an incomparable
Beauty, compounded of all the moſt admired graces and ſweet atracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
which placed her in the chief rank of all the Ladies of <hi>Andaluzia;</hi> and
ſo young, that ſhe had not yet ſeen the 17 year of her age, nor the
ſecond of her marriage. Yet could not all theſe ſweets and rarities
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi>'s ranging humour, whoſe depraved appetite
often quitted his own pure White-bread, to feed on that whoſe courſe
out-ſide and unſavoury taſte would offend the moſt hungry Beggar; which
cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this poor Lady to paſs her time very diſcontentedly, wanting
thoſe Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which her Youth deſired, and Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deſerved,
ſince her unjuſt and diſoyal Husband unworthily beſtowed on others what
was juſtly due to none but her, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving her alone to deplore in her own Bed
the want of thoſe Satisfactions which he enjoyed in anothers.</p>
               <p>This young Couple in their Journey had<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175400:7"/>already
paſſed the high and rugged Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Sierra Morena,</hi> when the
Horſes finding themſelves in an even Plain, began to go ſo chearfully,
and draw the Coach ſo ſwiftly, though heavy loaden, that they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at
<hi>Viſo</hi> before Sun-ſet. The Coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were deſirous to paſs
further, but <hi>Donna Margareta</hi>'s delicate Body, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with Travel,
and diſordered by the jogging of the Coach, made her deſirous to ſtay
there. They therefore alighted from the Coach, and the Coachmen and Attendants
having diſpoſed of their Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, and given Meat to their Horſes
(being acquainted with the Hoſt by often travelling that way) ſaw the
Chambers made ready, and gave order for Supper, which was quickly prepared for
the Table, becauſe all that was neceſſary they brought along with them
(as is the cuſtom in <hi>Spain</hi> (or ought to be ſo) amongſt thoſe
that are not ambitious to be famiſh'd.)</p>
               <p>Whilſt the Spit was turning, and the Cloth laying, <hi>Donna
Margareta</hi> was enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining her ſelf with her Waiting-maids about the
exceſſive height of the Mountains of that Countrey, painting them out more
prodigious than thoſe of <hi>Armenia.</hi> Her<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175400:8"/>Husband, on
the other ſide, was diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a wondrous fair Niece of the
Hoſt, not, as ſome may imagine of Affairs of State, or the Siege of
<hi>Oſtend,</hi> but only of ſome ſtratagem how to paſs the enſuing
night together in leſs dangerous Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. The young Girl defended her
ſelf againſt his Aſſaults, by telling him, That ſhe was but newly
married, and that her Husband, who was then in the Countrey, might, for ought
ſhe knew, return that night. Theſe words, though ſeeming ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles,
ſo inflamed our Cavalier, that he was abſolutely determined, or rather
tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted by his paſſion, to a reſolution never to give over the
Aſſault till he had won the Fort, and brought the Maintainer of it to yield
at diſcretion. Finally, it was appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our two Warriors to meet at the
Field of Battel, the Bed of the abſent Husband, at eleven a clock at night,
which would be the time when all others in the Houſe would be retired to
their Lodgings.</p>
               <p>The appointment thus made, <hi>Don Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> went to his
Wifes Chamber, who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him enter with ſo pleaſant a look, ask'd him
whence he came. He, who in ſuch occaſions never wanted Excuſes to conceal
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175400:8"/>his Vices, anſwered (as confidently as a Comedian that is
perfect in his Part) I was hearing ſome News which a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man newly come
from Court was talking of below; and really he did it with ſo good a grace,
that if a Cavalier which came to ſee him had not interrupted him, I would not
for any thing in the World have loſt the end of the Narration, I took ſuch
delight to hear him diſcourſe. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee, my Dear (ſaid <hi>Donna
Margareta</hi>) tell me what he talk'd of, whilſt Supper is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ready.
There's no time for that, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered a Page (as opportunely as if he had been
expreſly called for that purpoſe) for 'tis juſt ready; and, if you
pleaſe, we will ſerve it up preſently. Well, let us go to Supper, ſaid
<hi>Don Sebaſtian;</hi> we ſhall have time enough for this Story to
morrow.</p>
               <p>They ſate down, and fell to. <hi>Catalina</hi> (for ſo for
the future we ſhall call the Hoſts fair Niece) waited at the Table, and the
better to conceal her paſſion, had her eyes for the moſt part fixed on
the earth, leſt their motion ſhould betray her affection; and the force of
imagination of her intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed delights ſtruck ſuch an impreſſion upon
her ſpirit, that ſhe even melted like the<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175400:9"/>Snow by the heat
of the Sun; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times caſting her eyes upon <hi>Donna Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reta,</hi>
and ſeeing her endowed with ſo charming a Beauty, ſhe could not but ſay
within her ſelf, Alas! my deareſt Friend, I fear I ſhall miſs the
enjoyment of thee this night; for vanquiſh'd with the ſweet Careſſes of
ſo ſovereign a Beauty, how canſt thou chuſe but paſs it (like the Elm
embraced by the amorous Vine) claſped in thoſe lovely Arms?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> was in like diſtreſs, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
by ſtealth caſting amorous glances at <hi>Catalina;</hi> and ſometimes he
forgot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo far, that he could not poſſibly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his eyes
from ſo charming an object: And indeed there is no cauſe to wonder at his
aſtoniſhment; for <hi>Catalina</hi> was for Beauty an invaluable Pearl, and
her black Eyes ſo lively and ſparkling, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection caſt by a
Looking-glaſs ſwiftly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved againſt the Sun, had not a quicker mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
than they, when ſhe ſometimes moved them. Finally, ſhe was compleatly
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the purpoſe for which <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> deſigned
her.</p>
               <p>The Table-diſcourſe ended with the Supper; for <hi>Don
Sebaſtian</hi> counterfeiting<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175400:9"/>the falſe Sentinel, nodded,
and ſeveral times let fall a Book he held in his hand, 
<note n="*" place="margin">Naturalliſts obſerve, that when a
Flock of Cranes would ſleep ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely, one of them is ſet Sentinel, which
leſt ſhe ſhould be ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>prized
by ſleep, ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds vp a ſtone as
high as ſhe can with her foot.</note>like a Crane overcome by ſleep.
<hi>Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Margareta</hi> taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi>'s
drowſineſs, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that he had told her he intended to be early up
in the morning, thought fit to mind him of going to bed. <hi>Don
Sebaſtian</hi> no ſooner heard that, but he anſwered her, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from
his Chair, Go thou to bed, my Dear, and I'le but go down to my Coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and
Grooms, to bid them retire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, becauſe we muſt be ſtirring very
early in the morning, that we may be at <hi>Cividad Real</hi> betimes to
morrow; and I'le be with thee preſently. Having ſpoke to his Servants, he
found means to ſpeak with <hi>Catalina,</hi> and entertain himſelf with her
a while: Which done, having appointed an Hour, and ſhe ſhown him her
Chamber, he returned to his own, where he found his Wife already laid. Being
unclothed, he diſmiſs'd the Attendants, ſhut the Door, and went to bed,
where he was no ſooner laid, but he feigned as profound a ſleep, as 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175400:10"/>if he had watch'd a fortnight together with a ſick
perſon. This ſudden ſurrender to Sleeps aſſaults was not very
pleaſing to his Wife, who perhaps expected a more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Good-night; but
ſhe knew his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour ſo well, that to approach nearer him would rather
offend him than advantage her; ſo that the fear of diſpleaſing him
accommodating her preſent deſire to her future hopes, that the morning
would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore her what the evenings drowſineſs had deprived her of, in
this agreeable imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſleep ſlided ſo gently into her fair eyes,
that it kept her as faſt bound, (though in gentler chains) as if ſhe had
been captive to his younger Brother Death. There were no other Strangers this
Night in the Inn (though one of the beſt in the Countrey) but <hi>Don
Sebaſtian</hi> and his Train, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the Family to be in bed
before ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, there in a pleaſant repoſe paying the Tribute due to
Nature. The beauteous <hi>Catalina</hi> lay liſtning more attentively, to
hear if her beloved <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> knocked at her Door, than a ſick
Perſon when the Phyſician near his Beds head pronounceth to ſome of his
Friends or Kindred the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of his Life or Death: Nor would a 
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175400:10"/>benighted Traveller undergo a greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietude in a
tedious expectation of Day, in which only he could be delivered from an abyſs
of dangers with which he ſees himſelf invironed, than ſhe ſuffered in
her languiſhing expectation. But ſhe had no cauſe to deſpair, having
ſo diligent a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant as <hi>Don Sebaſtian,</hi> who leaving his Wife,
with a face more ſerene and lovely than <hi>Aurora,</hi> opened the Door with
as little noiſe as was poſſible, and (like a certain Thief, who going one
night to rob his Neighbour's Houſe, left open the Door of his own, through
which ſome of his own Profeſſion entred, and ſtole away all he had
worth carrying) leaving it open, march'd away ſo gently, that the Floor could
ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feel him. Being arrived at his Miſtriſſes Chamber-door, he
call'd her as low as was poſſible, and inſtantly felt it opened and
himſelf embraced by her. He ſtaid not long to recount the cuſtomary
amorous follies of Lovers, for the exquiſite plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure he felt prevented
him; nor could he have done it if he had gone about it, for the multitude of
raviſhing kiſſes and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces which our new-married <hi>Catalina</hi>
gave him: Therefore taking her in his <pb n="12" facs="tcp:175400:11"/>arms, without ever
removing his lips from hers, they both went to bed together. But let us leave
them here, to ſpeak of that which my Pen has been a great while de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous
to write.</p>
               <p>About half an hour after our Cavalier had left his Wife for
another Man's, one of his Pages, about 18 years old, and as beauteous as
<hi>Narciſſus,</hi> roſe from his Bed to make water; but wanting a Pot,
and being half aſleep, and not knowing where to do it without leaving a mark
of his unmanner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, to contradict the common opinion of the World, which
without reſpect of any, though of the moſt civilized ſort, will not allow
any of them to have the leaſt ſhare either of civility or good manners, he
went down to the Court-yard, and there ſatisfying Nature's neceſſity,
made it appear, that he ſurpaſſed his Camerades in good Breeding.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> had his Appartment in a great Gallery
of the Houſe, into which three Chambers opened: In the third, as being the
beſt, he lay himſelf, and his Wife; in the ſecond, the Pages; and in the
firſt, the Waiting-maids; and in the other Chambers in the Inn, being of
leſs conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175400:11"/>lay the ordinary Servants. The Page
having diſpatch'd his affairs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to his Bed, being ſcarce
fully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, miſtook his Miſtriſſes Chamber for his own, and after he
had groped by the Walls a good while for the Bed, he at laſt found it, and
lay down. He had not been long there, but <hi>Donna Margareta</hi> awaked at
the ruſtling he had made amongſt the Clothes as he lay down; and thinking
it had been her Husband, ſhe embraced him cloſely, ſaying, Lord, my Dear,
how cold thou art! And then putting her Feet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt his to warm them, made
him a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Careſſes. The Page thought his Camerade had been in a
Dream, and had done and ſaid theſe extravagances fancying himſelf in bed
with a Girl; but feeling her hands by degrees approaching the moſt
ſenſible parts of his Body, with more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant enticements than that
Goddeſs (of whom the <hi>Cytherean</hi> Iſle has taken its name) uſed to
her <hi>Adonis,</hi> and hearing theſe words, Turn thee to me, Deareſt, and
be not ſo cruel to me as to refuſe me thy em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces: Wilt thou not, my
Love? Alas! what's the reaſon? At this Diſcourſe the Page found he was
deceived, and that ſhe<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175400:12"/>that made him thoſe tender
careſſes, and cloſe embraces, was his Miſtris.</p>
               <p>He remained at firſt almoſt dead with fear; but having
recollected his ſpirits, he imagined how the caſe ſtood, having ſeen
the night before the amorous and wanton careſſes which paſſed betwixt
his Maſter and <hi>Catalina.</hi> She asked him whence he came; but he held
his peace, hoping that when ſhe perceived he made no anſwer, ſhe would
fall aſleep again, and give him an opportunity to ſteal out of the Chamber.
But her mind being wholly bent upon plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, in ſtead of moderating the
exceſs of her amorous paſſion, gave her freſh tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and thoſe
ſo piquant, that being not able to reſiſt the violence of their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour,
ſhe redoubled her amorous entice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to our ſuppoſed <hi>Don
Sebaſtian;</hi> who being heated with theſe delicious tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, began
to move, like a frozen Snake laid to a Fire: And indeed had it been a Marble
Statue, or a <hi>Timon Miſanthropos,</hi> ſworn Enemy to all Man and
Woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, being embraced by thoſe lovely Arms more white than Alabaſter,
kiſſed by Lips more freſh and ruddy than the Roſe or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and enticed
by Words ſweeter than<pb n="15" facs="tcp:175400:12"/>Honey, it had been enought to
infuſe Life into the former, and make the later for the preſent ſuſpend
his hatred, and be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to ſo fair an Enemy.</p>
               <p>So this young man, who had ſo often ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired his
Miſtriſſes Beauty, finding himſelf now ſo near her, that a
<hi>Lynx</hi> his eyes would have been puzzled to diſtinguiſh whether they
were one ſole Body or two conjoyned, without any more delay ſhut his eyes
to the injury he did his Maſter, in enriching himſelf with the richeſt
Jewel he poſſeſt, turning to her, kiſſed ſometimes her Alabaſter
Neck, ſometimes her ſnowie Breaſts, and ſometimes her Lips more red
than Coral, without being able to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh which of them gave him the
more delightful taſte, and raviſhing content: upon which ſhe whiſpered
him, If thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt to give me life, and all ſorts of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments
with it, let us proceed to the conſummation of our Loves. Who now could be
ſo far inſenſible, even beyond the dulneſs of Lead or Stone, who
ſeeing ſo extraordinary and raviſhing a Beauty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his Suppliant,
would not have imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated this our Freſh-water-Soldier, in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what ſhe
deſired. The more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175400:13"/>ſtrict embraces,
ſomewhat beyond thoſe of her Husband; the reiterated kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and
wanton geſtures, which of a long time paſt he had given over in thoſe
affairs, wrought ſome confuſion in our <hi>Donna Margareta,</hi> and a
violent ſuſpicion of her miſtake. The Page at that preſent, after the
act, found himſelf ſo afflicted with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of what might
enſue, that he could not but fancy his Maſter's Poniard in his Throat, for
a reward of his good Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. To diſcover himſelf to his Miſtris, and
beg her pardon, he durſt not; and to ſteal away without her knowledge, he
was afraid ſhe might diſcover it in the morning by ſome innocent raillery
with her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band upon the paſſages of that night, and by that means
unwittingly diſcover that, which could not come into open air with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his
Life to accompany it. Theſe fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful apprehenſions did ſo perplex his
ſoul, that it was an even wager whether his paſt pleaſure or preſent
fear were greater, till the former found means to diſſipate the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by
the invention of this following Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Donna Margareta</hi> had a Waiting-woman for Beauty and
Parts much exceeding moſt<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175400:13"/>of her rank, who had a moſt
ſignal love for this Page, whoſe gratitude joyned with her merits, wrought
in him a reciprocal affection, teſtified by his careſſes to her, the
moſt endearing his fancy or affection could afford. Their Maſter had had
intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of theſe Amours, who being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to keep his Family clear
of ſuch Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (though you cannot but find how ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligent he was to begin
with himſelf) had under the ſtricteſt penalties forbidden the continuance
of this familiarity, or a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther privity in their Amours, ſuſpecting
their deſigns in thoſe affairs to tend to the ſame end with his.
<hi>Valerio</hi> (ſo was our Page called) endeavouring to cloke this
preſent fault by one which was already but too well known, would undeceive
his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris in that affair, which would be the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of them both if
diſcovered to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter by her ignorance; and finding her more than
ordinarily aſtoniſh'd, and altogether ſilent, embracing her more
ſtraitly than before, he firſt broke ſilence, ſpeaking to her as if he
had meant it to another.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>I durſt never hope, deareſt <hi>Chimena,</hi> (this was
the Girl's name) ſo happy a reception from thee, ſearing that our 
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175400:14"/>Maſter's threats had ere this rooted out of thy heart all
the affection there plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for me: But ſince I ſee thy affection ſo
immovable (ſaid he, and ſealed it with a kiſs) believe me, my dear Soul,
that if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs could purchaſe thy embraces than the paſſing a
more dangerous Straight than that which <hi>Leander</hi> ſtemm'd to enjoy his
beloved <hi>Hero,</hi> the reward I receive in poſſeſſing thee, would
make the attempt the moſt inconſiderable thing imaginable. But what is the
mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (ſaid he again, reiterating his kiſſes) my deareſt Life? Why
art thou ſilent? Or whence proceeds this aſtoniſhment? Knoweſt thou not
that thy Companion, though ſhe may perhaps have eſpied our ſecrets, is
the faithful Secretary of our Amours, and would as ſoon die as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
them. On the other ſide, our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, altogether ignorant of what has
paſſed, now finds himſelf happy in the enjoyment of that lovely Girl thou
ſaweſt wait at Table the laſt night. As for our Miſtris, there is no
fear of her, who, poor Lady, is at preſent faſt aſleep, little
ſuſpecting the Treaſon of her ingrateful Husband.</q> With theſe and
ſuch like<pb n="19" facs="tcp:175400:14"/>words, often interrupted by the kiſſes and
embraces he gave her, without leaving any part of her lovely face untouched by
his lips, ſhe eaſily found this was not her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. At theſe laſt
words the poor Lady remained more aſtoniſhed at her Husbands miſcarriage
and her own misfortune, than <hi>Alcmena</hi> of old, when <hi>Jupiter</hi> had
enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her under the form of <hi>Amphitryo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſeeing there was no remedy, and that if by ſo ſtrange
an accident ſhe had broken her faith and bonds of Marriage, the fault lay not
on her ſide, but that all ought to be imputed to her Husband, to whom God
would give the juſt chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his ſin by the ſame means by
which he offended others; ſhe then taking a Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant from her ear, which
ſhe had forgot to lay by at her going to bed, put it in his hand, ſaying as
low as ſhe could, Take this Pendant, bold young man, by which to morrow
morning thou wilt perceive the Treaſon thou haſt acted againſt thy
Maſter. Upon this the Page, without reply, left her Chamber to haſten to
his own, where ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving, without being ſeen by any one, he ſhut the door
after him, and (void of thoſe joys or fears he found with his former
Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow)<pb n="20" facs="tcp:175400:15"/>laid down by his Camerade, who had ſlept all
the while like a Dormouſe; his joy being thus doubly augmented, by the
thoughts of having enjoyed ſo eminent a Beauty, and avoided ſo evident a
danger, like a Slave, who in ſtead of undergoing a miſerable Captivity till
the payment of his Ranſom, finds his Liberty advantageouſly reſtored, by
the augmentation of a maſs of Treaſure. And what more immenſe riches, or
more grand felicity could one imagine, to give ſo complete a ſatisfaction
to a Youth of the age of our fortunate <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerio,</hi> than the ſweet
embraces of ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete a Beauty as our <hi>Donna Margareta?</hi> Alſo
this ſpruce young Blade, being of an excellent humour, did acknowledge the
incomparable engagement he had to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune for ſo ſignal a favour, and
forgetting the peril he before endured, he would willingly have dared the Rocks
and Waves in the ſame Veſſel in which his Heart was now embarked, if he
could but promiſe himſelf to find another ſo favourable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Donna Margareta</hi> conſidering <hi>Valerio</hi>'s ready
wit and comely ſtature, his beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous complexion and admirable diſcretion,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:175400:15"/>was ſo far from being diſpleaſed at what was paſt,
that ſhe preferr'd her Revenge far before her Honour, rejoycing that ſhe
had thus quitted ſcores with her faithleſs Husband, whom ſhe attended
every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But ſeeing the Captain of her Fort came not, ſhe accuſed
her own indiſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for having diſmiſs'd ſo valiant a Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
who was now endeavouring to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruit by a profound ſleep the ſtrength he
had loſt in his former ſervice.</p>
               <p>Let us leave him ſleeping, and her alſo to vail her
ſparkling eyes with her lovely eye-lids; and let us return to our <hi>Don
Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtian,</hi> who in the mean time ſuffers under a Bed miſeries enough
to balance the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures he had enjoyed upon it, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons you
ſhall underſtand in the enſuing Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:175400:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DOn Sebaſtian</hi> had not yet paſs'd two hours with his
beauteous <hi>Catalina,</hi> but her Husband came knocking at the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gaie
of the Inn, cloſe by the Stables, which was too far from his Wifes
Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber for the noiſe to approach her ears. He did not knock there long;
for the Oſtler who lay over the Stable heard him the firſt ſtroke, and
had let him in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he needed to make a ſecond. Being entred, he only took
off his Portmanteau, and recommended his Horſe to the Oſtlers care, and
taking a Candle, went directly to his Wifes Chamber, where our two Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers were
bound in ſtronger chains than thoſe that enſnated <hi>Mars</hi> and the
Queen of Love. He knocked twice or thrice at the door; but the Wife, who was
juſt then in the height of her ſpeed at her delicious exerciſe, was not
at leiſure to anſwer him, but, like a Woman of good forecaſt in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,
reſolved not to begin another, till ſhe had finiſh'd what ſhe was
about: At laſt hearing the <hi>Open the door,</hi> and knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings 
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:175400:16"/>againſt it ſhowr like Hail, making as if ſhe had been
newly awaked from a ſound ſleep, ſhe anſwered, in words pronounc'd like
one half aſleep, half waking, Who is there? 'Tis I, ſaid the Husband. Who
are you, quoth <hi>Catalina?</hi> 'Tis I, I tell thee, replied
<hi>Roderigo</hi> (that was his name) haſt thou forgot me? Theſe laſt
words ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred her more certain who was at the door, than able to open it,
every ſyllable being a Dagger which ſeem'd to pierce as deep into her heart
as her ears; and all ſhe could then think on to ſave her ſelf and <hi>Don
Sebaſtian,</hi> was to make him ſeek his ſafety under that Bed upon which
he had ſo lately enjoyed ſo much delight: And then ſeeming to be
throughly awake, ſhe anſwered, O <hi>Roderigo,</hi> my dear heart, thou art
happily arrived; ſtay but a while, till I riſe. This while <hi>Don
Sebaſtian</hi> had time to get under the Bed; but with ſuch ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and
aſtoniſhment, that he forgot his Cloke that lay upon the Table.</p>
               <p>She opening the door, her Husband en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, who intending to
ſhew her ſome Toys he had bought her, laid his Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manteau upon the Table,
which he ſeeing furniſh'd with other things, went to clear 
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:175400:17"/>it, that he might have more room to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplay his Ware,
where, by misfortune, the firſt thing he laid hands on was the Cloke.</p>
               <p>The Wiſe conſidering the extreme dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger which her Friends
negligence had brought upon them both, if not remedied by her, her ingenuity
quickly infuſed into her this ſudden effort of female ſubtilty: I dare
wager, ſaid ſhe, I have left ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing there; and coming nearer, and
ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Cloke, ſhe begun to croſs her ſelf infinitely, ſaying Lord,
Lord! was there ever ſuch a Sot as I, to leave that there ſo openly! If any
one but you had entred, I had paid dear for my negligence. The Husband amazed
at his Wifes aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and croſſing her ſelf in that manner, (as
if his Horns had made her take him for a Devil) ſaid to her, What means this
Cloke, and all this ado? I'le tell thee (ſaid the ſubtle Gypſie): But
ſtay, continued ſhe, opening the door and looking out, let us be ware that
none hears us; and ſhutting it again ſhe began as followeth.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>Doſt thou not remember a Cavalier that lay here a while ago
on his way to <hi>Sevil?</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <q>What Cavalier, ſaid he?</q> 
                  <q>A <pb n="25" facs="tcp:175400:17"/>young Gentleman, ſaid ſhe, which was
here about a Month ago, in a Tawney Cloth Sure embroidered with Gold, mounted
upon a Bay Horſe, with a laced Saddle, with gilded Bit and Stirrops.</q> 
                  <q>I have forgot, ſaid he.</q> 
                  <q>Lord, ſaid ſhe, what a memory haſt thou! I'le lay thee a
Wager I'le make thee call him to mind.</q> And thereupon opening her Trunk,
ſhe took out a Silver Cup which her Husband had ſtole from that Cavaliers
Butler which ſhe ſpoke of, and ſhewing it him, ſaid, 
<q>The Maſter of this Cup is he I mean of.</q> 
                  <q>Oh, oh, ſaid he, I remember him now.</q> 
                  <q>This ſame Cavalier, ſaid ſhe, paſſed this way again
about eight days ago, with all his Train; and becauſe it grew late, and the
weather was very rainy, he was conſtrained to take up here: and as ſoon as
they were lighted, every one fell to untruſſing their Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage: But one of
the Cavaliers being troubled to get off his Portmanteau, by reaſon of a hard
knot on the Cord that tied it, laid by his Cloke upon a Bench in the Yard, that
he might the better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do the knot: So having untied and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it off, he gave
his Horſe to an Oſtler,<pb n="26" facs="tcp:175400:18"/>and went in with his
Portmanteau, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting his Cloke. I, who watch'd him carefully hard by,
eſpying his negligence, ſeeing the Coaſt clear, went and ſnatch'd up
the Cloke, and lock'd it up ſo cloſe that none has ſeen it ſince. There
came in immediately after a Parcel of Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ſo many others with
them, that the Houſe was filled in an inſtant.</q>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <q>About an hour after, this Cavalier remembring the Cloke,
returned to ſeek it at the place where he had left it; but to no more
purpoſe than to ſeek a grain of Muſtard-ſeed in a great heap of Stones
at midnight, or a Bird after ſhe has left her Neſt. It was to no purpoſe
to curſe or complain; for I had laid it up ſafe enough, and hearing him
inquire for it, told him, it was to ſmall purpoſe to look for it now, for
if he had left it there, he might be ſure it was ſtole be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time,
And he conſidering how hard it was now to retrive it, there ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been ſo
many People there paſſing to and again, returned to his Chamber, and
confeſſed by his ſilence that he could blame none but himſelf, and ſo
abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it to the Thieve's mercy. In fine, I<pb n="27" facs="tcp:175400:18"/>have kept it
here cloſe lock'd up ever ſince, till this evening, that, as I was going to
bed, I took it out, the better to come at thy clean Linen and beſt Clothes,
which I have laid thee there ready againſt to morrow, thinking thou
wouldeſt not fail to return to night, and I was ſo heedleſs to forget to
put it up again; and now I warrant thou'lt go ſell it, as thou haſt done
other things, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving me a ſhare (ſaid ſhe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
frowning)</q> and ſo concluded her well-framed Lie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Roderigo</hi> fell a laughing heartily at theſe words, and
as one that would not have ſpared it at ſuch an opportunity, though the
Bench had been an Altar, ſaid to her very jocundly, There's no need to take
care to provide for thee, that haſt ſuch tricks to ſhift for thy ſelf.
By my faith, this Cloke might become <hi>S. George</hi> himſelf: We'll ſell
it, and part the money betwixt us. And turning about to ſee that none heard
him, Upon my ſoul, ſaid he, the Cloke's as well worth twenty Crowns, as a
Thief's worth a Rope: But tell me one thing, for God's ſake, Does thy Uncle
know nothing of this? My Uncle, ſaid ſhe, with a Pox<pb n="28" facs="tcp:175400:19"/>to
him, didſt thou think me ſuch a fool? If he had known of it, he would not
have been contented under half ſhare. That's well, ſaid <hi>Roderigo;</hi>
for I do not intend him a Penny of it, by my good will: And to morrow I intend
to go ſell it either at <hi>Sante Cruz</hi> or <hi>Almagro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> hearing <hi>Catalina</hi>'s ſubtily,
than which nothing elſe could have avert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the preſent danger, was well
contented with the loſs of his Cloke, and would willingly it were worth
thrice as much, and the Husband gone to ſell it, as he ſaid, upon condition
he were delivered from the preſent danger, which had not put him into ſo
great a heat at firſt, but he found himſelf now ſufficiently cold, by
lying all along in his Shirt upon the ground, which, though not much his
friend, yet made him almoſt think he ſhould ſcarce ever part from it
alive.</p>
               <p>See here to what perils they expoſe themſelves, who
forſaking God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing his Commandments, launch out from that
ſafe Harbour, into the tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sea of unchaſte Love. What
<hi>Damon</hi> guided this Cavalier to neglect the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Lady that
might vie Beauty with<pb n="29" facs="tcp:175400:19"/>
                  <hi>Venus,</hi> Wit with
<hi>Minerva,</hi> and Chaſtity (had not he been Bawd to his own diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour)
with <hi>Diana,</hi> which added to his other enjoyments were enough to
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete all worldly felicity, infringing the ſacred Law of Marriage made by
the great Lawgiver in <hi>Eden,</hi> and whoſe bounty had ſo amply rewarded
him with ſuch pleaſure in the performance, to follow with the hazard of
Soul, Body, and Reputation, theſe unclean pleaſures, which were by God
forbidden upon pain of damnation. Vain man! As if the diſpleaſure of God
that precedes, the dangers that accompany, and that repentance that ſucceeds
this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit, were the only advantage for which thou preferr'ſt it
above the lawful. But to proceed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Roderigo</hi> having done talking with his Wife, was going
to uncloath himſelf for bed, there to paſs the five Hours yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining
betwixt then and morning; but ſhe foreſeeing how hard it would be for her
to open the door, or the poor Cavalier to paſs out through it undiſcovered,
was forced to bethink her ſelf of another ſhift, to give him a more certain
Paſſport from his preſent Purgatory, which was as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:175400:20"/>O, my dear, (ſaid the ſubtle
<hi>Catalina</hi>) I had forgot to tell thee I could have given thee a taſte
of the moſt excellent <hi>Rabadabia.</hi> Wine that ever thou haſt ſeen
or taſted; and that thou maiſt judge whether I give it too large an Eulogy,
before thou putteſt off thy Clothes go down into the Kitchen, where thoul't
find a Bottle of it, and a Partridge Leg upon a Pewter Plate. And whence comes
all this Good Cheer, ſaid he? A Cavaliers Lady, ſaid ſhe, that lies in
the Houſe ſent it me laſt night at Supper. And is there no body come with
her, ſaid he? Why doſt thou ask, replied the Wife? Why? becauſe (ſaid
he) thou ſpeakeſt of her only, as though ſhe were come by her ſelf.
Why, ſaid ſhe, what occaſion had I to ſpeak of him, ſince I had
nothing to do with him, but the Wife, in this Diſcourſe? But what need all
theſe words about no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? 'Tis becauſe I conſidered with my ſelf
(ſaid the Husband) that if ſhe had been alone, it might be worth my time to
try my fortune with her. What fortune ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou think to find there,
Blockhead, ſaid <hi>Catalina,</hi> but at the firſt extravagance thou
ſhouldeſt begin to utter to her, her Nails ſhould make thy Eyes pay for
thy<pb n="31" facs="tcp:175400:20"/>Tongues impertinence; and to make up the full payment of
thy impudence, make her Servants reward thee with a Baſtinado? Fair and
ſoftly, good <hi>Catalina</hi> (replied <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derigo</hi>) if the Cuckold
her Husband were by, he durſt not take this privilege. Good Lord, (ſaid the
Wife) I am afraid that ill Tongue of thine will ſome time give the reſt of
thy Body cauſe to curſe it: But hold, what noiſe is that? Pox take him
(ſaid <hi>Roderigo</hi>) 'tis an Oyl-ſeller; the wide-throated Dog makes
ſuch a noiſe, that I fancy his very words ſpoil all my Clothes: As God
judge me, if I catch him again in the Street diſturbing the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at this
time of night, I'le—but I'le ſay no more; for this long Diſcourſe,
and the remembrance of this Divine Liquor have wrought ſuch an alteration in
my Throat, that if the Bottle come not quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it had as good ſtay away
till Doomſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day. Thou wert beſt go take it preſently then, ſaid ſhe;
but I wiſh it be ſcaped from the roguiſh Boy that help'd to wait laſt
night, for he loves Wine as he does his Life, and is as ravenous as a Wolf; and
if it be there now, and remain till morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he'l be as ſure to be at it
then, as I<pb n="32" facs="tcp:175400:21"/>ſhall be to go to Maſs on <hi>Sunday.</hi>
But I'le prevent him, if it be poſſible (ſaid the Husband) for before God
I have more need on't my ſelf; for beſides my thirſt, it is above ſix
months ſince I have taſted any of it, which does juſtly bear a greater
price than any other in <hi>Spain.</hi> And as he was talking on in this
manner, he was ſtooping down to look for a Slipper which was ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded under
the Beds-feet amongſt ſome Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements that lay there; but he could not
find it without a Candle, and was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore going to take one off from the
Table. <hi>Catalina</hi> ſeeing her ſelf upon the brink of Perdition,
without a ſudden invention, leap'd quickly out of the Bed, and ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
haſtily the Candle out of his hand, ſaid, Is't poſſible thou canſt
not find a Slipper under half an hours time? and looking about the Table,
removed the things that lay there, to ſee if ſhe could find it.
<hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derigo</hi> vexed to ſee his Wife run bare-foot round the Room, ſaid
to her in a fury, God's my life, I think thou'rt beſides thy ſelf; what
needeſt thou to come out of the Bed, and then to run about bare-foot thus?
Thou haſt a mind to get a Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that will coſt us all we have to
cure. <pb n="33" facs="tcp:175400:21"/>Get thee to Bed, and trouble thy ſelf no further; I
hope in God my eyes are good enough yet to find a Slipper without the help of
thine.</p>
               <p>What caſe <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> was then in, he that hath
ever been in like dangerous exigents may eaſily imagine; for undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, if
<hi>Catalina</hi> as ſhe went had not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſtumble at the
Portmanteau, and thrown down the Candle at the inſtant her Husband demanded
it to look under the Bed, all had been irreparably loſt, beyond the help of
her crafts and ſubtilties.</p>
               <p>Whilſt the Husband in a rage was taking up the Candleſtick
and Candle, <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina</hi> coming to the Bed, put her Arm un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to grope
for the Slipper, and catch'd <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> by the Foot, who thinking
it had been her Husband, was ready to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take himſelf to his laſt remedy,
and with a Poniard he had brought along with him force his paſſage from
that danger through the Heart of <hi>Roderigo;</hi> but hearing no words from
them that touch'd him, it wrought a calmer reſolve in him: ſo that
<hi>Catalina</hi> having found the Slipper, gave it to her Husband with a
thouſand Curſes, which were not all capable to do it ſo 
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:175400:22"/>much miſchief as it had like to have done her.
<hi>Roderigo</hi> had by this time taken up the Candle and Candleſtick, and
proffer'd them ſeveral times to the Devil (if he had had the manners to
accept them) for lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him in the dark. The Wife too, being laid down again,
asked him whether he was a fool or bewitch'd, that had not the wit to go light
it again. He then ask'd her if there were any Fire in the Kitchen. What an
impertinent queſtion is that (ſaid ſhe?) Didſt thou ever know it
without? So <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derigo</hi> went ſtraight thither to light his Candle. He
was no ſooner gone, but <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talina</hi> leap'd out of the Bed, to conduct
her Lover from under it; who being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, ſtaid there no longer but to
take his laſt leave of her: And though the cold had almoſt taken away his
ſenſes, he found himſelf the moſt overjoyed man in the world, being
delivered from ſo ſtraight and naſty a Priſon, though carrying along
with him more Gnats and Fleas on his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, than Hairs on his Head, enough to
ſtock an Hoſpital; and carrying along a ſtink of Piſs ſufficient to
infect the Air about him; and withal ſo pale and ſhive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that he was
more like a diſmal Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition<pb n="35" facs="tcp:175400:22"/>than a Man, ſo
intolerable was the torture he had undergone for the ſpace of two Hours or
thereabouts: But all theſe miſchiefs were eaſily amended by the help of a
little repoſe, and therefore no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing comparable to that of the Page, which
was for ever irreparable. Finding himſelf in this eſtate, it went againſt
his conſcience to approach his Wife in ſo naſty a pickle; he thought it
fitter to go to the Pages Chamber, where knocking once or twice, he that had
robb'd him of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in his Wifes Chaſtity, whoſe thoughts of what had
paſs'd had kept him waking, anſwered, Who is there? But hearing by the
anſwer that it was his Maſter, he was quite aſtoniſh'd; and the guilt
of his fault trightning him with a fear of puniſhment, infuſed into his
Brain, that his Miſtris had diſcovered all to his Maſter, who was now
come to waſh off the Offence with his Blood: His Fear therein blinding his
Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to think that <hi>Donna Margareta,</hi> whom he knew to be ſo
wiſe and diſcreet, would diſcover ſo great an infamy to him, from whom
of all Perſons ſhe had the moſt cauſe to hide it, who being the moſt
inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed in it, was moſt likely to make them<pb n="36" facs="tcp:175400:23"/>both
feel the effects of his vengeance; or that ſhe who would rather have
ſuffered the bittereſt torments, than reveal the leaſt tittle, ſhould
unconſtrained diſcover all. But this young ſinner was ſo troubled in
ſpirit, and his Courage had ſo left him, that he was quickly covered over
with a cold ſweat, fearfully trembling, like one half dying of a Fever,
whoſe cold ſweats denote the deſperate ſtate of the Patient. Having
none but that Door to the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, nor no Window big enough to leap out at, he
went and opened it, and at the ſame time was ready to kneel down to his
Maſter to beg pardon for his Infidelity; but by the light of the Moon, which
was then in the increaſe, ſeeing his Viſage ſo mortified and meager,
that he ſeem'd more like a half-ſtarved Beggar, than a man puft'd up with
Paſſion, or tranſported with Jealouſie, recovering his breath, and
recollecting his Courage, he framed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the beſt he could to anſwer
his Maſter, who perceiving his diſorder, demanded the reaſon. Sir,
(anſwered the Page, with a trembling voice, and ſuitable geſture) the
ſeeing of you in this condition put me into ſuch a diſorder, that I fear
the remaining<pb n="37" facs="tcp:175400:23"/>part of the night will hardly ſettle me; for
at firſt not knowing you, I thought it had been ſome evil Spirit come from
the other World to chaſtize me for my Sins.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Sebaſtian,</hi> though almoſt dead with cold, could
hardly reſtrain his laughter at the words of the ſubtle Page; and after a
charge of ſecrecy, under the ſtricteſt pains, he recounted to him his
late dangerous Adventure (who had not yet the manners or ingenuity to keep the
Laws of Romance, in requiting him with a Narration of his) and bid him light a
Fire to warm him a clean Shirt. There was, by good hap, ſome Sparks yet alive
of the laſt nights Fire, with which (for want of other Fuel) the Page lighted
ſome Straw which he pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from under his Bed, wherewith his half-ſtarved
Maſter warmed himſelf the beſt he could. Having at once caſt off his
foul Shirt, and therewithall his numerous un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcom Gueſts, and having
ſmugged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf up the beſt he could, he went into his Chamber,
ſlipping as ſilently into bed to his Wife, as the Snake that ſlides with
his ſpeckled skin over the poliſh'd Marble; where we will for the preſent
leave him, and return to <hi>Catalina</hi>'s Husband <hi>Roderigo,</hi> 
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:175400:24"/>who had beed a long time puffing and blowing at a Cole,
with Cheeks ſwelling out like a pair of Bagpipes (only now and then taking
breath to curſe) before he could light his Candle; but at laſt, with much
ado, having lighted it, and his thirſt for the rare Bottle of Wine being
highly inflamed by this toiling amongſt Aſhes and Fire, he leap'd like
Lightning to the Cupboard, his mouth watering extremely (which perhaps had been
the cauſe he had been ſo long a lighting his Candle) in expectation of the
Dainties; when, alas! like the Alchymiſt, in ſtead of the longed for Stone,
after all his blowing the Coals, he found nothing but empty Alymbecks, the
Bottle and Plate as empty as his Head or Belly, which made him preſently
think the Boy had deceived him, as his Wife feared; for which cauſe, without
ſecond thoughts, he marched ſtraight to the Bed, where finding the Boy
ſleeping, as innocent of the fact, as ignorant of the danger that attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
him, he (without waking him in order to a Tryal) fell ſtraight to Execution,
which he performed unmeaſurably, with a Cudgel he had found in the corner of
the Kitchen. The Boy feeling the blows<pb n="39" facs="tcp:175400:24"/>ſhowr down ſo
thick upon him, thought it had been ſome of thoſe roguiſh Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits which
he had often heard talk of, that haunted Countrey-houſes in the night; and
(knowing no better remedy for the preſent danger) fell to making as many
Croſſes, and invoking as many Saints as his Maſter gave him blows. The
fear at firſt aſtoniſh'd him more than the blows; but the former
vaniſh'd as the later en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed: ſo that ſeeling the hail encreaſe
ſo faſt, that it had almoſt broken his Ribs, and beaten his Fleſh to a
Mummy, which being no longer able to ſuſtain, he leap'd ſuddenly out of
the Bed, and preſently knew his Maſter, who uttered theſe words, How did
you like your <hi>Rabadabia,</hi> pray Sir, was it good? Was the Partridge leg
well roaſted and tender? I am ſorry I could provide you no better Sawce
than this. But the Boy, who neither underſtood this Heathen-Greek, nor the
Riddle of the Bottle which his Maſter held in his left hand, ſtill
repeating theſe words, and other ſuch like, turned his back to his
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and his face towards the Stairs, and endangering his Neck to ſave
his Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, at two or three jumps was got down<pb n="40" facs="tcp:175400:25"/>Stairs,
ſtill (like a fearful Hind) thinking his Tormenter at his heels, whom he
could not well tell whether he was mad or drunk, but judged the later by the
empty Bottle. Having performed this unjuſt chaſtiſement at the
inſtigation of his Wife, who had made a Supper of that for which the Boy was
ſo ſeverely puniſh'd, and (as we ſaid) uſed this trick to make way
for her Gallant to eſcape; for ſhe knew that the purchaſe of ſuch Wine
as ſhe had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed this to her Husband, and ſuch Dainties, would
encourage him to venture as far as the <hi>Argonauts</hi> for the Golden
Fleece: After this (I ſay) <hi>Roderigo</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Bed to his Wife,
recounting to her what a Supper he had given the Boy for robbing him of his,
which ſhe approved of, ſaying, He well deſerved it for his
ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cineſs; aſſuring him, there was above a Quart in the Bottle: and
for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge, there was but a Leg; but it was not ſo valuable for the
quantity as the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, it being the beſt ſhe ever ſaw. With theſe
Diſcourſes, and ſuch like, followed by their Conjugal Careſſes and
ordinary Embraces, we will leave them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (it being unfitting to
be preſent at<pb n="41" facs="tcp:175400:25"/>what paſſed betwixt them) and return to
our Page <hi>Valerio,</hi> who being come to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf again, and his Maſter
gone from him, went to Bed, there to expect the approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing day, without
ſleeping; finding it better refreſhing to him to ruminate on the
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful paſſages of that Night.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Firſt Part.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:175400:26"/>
            <head>THE AMOROUS TRAVELLERS, OR THE
<hi>Night-Adventures.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>PART II.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He lovely <hi>Aurora</hi> had already by the clarity of her
Beams diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the tops of the Mountains of <hi>Sierra Morena,</hi> when
<hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi>'s Coachmen, willing that their Maſter ſhould ſee
their diligence to obey his commands by their timely riſing, went to knock at
their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Chamber-door, to let him know they were ready, not doubting
but he was ſo<pb n="43" facs="tcp:175400:26"/>too, that had given them ſuch charge
over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night; but the obſcurity which through the Key-hole they perceived to be
in the Room, anſwerered them that they that were within were aſleep
ſtill. They there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore returned back, and a while after came again, and were
forced to return as at firſt. So that ſeeing they made no more haſte to
riſe, they thought of no way bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to paſs that time, whilſt our
laſt-nights valiant Warriors continued Captives to Sleep, than in a good
Breakfaſt and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Mornings-draught.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Donna Margareta</hi> was the firſt that awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and
remembring the paſſages of the night paſt, could ſcarce think them any
other than a Dream: But the Pendant, and ſome other marks ſhe found about
her, certified her of the contrary. She would not awake her Husband (who
ſlept like a man throughly wearied and ſpent with labour; and the noiſe
he made in ſnoring teſtified to her the pleaſure he took in his reſt,
and the pains he had taken that night to be as great as hers) but reſolving
to tell him that ſhe never wak'd all night, but ſlept till ſix in the
morning, ſhe went to open the Door to her Chamber-maids,<pb n="44" facs="tcp:175400:27"/>who were not far thence attending her call; and having let them in,
they brought her her Clothes, and ſhe begun to dreſs her ſelf, and comb
her lovely Hair, which hanging in curious Rings, as ſo many Snares,
diſplayed more enticements than ever the moſt ingenious Painter could draw
for the Picture of <hi>Venus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chimena</hi> being dreſſing her Locks, miſſed the
Pendant, and told her it was loſt. No (ſaid <hi>Donna Margareta</hi>) for
when it fell I took it up, and gave it to <hi>Valerio</hi> to keep for me; call
him hither, and bid him bring it me. <hi>Chimena</hi> went to him preſently,
bidding him bring the Pendant his Miſtriſs gave him to keep.
<hi>Valerio,</hi> who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood his Ladys meaning, who uſed this trick,
fearing that the opinion he might have of having laid with <hi>Chimena,</hi>
might occaſion his diſcovery to her what had paſs'd, and ſo reveal that
ſecret which if not kept cloſe might ruine them both, went inſtantly to
her Chamber, and gave it to her; which ſhe taking with her delicate white
Hand, the remembrances of what had paſſed the night before dyed her Roſie
Cheeks into a deep Scarlet. <hi>Valerio</hi>'s confuſion alſo being no
leſs than hers,<pb n="45" facs="tcp:175400:27"/>made him not dare to look her in the
face.</p>
               <p>By this time <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> awaking, ſaid to his
Wife, My dear, prethee ſend word to the Coachmen and Grooms that they make
not too much haſte; for I find my ſelf ſo indiſpoſed, that it is
impoſſible to riſe yet, and I fear we ſhall hardly go hence till after
Dinner. Alas! what is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with thee, Deareſt, ſaid <hi>Donna
Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reta?</hi> Nothing but a little Head-ach, ſaid <hi>Don
Sebaſtian;</hi> but I hope it will quickly be well with a little reſt:
Onely prethee let all go out of the Chamber, or make the leaſt noiſe they
can in it, that I may reſt quietly. Well, deareſt, (ſaid <hi>Donna
Margareta,</hi> ordering the Maids to draw the Curtains and depart) I will go
to Maſs whilſt you ſleep: And without further ſtay, ſhe and her Maids
avoided the Room.</p>
               <p>Having done her Devotion, as ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurned towards her Lodging
ſhe ſaw a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, followed by three or four Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, come riding
towards her; and near the Cavalier ſhe eſpied a Lady, the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of
whoſe Habit beſpake her of ſome Illuſtrious Family. She was mounted on
a white Horſe, with a Saddle of <hi>Brazile</hi>-wood as red as Coral, and
richly gilded,<pb n="46" facs="tcp:175400:28"/>the Seat being of Crimſon-Taffeta, laid
thick with Gold and Silver Lace. She had a looſe Riding-garment of Damask,
all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas'd with Silver, and laced; her Gown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skirts of the ſame, and the
Body of her Gown of Cloth of Gold, with a Hat all covered over with a gallant
Plume, which aſtoniſhed <hi>Donna Margareta,</hi> to ſee a Lady ſo
advantageouſly habited and richly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coutred.</p>
               <p>They paſſed near her; and though ſhe was curiouſly
regarding our fair Stranger, ſhe could not diſcover her face, becauſe it
was moſt part covered with a white Taffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Hood: but her gallant Meen, and
grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Carriage did evidently declare, that this Vail concealed as rare a
Beauty. They ſaluted her very courteouſly, and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier ſaid to the
Lady he conducted, which we now ſpake of, as ſhe paſſed cloſe by
<hi>Donna Margareta,</hi> Madam, this Country, though rough and mountainous,
and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in little elſe, does produce as beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ladies as the
richeſt, as you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by this Lady behind us. By what I perceive
(replied the Lady) ſhe is not of this Countrey; or though ſhe were, it is
not the firſt time we have heard of lovely<pb n="47" facs="tcp:175400:28"/>Nymphs (as
without vanity we may term this) amongſt rugged Mountains. I leave you to
judge whether <hi>Donna Margareta</hi> were not well pleaſed with theſe
words; but much more when ſhe ſaw them ſtop before her Inn, becauſe
ſhe was extremely deſirous to ſee if this Ladies face were ſuitable to
her other excellencies. The Cavalier was no ſooner arrived at the Inn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,
but he alighted from his Horſe to help the Lady from hers, who at the ſame
time asked the Hoſt what a Clock it was, and taking off her Hood,
diſcovered ſo beauteous a Face, and imbelliſhed with ſo many Graces,
that the ſplendour was enough to dazzle the beholders eyes. The Cavalier
asked her if ſhe would eat any thing; but ſhe anſwered, ſhe had more
mind to repoſe her ſelf, being ſomewhat weary with Travel.</p>
               <p>The Hoſt conducted them into a large Ground-room, where they
were no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er entred with all their Equipage, but the Cavalier went out, to
enquire if a Cavalier and his Lady, and all their Train, that were going to
Court, had not lain in the Houſe the night before, becauſe they heard at
the foot of the Mountain that they were<pb n="48" facs="tcp:175400:29"/>parted from
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>beda</hi> the day before, and he ſhould be glad to wait on them,
becauſe his Niece was deſirous of the Ladies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, having heard of her
Beauty and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility. The Hoſt anſwered him, ſmiling, I wonder, Sir, your
eyes ſhould be ſo dim, as not to ſee the Sovereign Beauty you ſpeak of,
having her ſo near you; that is ſhe that is juſt now entring the Yard,
whom you are ſo deſirous ſhould accompany your Niece, which I ſuppoſe
may eaſily be compaſſed, for I gueſs you go all one way. I know not,
anſwered the Cavalier, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the Lady will agree to it. <hi>Donna
Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reta,</hi> who had over-heard their Diſcourſe, anſwered, Yes, Sir;
and I ſhall take it for a great honour. At leaſt, Madam, repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the
Cavalier, you will find in the Lady that comes along with me a Siſter not
one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Beauty and good Grace, but alſo in her deſire to ſerve you, and
in me an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servant. On the contrary, Sir, replied <hi>Donna
Margareta,</hi> you and ſhe ſhall find me ready to ſerve you upon all
occaſions: And if my Beauty do not equal that of the young Lady your Niece,
yet I will ſo far endeavour to make amends in the confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of my will to
hers, that her deſires<pb n="49" facs="tcp:175400:29"/>and mine ſhall be the ſame. For
me and my Niece, ſaid the Cavalier, I promiſe you that we will ſtrive by
our behaviour in this Journey, to let you ſee that our chiefeſt ſtudy
ſhall be to pleaſe you. Upon this <hi>Donna Margareta</hi> took leave of
him, to go ſee if her Husband were awake, without giving leave to the
Cavalier to renew his obliging language, onely making him the civilleſt
obeiſance ſhe could.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Donna Margareta</hi> entring her Chamber, found her Husband
awake, and ready to ariſe; whereupon ſhe told him all ſhe had ſeen, and
the good Company ſhe had met with to eaſe the troubles of the remaining
Journey. <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> was hugely pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at his Wifes
Diſcourſe, principally when ſhe exagerated the Beauty of her that was
ſo deſirous of her company; and wiſh'd that Time's Wings were a little
ſwifter, he longed ſo to ſee this Lady, whom his Wife had painted to him
with ſo advantageous a Diſcourſe. He aroſe very joyful of the
contentment which he hoped for from this new Company, which put Wings to his
haſte in making himſelf ready, telling his Wife that his Head-ach had left
him, and that he found himſelf ſo<pb n="50" facs="tcp:175400:30"/>lively, that he
ſhould think himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of that bleſſing, if he did not
te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie his gratitude and ſatisfaction, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the moſt
ſumptuous of his Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel; and that beſides, it was fit he ſhould appear
ſomething extraordinary in ſuch noble Company, to make himſelf appear in
the luſtre his Condition required. It this deſign of changing his Sute
occaſioned this Diſcourſe, the loſs of his Cloke (as you have heard)
made him deſirous to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh it, the better to conceal his
laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nights debauche: So that leaving his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Habit, he took another very
gentile one, and asked his Wife how it became him; who told him very well,
which pleaſed him extremely: So taking leave of her for half an hour, he went
to Maſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:175400:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DOn Sebaſtian</hi> was no ſooner gone out of the Chamber
to hear Maſs, but <hi>Don Sancho</hi> and <hi>Donna Leonora</hi> (for ſo
were our new Gueſts named) came in to viſit <hi>Donna Margareta,</hi> who
was then diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Chimena</hi> her Maid, about what they had
ſeen in the Church. After Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements paſſed on the one part and the
other, they ſate down, and paſſed betwixt themſelves all the time till
<hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> returned from Maſs, entertaining one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with
words ſo charming, that none but thoſe two could have made ſuch
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements with ſo good a grace, and with ſuch gentile reparties as
paſſed betwixt them in this firſt encounter, and thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
with ſo brave an air, that one would have thought that Love had given them
his Artifice, to raviſh the hearts of all the Hearers. Theſe Entertainments
laſted pretty long, till <hi>Donna Margareta</hi> calling to mind a Perſon
whom ſhe had formerly loved as dearly as her life, and whoſe Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traicture
ſhe fancied ſhe ſaw drawn to the<pb n="52" facs="tcp:175400:31"/>life in the Face of
<hi>Donna Leonora,</hi> could not ſpeak ſo diſcreetly as before, nor give
ſuch ſharp or ſubtle replies to <hi>Donna Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora,</hi> who asked her a
thouſand queſtions; for her fancy was ſo fixed on that dear ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that
it had no room left for other concerns. <hi>Donna Leonora</hi> knew, but
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled her knowledge of the diſorder of her ſpirit, and not
ſeeming to take notice of it, riſing up, and taking her by the hand, ſhe
ſaid,</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>Madam, 'tis a general Rule, That to Perſons who enjoy a
great contentment, the time ſeems ſo ſpeedy, that though they continued a
whole Age in that fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, it would all ſeem to have ſlipp'd away in a
moment. At this time I have had a full Experiment of the verity of this
Aſſertion; for though effectually I have had a large enjoyment of your
ſweet Converſation, yet methinks I am but juſt entring upon the brinks of
that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: Wherefore, Madam, (ſaid ſhe, with a low obeiſance) I hope
you will pardon me if I have been troubleſom in this my firſt Viſit,
which is the firſt and greateſt happineſs I have received of Fortune, in
making me happy in the<pb n="53" facs="tcp:175400:31"/>knowledge of ſo deſerving a
Lady.</q> And as <hi>Donna Margareta</hi> was deſiring her to ſit down
again, and with a thouſand careſſes to let her know the content and
honour ſhe took it for, to be viſited by a Lady of her quality, upon this
<hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> entred, who ſeeing his Wife in ſo good company, he
(being a complete Courtier) accoſted them the beſt he could, and with very
great civility. <hi>Donna Leonora</hi> returned him hers very gracefully, with
whoſe Beauty he was infinitely charmed, and fancied to himſelf he never
ſaw a more complete one. They began anew their Entertainment, and in leſs
than an hour all their four humours were ſo exactly conformable, and in ſo
much pleaſure and contentment, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the communicating of one anothers
Affairs, and the cauſes of their Journeys, they contracted amongſt
themſelves an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable Friendſhip, as you may remark in the Sequel of
this Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>And for this happy encounter which every one of them had made,
they reſolved to ſtay there that day, which they intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſpend in
Sports and Paſtimes. The pretty <hi>Catalina</hi> did not fail in employing
her utmoſt dexterity amongſt them in their<pb n="54" facs="tcp:175400:32"/>Plays and
Dances; but <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> had his mind ſo firmly fixed upon a more
wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Subject, that he had no room for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring her excellencies, though all
the reſt did highly eſteem them. <hi>Donna Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reta,</hi> who fancied
that ſhe ſaw in <hi>Donna Leonora</hi> the lively Image of one who had
formerly captivated her Affections, revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in her mind the continual
thoughts of their former Amours, and the contentments which ſhe and her Lover
had formerly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed.</p>
               <p>The heavineſs and trouble which feiſed her at the
remembrance of ſo ſweet fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt joys, wrought in her the ſecret
Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſes following.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>O happy time, in which I enjoyed the ſight of my adored
<hi>Don Carlos!</hi> O fortunate ſeaſon! Would God that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the
enjoyment of ſo delicious a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as I was bleſſed with during thy
ſhort hours, in the company of ſo dear a Perſon, I had therewith loſt
the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the good which I ſee my ſelf deprived of in loſing
thee. And thou, Angel or Phantaſm, which repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteſt in different
Habits the ſelf-ſame Lineaments and ſweet Behaviour, tell 
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:175400:32"/>me, I ſay, dear Spirit, if he thou repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteſt do
ſtill continue his affection for me, and for whom I now feel revived in me
the torments I formerly ſuffered for him.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Complaints, and others ſuch-like, were forging in the
Breaſt of <hi>Donna Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gareta,</hi> whilſt <hi>Donna Leonora</hi> was
making her a thouſand careſſes. On the other ſide, <hi>Don
Sebaſtian</hi> and <hi>Don Sancho,</hi> who with divers ſorts of
Recreations diverted the Company, obliged <hi>Donna Margareta</hi> to keep time
with the reſt, and by imitating them, ſtrive the beſt ſhe could to
allay the torment which was cauſed in her by thoſe piercing eyes, which
opened afreſh thoſe wounds which Love had made when ſhe was in her
Father's Houſe.</p>
               <p>Our beauteous and complaiſant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany paſſed all the day,
as you have heard, in all ſorts of Sports and Recreations; and after Supper
they reſolved to depart the next day early in the morning, which made them go
to bed the ſooner, but every one with different thoughts. Some of them
ſlept ſoundly, the others ſtill diſcourſing to themſelves upon that
which their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations propounded to their Judgments, <pb n="56" facs="tcp:175400:33"/>while ſeeking the means to give ſatisfaction to their deſires,
they found a deprivation of the ſweetneſs of ſleep, which finding the
doors of their Senſes ſhut againſt his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, went nimbly from
one of them to the other to ſeek a retreat, till the wearineſs of their
Bodies abating the forces of their Spirits, conſtrained them by his hands to
pay the Tribute due to Nature.</p>
               <p>They all awaked with the dawning of the morning, and made
themſelves ready with all expedition, ſutable to their deſires of making
a good large Journey that day, bidding the Coachmen make ready the Coach
preſently, whilſt the others truſs'd up the Baggage, and they paid their
Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning. <hi>Don Sebaſtian, Don Sancho,</hi> and the two Ladies, with
<hi>Chimena</hi> and <hi>Scintilla</hi> their Maids, went into the Coach; and
the reſt of their Servants, mounted upon Mules, rode before them. Whilſt
the Coach went ſmoothly along, the Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers and Ladies entertained the time
with ſuch agreeable Diſcourſes and amorous Conceits, expreſſed in
ſuch charming Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, that it would have raviſh'd the beſt Wits to
have heard the politeneſs of their Talk, and the union of their Minds.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:175400:33"/>They ſo diverted themſelves with this
agreeable converſation, that the way did not at all ſeem long to them; ſo
that they arrived at <hi>Almagro,</hi> when they thought they had ſcarce been
clear of the Suburbs of <hi>Viſo:</hi> and joyful of having cleared ſo much
ground in ſo ſhort a time, they dined with a good appetite, and paſſed
the reſt of the day in viewing the Town, which is a very pretty one. The
night being come, they went to bed, and ſo ſoon as the day begun to appear,
and the Rays of the Sun to gild the tops of the Mountains, they purſued their
Journey, without letting ſlip any moment which was not employed in moſt
agreeable divertiſements. They dined that day at <hi>Malagon,</hi> and after
continued their Journey with their wonted Paſtime: But whilſt the reſt of
the Company thought on nothing but theſe pleaſures, <hi>Donna Leonora</hi>
began to complain of the Head-ach, which in the inſtant changed all their
content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments into plaints and regrets. <hi>Donna Margareta</hi> was the
firſt that came to help her, and bound a Handkerchief faſt about her Head,
which notwithſtanding, ſhe ſtill continued the complaint of her
afflicting malady. Her ſighs and groans were ſo<pb n="58" facs="tcp:175400:34"/>many
thunder-claps to <hi>Don Sebaſtian,</hi> each of which ſplit his Heart
aſunder: His paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he had for her at firſt ſight, was now chang'd
from love to pitty, joyn'd with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme ſorrow, fearing that death like a
ſudden inundation, ſhould drown this new-diſcovered pleaſant Countrey,
ere he had time to take poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Donna Margareta</hi> ſupported this diſaſter with no
leſs Commotion of ſpirt; her outward behaviour witneſſing to the
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, that her inward malady was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing inferior to hers whom ſhe
bewailed. <hi>Don Sancho</hi> too ſeemed very much afflicted by his Nieces
diſaſter, ſeeming no leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd leſt ſome further miſchief
might come to her before they could get her to the Inn of the
<hi>Carçuela,</hi> which made him earneſt to know of the Coachmen how
far it was thither, by whom he was informed, that it was not above a
Bow-ſhoot or two at the moſt, which much alleviated their ſorrows.
<hi>Donna Leonora</hi> deſired her Uncle to take her out of the Coach, that
ſhe might take the benefit of the Air, which he did, and at the ſame time
all the reſt of the Company did the ſame. <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> and
<hi>Don Sancho</hi> took her by the Arms, and<pb n="59" facs="tcp:175400:34"/>conducted her
to the Inn, where they were no ſooner arrived, but a great ſwooning ſo
diſſipated her Spirits, that they feared ſhe had breathed out her ſoul
in a ſigh ſhe gave, ſinking down upon their Arms. This ſo afflicted all
the Company, that they were in little better caſe than ſhe, having ſcarce
power left to run to aid her. <hi>Donna Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gareta</hi> was the firſt, who
ſeeing her dear Companion, the lovely Pourtraicture of her beloved <hi>Don
Carlos,</hi> in that condition, preſently ſprinkled her face with cold
wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, mixed with the warm tears which this ſorrowful ſpectacle extracted
from her fair eyes, which in a little time reduced her Spirits to their former
function.</p>
               <p>He that ſhould dream of being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to a cruel and
ignominious death by a Sovereign Tribunal, from whence lay no Appeal, and from
whence no Mercy could be hoped for, could not be more joyful when with his
ſleep he finds himſelf delivered from theſe black and diſmal
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, the terror of which had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved him into ſweat, than
our Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſeeing their ſpirits revived together with thoſe of
<hi>Donna Leonora.</hi> One was ſo tranſported with this ſudden joy, that
he<pb n="60" facs="tcp:175400:35"/>had almoſt loſt the ſenſe of it: The others
beholding in the ſweet (though languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) eyes of our ſick Lady two
gliſtering Stars, with which Love, drawing the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and diſſipating
the clouds of her eye-lids, aſtoniſhed the beholders, were more amazed than
the ſolitary Shepherd, who having never been out of the ſight of his own
homely Cottage, comes to view the proud and ſumptuous Buildings of ſtately
Courts and opulent Cities.</p>
               <p>Having laid her upon a Bed, they went to fetch her ſome
refreſhments, the fitteſt for one in her condition to take. <hi>Donna
Margareta's</hi> ſollicitous care would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit her to leave the Beds
ſide, but, like the Mother that has loſt her onely Infant, the repoſitory
of all her worldly comfort, and finding another the exact Picture of it, does
kiſs and cheriſh it with her tendereſt affections, ſtill ſuppoſing
to hold in her Arms the true one, which Death had cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly deprived her of: So
this afflicted La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſeeing her dear <hi>Don Carlos</hi> his Picture in the
face of <hi>Donna Leonora,</hi> teſtified her ſatisfaction in tender
kiſſes and gentle em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, the ſick Lady not moving her head the while;
onely to witneſs to <hi>Donna Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gareta</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:175400:35"/>the content
ſhe took in her Careſſes, ſhe joyned her Lips to hers, and kiſſed
her with ſuch tender ſighs, that ſhe ſeemed even to ſwoon betwixt her
Arms.</p>
               <p>But though 'tis fit my Pen ſhould take a little ſcope to
ramble in this Narrative, 'tis convenient it therein take the ſhorteſt path
to arrive at the mark at which it aims, and the Reader impatiently expects: And
my opinion is clearly this, That to recount Adventures of this nature, it is
improper to amuſe the Reader with unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Circumlocutions, who for the
moſt part troubled with a tedious and ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Diſcourſe, caſts
it careleſly in a corner of the Room, there to lye contemned for an
impertinent Prater. This for the future I intend diligently to obſerve,
though hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto I may ſeem to have been ſomewhat peccant. Therefore,
Reader, take a little breath, and prepare thy attention, if thou beeſt
curious to know what is contained in the enſuing Chapter, whoſe pleaſure
may chance deſerve thy attention in the reading, if their novelty do not
cauſe thy admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion when read.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:175400:36"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>THe Sun already wearied with having run ſo long a courſe
through the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Circle of the ſpacious Zodiack, was diſharneſſing
his Horſes, to plunge with them into the Ocean, his ordinary noctur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
Retreat; and the ſerene unclouded, though ſomewhat darkned Sky, was
alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy expecting the approach of beauteous <hi>Cynthia,</hi> when <hi>Don
Sebaſtian</hi> and <hi>Don San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho</hi> came to preſent <hi>Donna
Leonora</hi> with their Conſerves and Sweet-meats; but her chearful
Countenance had already diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Flag of Health, and her pleaſant
Words diſcovered the lightneſs of her Heart. This (ſays ſhe) was
nothing but a ſudden qualm; but now, I thank God, I find that quite
vaniſh'd, and my perfect Health taken poſſeſſion of its former
habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: In the mean time, like ſick perſons let us eat theſe
Confectures, and as heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy take care for Supper to be made ready; and to make
it appear that I am now ſo perfectly well, that your further care of me is
needleſs, I intend to ſup amongſt<pb n="63" facs="tcp:175400:36"/>you, and with my
wonted contentment re-enjoy our former diverſions.</p>
               <p>She had no ſooner ſaid this, but all, to teſtifie the
intereſt they had in her reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, ſtudied who ſhould invent the moſt
pleaſant Stories and new Divertiſments to pleaſe her, till a Page
interrupted them, by telling them Supper was already upon the Table. After
Supper, for their better di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, they took a turn in the Fields near the
Inn, and after returned to the Houſe, with a deſign to go to Bed betime,
and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Hoſteſs to lay clean Sheets upon the Bed. But ſhe
whoſe Head was little troubled with that care, as one that had ſeldom been
uſed to make more Beds in the Houſe than her own, anſwered them
admiringly, ſaying, I wonder, Gentlemen, that you, who, I am ſure, have
travelled not onely this Road, but through all <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhould be
ignorant that many Inns, eſpecially in ſuch a Deſart place as you may
know this to be by the very name of it (which is called 
<note n="*" place="margin">The Spaniſh word çarças,
ſsgnifies thorns and briers.</note>
                  <hi>Carçuela</hi>) have no more
Beds but for their own Families; which is the reaſon that all Travellers
ſtrive to ſtretch on to the next great Town,<pb n="64" facs="tcp:175400:37"/>and never
ſtay to lie there, no more than you, I ſuppoſe, would have done here, had
it not been for this Ladies Diſtemper: But all that I can do for you, is to
give theſe Ladies my Bed: And for you, Gentlemen, the inconvenience you will
ſuffer this night for want of a Bed, will ſerve to moderate your joy for
the Ladies ſudden recovery, and you may paſs your time the beſt you can
by ſaying your Prayers in this Book (throwing a Pack of Cards upon the
Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) for there is no other remedy, if you diſpute till to morrow.</p>
               <p>We muſt be contented then, ſaid <hi>Don Sancho,</hi> and let
us ſhuffle the Cards; for <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelf has ſuffer'd a great
deal more hardſhip, when he travell'd through <hi>Germany</hi> in the midſt
of Winter amongſt Ice and Snow. I wiſh (ſaid <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi>)
this may be the greateſt miſchief that I ſhell ever be forced to undergo;
for it is not long ſince, in a Night-adventure (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that at
<hi>Viſo</hi>) I would gladly have bought this ſafe divertiſement at a
good many Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cats: But go you to Bed, Ladies (ſaid he) if you pleaſe; for
for our parts, we will endeavour to divert our ſelves at Picquet, or ſome
other Game, and paſs the night as<pb n="65" facs="tcp:175400:37"/>merrily as we can: And
you, Madam <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora,</hi> be ſure you do nothing to my Wife; for if you
do, you and I muſt quarrel to morrow morning, if I know it. They all laughed
at theſe words of <hi>Don Sebaſtian;</hi> and the Ladies would have
excuſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from going to Bed, becauſe they thought it uncivil to
lye at their eaſe, whilſt the two Cavaliers ſuffered the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodity of
ſitting up. Upon this, the Hoſt arriving, ſaid to them, Pray Ladies go to
Bed; for I intend to play this Purſe of Reals with my Maſters here, and I
ſhould not be well content to have you by, for the ſight of a ſuſpected
perſon is not more offenſive to a jealous man, than the preſence of a
Wife to him that plays with her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. Theſe, and ſome ſuch other
Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſes, took up a certain ſpace of time, till the Ladies,
vanquiſh'd by the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Company, went to Bed, and left the
Cavaliers to their Gaming.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Second Part.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:175400:38"/>
            <head>THE AMOROUS TRAVELLERS, OR THE
<hi>Night-Adventures.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>PART III.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OT to hold you long in in ſuſpence about what I have to
ſay in the enſuing Diſcourſe, I will imitate the Painter, who having
compleated the Picture of a beauteous Woman, does with two ſtrokes of his
Pencil upon her Face, two upon her Breaſt, and two betwixt her Thighs, change
her inſtantly into a Man: So I at preſent will in leſs than ſix words
endeavour to change <hi>Donna Leonora</hi> into<pb n="67" facs="tcp:175400:38"/>
                  <hi>Don
Carlos;</hi> not with prodigious Stories, and alledging things that never were,
but onely let you know in ſhort, that <hi>Don Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los</hi> was the Son of a
certain Duke, whoſe name we ſhall for certain reaſons conceal, as being
unneceſſary to this Narrative: It may ſuffice to ſay, that his Houſe
was not far from that of <hi>Donna Margareta's</hi> Father. For his Beauty I
refer to what is ſaid already, I having before exaggerated it to ſo high a
perfection under the Habit of a Woman, that the faireſt of this time might
have juſt cauſe to envy it. It may yet ſeem miraculous to find in <hi>Don
Carlos</hi> ſo rare a Beauty as we have deſcribed, who though never ſo
complete and handſom a Cavalier, ſhould in this diſguiſe ſeem but
foul and deformed, compared to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Female Beauty; or that he, in
ſo different a Habit from his own, ſhould ſo dexterouſly behave
himſelf after the Cuſtoms and Gallantries of a Lady. I muſt onely ſay,
to remove this difficulty, that <hi>Don Carlos</hi> was a man of a Beauty far
beyond the ordinary Maſculine one, and ſo always eſteemed by thoſe that
ſaw him; and his wit and addreſs, joyned to the boldneſs which Love
infuſed into him,<pb n="68" facs="tcp:175400:39"/>made him every way ſo complete, that I
queſtion whether <hi>Achilles</hi> made a better Girl when he courted King
<hi>Lycomedes</hi> his Daughter in that Habit; or whether <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi>
took a better ſhape, when he enjoyed his <hi>Caliſto</hi> in that of
<hi>Diana. Don Carlos</hi> was ſent by the Duke his Father at the age of
ſixteen to ſtudy at <hi>Oſmus,</hi> an Univerſity whoſe Learning,
that flouriſheth there, has made it ſufficiently known throughout
<hi>Spain.</hi> In this place lived <hi>Donna Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reta's</hi> Father, whoſe
Houſe was directly oppoſite to <hi>Don Carlos</hi> his Lodgings, who the
firſt time he ſaw her appear through the Window, more beauteous than the
Sun riſing from the Eaſt, quickly became amorous of her; and it was
needleſs for Love to repreſent the charms of her Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a ſecond time,
becauſe at this firſt view he became ſo ſmitten, that he yielded up his
Liberty to her diſpoſal, ſacrificing his Heart to his fair Deity. Time,
and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity the mother of Diligence, and Love the Miſtriſs of
Invention, gave means to our new Lover to diſcover his Affections to
<hi>Donna Margareta,</hi> who no leſs ſenſible than he of the wounds of
Love, accepted the tender of his Service, and gave him<pb n="69" facs="tcp:175400:39"/>her
Heart in exchange. Theſe Amours continued ſtill encreaſing by degrees,
whilſt none perceived them; but at laſt their paſſion ſo far
augmented, that it was impoſſible to conceal it any longer; and they having
no other remedy but a free enjoyment, for thoſe pleaſing Flames that
conſumed their Hearts, reſolved to come to the point to which all Lovers
tend; which they had accordingly done, had they not been interrupted by the
following miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Carlos</hi> his Tutor perceiving, amongſt others, his
new Affection, thought fit to reveal it to his Father, to avoid bearing the
blame of his Pupil's fault; for ſo now a days we term the Love of the Rich to
their Inferiors in Eſtate, which with the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents was the leaſt thing
conſidered amongſt Treaties of Marriage, who ſet a far higher value upon
Vertue than Money: For what greater happineſs can a man enjoy, howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
highly he be advanced in Fortunes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, than in ſtead of the droſs of
tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Riches, to enjoy a Woman rich in the more pure ones of Wit and
Vertue, which hath been the chief accompliſhment deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in a Wife even by
the moſt Barbarous Nations.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:175400:40"/>Don <hi>Carlos</hi> his Father violently
ſtartled at the news of theſe Amours, took Poſt immediately to break
them, and in a ſhort time arrived at <hi>Oſmus,</hi> juſt time enough to
prevent the Marriage, which was then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on point of celebration. This was to
them as it happens to a Pilot, who being come even in view of the Harbour
deſired, and thereby free from ſuſpecting a ſtop or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hap, finds
himſelf ſuddenly, by the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of Winds, and fury and impetuoſity of
the Waves, driven to a Haven which of all others he would have avoided: Even
ſo our Lovers ſped; for the Duke coming, after he had ſharply chid his
Sons offence in the neglect of his Duty, and contracting Marriage without his
Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers conſent, for his Penance he enjoyn'd him two years Exile in
<hi>Flanders,</hi> judging (and indeed rightly) that nothing but ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence was
able to cure his Sons diſtemper: After which he reproached the Father of
<hi>Donna Margareta,</hi> for going about to make a Match ſo unequal and
injurious to him, as that of his Daughter with the Dukes Son. Don
<hi>Pedro</hi> (that was the name of Donna <hi>Margareta's</hi> Father)
excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf, ſaying, that this was the firſt<pb n="71" facs="tcp:175400:40"/>time he ever heard of it; and that he was infinitely ſorry his
Children ſhould be the occaſion either of diſpleaſing or incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moding
him, ſince none was more his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant than he: But, Sir, (continued he) be
pleaſed ſomewhat to undeceive your ſelf; for there is perhaps no ſuch
inequality in it as you ſuppoſe: for though you be Duke, I am a Gentleman
of ſo good a Houſe, that my Anceſtors have no reaſon to give place to
yours, either in Nobility, Vertue, or Merits, but rather in ſome things have
much the advantage; for ſome of them have governed the Kingdom of
<hi>Caſtile</hi> with Name and Dignity of Vice-Roys, which, under favour Sir,
is more than I ſuppoſe yours could boaſt of.</p>
               <p>Theſe words ſo provoked the Duke, that he laid hold on his
ſword to revenge the injury upon Don <hi>Pedro,</hi> who likewiſe drew his
to defend himſelf; and if ſome Cavaliers their Friends had not opportune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
arrived to part them, there had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly ſome miſchief enſued: But
all things being appeaſed, they ſeparated, the one home, and the other with
his Son Don <hi>Carlos</hi> to conduct him into <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Don <hi>Pedro,</hi> to ſtop the mouth of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant 
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:175400:41"/>Vulgar (which is always readier to defame than to praiſe
any one) from utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words to his Daughters diſadvantage, reſolved to
marry her, which he did ſnott<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, through a Friends means, with Don
<hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> who is at preſent the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this Narration.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Carlos</hi> had not yet finiſh'd the firſt year of
his Exile, when a Courrier from his Mother brought him news of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
death, ordering him upon receit of that Letter to take Poſt and return
ſpeedily for <hi>Spain.</hi> Whether he received this news joyfully or no, I
am not certain, and am as unwilling to diſcover my Conjectures in theſe
lines, becauſe a natural ſhame, proper to all good Chriſtians,
reſtrains my Hand, and ſtops my Pen, and makes me confeſs that nothing
ought to be put in parallel with the Love of our Parents; though Love hath ſo
abſolute and puiſſant an Empire over the Soul, that in former Ages we may
read, and in our own ſee many horrid Examples of the moſt inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and
bloody faults that Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is capable to invent, exerciſed with the
greateſt Barbarity imaginable upon their own Blood, to ſatisfie the
bruitiſh<pb n="73" facs="tcp:175400:41"/>appetite which this furious paſſion excites
in them which are poſſeſſed with it, and yield up themſelves to the
rule of its Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</p>
               <p>Though Don <hi>Carlos</hi> (ſuitable to Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers of his Age
and Conſtitution) had contracted new Amours ſince his being in
<hi>Flanders,</hi> yet now ſeeing his way ſo plain, and all the
difficulties removed which not long before combated his deſigns, all
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles now being buried in the Grave of his Father, however engaged in
other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Love in <hi>Flanders,</hi> his inconſtant humour
continually brought into his fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy the memory of Donna <hi>Margareta,</hi>
which repreſented her to him with the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ſhe before
poſſeſſed, which ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled his ardent deſire for her, (backed
with the conſideration of the delights and joys they had formerly
interchanged) that he reſolved to marry her, and to quit his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in
any that could claim a title to his Affections in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus reſolved, he left <hi>Bruxells,</hi> without taking leave
of any one; and tranſported with the hopes of ſeeing Donna
<hi>Margare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> he made ſuch a quick diſpatch of his Journey, that he
arrived at his own home<pb n="74" facs="tcp:175400:42"/>in leſs than fifteen days, where
he ſtaid on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to refreſh himſelf after his weariſom Journey, and to
pay his laſt duty to the memory of his dead Father; which done, he went for
<hi>Oſmus,</hi> there to conſummate his intended Marriage: But arriving
there, he underſtood from his ancient Hoſt that his Miſtris was already
married, which ſo afflicted him, and reduced him to ſo pittiful a
condition, that his Phyſicians al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt concluded his ſtate to be
deſparate: At laſt conſidering with himſelf that all his grief and
melancholy were unprofitable to the cure of his Diſtemper, and ſeeing the
impoſſibility of enjoying her as a Wife, he reſolved at leaſt to make
her his Miſtris. With this reſolution he left <hi>Oſmus</hi> as
ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly as he could, to go for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>beda,</hi> Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi>'s
ordinary abode, where he was no ſooner arrived, but he heard that Don
<hi>Sebaſtian</hi> in few days intended to go to Court with his Wife.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Carlos</hi> hereby ſeeing his hopes fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, and
that this ſudden departure would hinder him from ſeeing her for whom his
heart daily conſumed in ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Flames, began ſo to afflict
himſelf with his misfortune, that his Domeſticks<pb n="75" facs="tcp:175400:42"/>could
not hope for a long continuance of his life. Don <hi>Sancho,</hi> one of his
Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſeeing his Maſter in ſo miſerable a condition, his
compaſſion made him aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the boldneſs to ask the cauſe. Don
<hi>Carlos</hi> having often experimented Don <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho</hi>'s ability and
dexterity in moſt Affairs, and that he was of a moſt ſubtle and
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventive wit, made no difficulty of revealing his diſtemper to him, upon
hopes of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from him ſome eaſe and conſolation for his
Paſſion, which the other, without long conſulting about the Cure, after
his Maſter's diſcovering his Wounds to him, told him in few words as
followeth: The beſt advice, Sir, I can at preſent think on, is, that
diſguiſing your ſelf in a Womans Habit, you overtake them at ſome Inn
up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Road, pretending you are to go the ſame Journey with them: and for
the reſt, truſt it to me; for I engage within two or three days Journey to
bring you to Bed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, without the leaſt ſuſpicion from the Husband:
For being attired in Womans Habit, the cleareſt eye or the ſubtileſt wit
will never be able to diſtinguiſh your Sex through the beauty and delicate
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion of your Face.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:175400:43"/>Don
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> would never have conſented to
this D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, had not Don <hi>Sancho</hi> made him comprehend
that it was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly means poſſible to compaſs his deſigns without
either difficulty or danger. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, his Reaſons made our young Duke
reſolve to follow his advice, and therefore gave order for the making of
Womens Habits, the richeſt imaginable, and another Womans Habit (not ſo
rich as his) for his Page, whom he intended to turn into a Chamber-maid. They
parted from <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>beda</hi> the ſame day that Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> ſet
out with Donna <hi>Margareta;</hi> but it was pretty late in the evening
firſt, to prevent his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeen in that Habit by ſome that might know
him, which was the reaſon that he reached not <hi>Viſo</hi> till the next
morning at nine of the clock, where they found Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> and his
Wife, as you have heard.</p>
               <p>You know now the ſubſtance and reaſons of all that is
paſt, as well as my ſelf: Read now what the next Chapter contains, and you
will find in it as much content and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction as in the former.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:175400:43"/>
               <head>CHAP. II</head>
               <p>WE broke off the Thred of our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe where Don
<hi>Sebaſtian</hi> and Don <hi>Sancho</hi> bid Good-night to Donna
<hi>Margareta</hi> and Donna <hi>Leonora,</hi> who were then going to Bed, and
having taken leave of all the Company, the Hoſteſs conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to their
Chamber, which was well furniſh'd the. Hoſt being a rich Fellow. Being
entred, their Waiting-maids undreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, and they went to bed together.
The Maids having drawn the Curtains, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted the Room, locking the Door after
them, as Donna <hi>Leonora</hi> had ordered, that none might enter to diſturb
them. After this, the Maids and the Hoſteſs, for want of a Bed, went and
ſate down by the Fires ſide, where they paſſed the night as merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as
they could, with the old Stories which the Hoſteſs had heaped up together
in her youth.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Carlos</hi> finding himſelf ſo near that object
which of all others in the World he loved the beſt, feared to diſcover
himſelf preſently, leſt the ſudden exceſs of ſo great 
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:175400:44"/>and unexpected contentment ſhould cauſe ſome
finiſter and dangerous accident, as it once hapned to two Lovers at
<hi>Madrid,</hi> whoſe ſudden &amp; unexpected happineſs cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them
to expire in one anothers Arms: But Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> ſometimes
kiſſing her ſnowie Breaſts, ſometimes her Lips, more pleaſant and
ſweet than the richeſt Spices of <hi>Arabia,</hi> made her all the time all
the amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Careſſes that he could invent. Donna <hi>Margareta</hi>
returned him the like, adding a hundred ſorts of Miguardizes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights,
and with ſo much liberty, that Don <hi>Carlos</hi> no longer holding out
againſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Aſſaults without, and Traitors within, diſcovered to
her by little and little (with many gentle Love-ſighs intermix'd) who he was,
and all the Diſcourſe that you have already heard.</p>
               <p>A Father that has already given over his dear and only Son for
loſt, has not more contentment to find him ſafe, and embrac'd in his aged
Arms, than our Donna <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reta</hi> when ſhe heard theſe words from
her deareſt Friend: but the ſtrangeneſs of it ſo faſtned her Tongue
to the Roof of her Mouth, that ſhe could not expreſs her amazement in one
ſole word: Yet at length<pb n="79" facs="tcp:175400:44"/>rallying her ſpirits, and the
diſloyalty of her Husband working as great a compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in her as the
tenderneſs of the others affection, theſe two paſſions at once ſo
firmly aſſaulted her, that ſhe embraced him with all imaginable
affection. O Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers infinitely happy! What Pen, though guided by the moſt
ingenious Poet in the World, could deſcribe thoſe raviſhing joys and
incomparable delights in which your ſouls ſo ſtraightly intwined, do now
ſo amply bathe themſelves? What under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding can be ſo fruitful as to
attain to a Style ſufficient to expreſs the happy ſtate in which you now
find your ſelves? For my part, I freely confeſs, that the fluency of my
Pen, or ſtrength of my Wit are not able to attain to the accompliſhment of
that deſign. Let it ſuffice then, friendly Reader, to tell thee, That the
Cock had already often chearfully ſaluted the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching day, when our
Lovers were ſtill Captives to Sleeps irreſiſtible Power.</p>
               <p>Let us leave them amongſt their Miguar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes, and return to
Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> and Don <hi>Sancho,</hi> who, though the Sun was
pretty well advanced on his way to our Hemiſphere, and their Hoſt had left
them<pb n="80" facs="tcp:175400:45"/>with thirty Crowns gains, yet continued their Gaming as
hard as ever, the one to endeavour the recovery of a hundred Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols which
he had loſt, and the other to prolong the joy his Maſter then poſſeſt
in the embraces of fair Donna <hi>Margareta</hi> without diſturbance; which
was the cauſe that our Lovers had time not only to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template one another
by the Light of the Chamber, but alſo to recount their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Adventures
after ſo long an abſence, and how for the future they ſhould regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
their Affairs to conceal their Amours from the World. And as the time flies
ſwiftly from thoſe that paſs it ſo delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, ſo our Lovers
thought of nothing leſs than riſing, though the Sun was got a pretty
height, till hearing their Maids en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Chamber, they reſolved (though
moſt unwillingly) to riſe, and cloath them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſpeedily, for fear
leſt Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> and Don <hi>Sancho</hi> ſhould find them
abed, being advertiſed by their Waiting-maids that they were ready to viſit
them, becauſe Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> the loſer had at two Games recovered
a good part of his Money, and was willing to give over with the loſs of fifty
Crowns.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:175400:45"/>The Ladies were no ſooner dreſt, but the
Cavaliers entred their Chambers to give them the <hi>Bon-jour,</hi> and know
how they had reſted; telling them how they had paſſed the night, and how
the Games had gone through all the Play, concluding with the Praiſes due to
Heaven for the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py recovery of <hi>Donna Leonora:</hi> Yet there were ſome
who (according to cuſtom) ſaid ſhe was hardly throughly recovered,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe looked ſomewhat thinner and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler than ordinary. Finally,
all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready for a march, they took leave of their Hoſt and
Hoſteſs, who could hardly contain themſelves for joy that they had
thriven ſo well by that nights Adventures. Let us a while leave them to
congratulate their good hap, and whilſt the Coach is running ſmoothly
along, let us a while give ſcope to our fancies, to conſider the deceits
that are in the World, and with what crafts and ſubtilties this ſenſual
Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite will plain and ſmooth the greateſt rubs and difficulties that
oppoſe the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of its inordinate deſires.</p>
               <p>Can any man in the World reaſonably boaſt to know better
ſecrets for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the wanton ſlips of a Wife, than 
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:175400:46"/>to guard her with as many eyes as <hi>Argus,</hi> placing
more Sentinels in the Houſe than a wiſe and provident Captain would do in a
Town ill fortified and hard to be defended; for there where ſuſpicions and
jealouſies reſide, we may eaſily infer that they are matched with care
and vigilance, and a man whoſe ſpirit is tormented and diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with
theſe two Paſſions, is continually upon his guard. Let a man watch as
long as he will, and fix all his cares upon that deſign; let him even
exhauſt his ſpirits with more crafts and devices than <hi>Dedalus</hi> of
old, when he invented the <hi>Cretan</hi> Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth: After all this, I am
clearly of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that it is as impoſſible for a man to defend his
Honour and his Wifes Chaſtity from the Attaques of a potent purſuer, who
aſſaults his Wife with Courtſhip, and batters her with fair words, and
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermines her and corrupts the Sentinels with Preſents, or deceives them
all by Stratagems (eſpecially if her paſſions and inclinations be on his
party) as to hinder the Sun, when he is for ſome few minutes eclipſed, to
return to light us in four days time, or to confine his Rays for fifteen days
together to the tops of the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,<pb n="83" facs="tcp:175400:46"/>without ſuffering Night to cover the face of the Earth with her dark
and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Veil. Admit but a few Examples. What ſhould we think of
<hi>Danae</hi>'s Tower, <hi>Atalanta</hi>'s Swiftneſs, <hi>Caliſto</hi>'s
Honeſty, <hi>Lucretia</hi>'s Chaſtity, King <hi>Lycomedes</hi> his
Vigilancy, <hi>Juno</hi>'s Jealouſie, the ſtrict guard kept upon the
Veſtals Purity? What ſhould we judge, I ſay, of this, but that all the
Induſtry of all the Fathers, Husbands, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Wifes, and Kindred before
mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, were not capable to prevent <hi>Jupiter, Tarquin, Achilles,</hi>
and and all the reſt, from wreathing themſelves with the Branches of
thoſe Trees which they had ſo diligently fenced? For there is no Stone ſo
hard, but the continual dropping of Water upon it will make a breach and decay
it; nor no Ox ſo unruly, but he is at laſt made plia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Yoke; no
Mine, but may be countermined; No Fortreſs ſo high, or ſo difficult of
aſcent (if <hi>Philip of Macedon</hi> may be credited) over which an Aſs
laden with Gold cannot paſs; not any Husband ſo vigilant, as to be able to
hinder the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent cares and ſubtle underminings of a Lover from ruining
the Fortreſs of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. See but the concluſive Example of 
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:175400:47"/>Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> and conſider what Husband, though
ever ſo jealous or politick, could have prevented the ſucceſs of ſuch
well-founded Deſigns? Who would have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented ſuch a ſubtilty as that of
Don <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho,</hi> or imagined that a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Duke, the Gravity
of whoſe Nation even out-does Gravity it ſelf, ſhould ſuffer himſelf
to be ſo blinded by ſo diſordered and vile a Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? And yet
Antiquity aſſures us, that a famous old Poet whoſe renown has ſo long
taken up ſuch room in the World, made himſelf be let down in a Basket
through a Window for the Love of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. I conclude therefore, that it is no
wonder Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> fell thus twice into an accident which he was
neither ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of, nor provided againſt; ſince the moſt ſubtle
and ſuſpicious do daily the ſame. But you may wonder at me, that I make
ſo many Conſiderations upon what ſerves ſo little to my Buſineſs;
that I thus give wing to my Quill, to precipitate me, like another
<hi>Icarus,</hi> into a Sea of vain Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, without having any other
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for my Error than a thouſand Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names of Fool and Ignorant. I take
Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to witneſs, it is not in my power to<pb n="85" facs="tcp:175400:47"/>do
otherwiſe, though I am often more vexed and enraged at my own prolixity, than
any one elſe can poſſibly be: And then it happens to me as to a Horſe
unaccuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to a large Carriere, who at firſt ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, flurts
ſometimes to the right hand and ſometimes to the left, making a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed 
<note n="*" place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> running at the Ring.</note>
                  <hi>Caracol:</hi> So always when my Pen
would begin to write after a long diverted Narration, my Fancy finds it ſelf
ſo dull and defective, that it is very difficult for it to return to the Clew
of the Diſcourſe which it left before, and wind it up hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly, without
making a great many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious faults and knotty incongruities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:175400:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>IT is accounted twenty Miles from the Inn of
<hi>Carçuela</hi> to the famous City of <hi>Toledo;</hi> The way is ſo
fair and even, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of that which we have left behind us, that a
Coachman coming there can hardly make his Horſes go quietly, they find the
Coach come ſo lightly along. This alacrity brought them with all ſpeed
imaginable within ſight of <hi>Toledo,</hi> the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſtatelineſs
of whoſe Buildings cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes no ſmall admiration in the beholders. Our
Ladies here were deſirous to alight within half a League of the City, to take
a view of that ſtately Caſtle which is ſo ſingular an Ornament to the
City, where the ſilver Streams of the River 
<note n="*" place="margin">Formerly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<hi>Tagus.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Tayo,</hi> conducted by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Art of the
fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Jago</hi> of <hi>Cremona</hi> in the Dutchy of <hi>Milan,</hi>
ariſe more pure than the moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd Cryſtal, falling into moſt
coſtly and curiouſly wrought Fountains in the Courts of the Caſtle. Their
curioſity alſo made them deſirous to take a view of the magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence 
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:175400:48"/>and incomparable Grandeur of the principal Church in which
the happy <hi>Ilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonſus</hi> received the 
<note n="*" place="margin">A ſort of Copes warn by the Prieſt
at Maſs.</note>
                  <hi>Chaſuble</hi> from the Hands of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin
Mother of God.</p>
               <p>All theſe Rarities, and many others, which this fair
Proſpect diſcovered, did ſo delight the Women, and eſpecially Donna
<hi>Margareta</hi> and her Waiting-Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen, that they begg'd of Don
<hi>Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> to ſpend four or five days in that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that they who
had never before ſeen ſuch Magnificences, might have a more leiſure view
of theſe. Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> to whom all things were indifferent,
provided he enjoyed but the fight of Donna <hi>Leonora,</hi> who was the Center
of all his Deſires, and the ſole Object of his Affections, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 
<q>Thou doſt not conſider, my Dear, that my Will ſo depends
on that of our Noble Company, that without them I can reſolve on nothing.</q>

                  <q>I queſtion not (replied Donna <hi>Margareta</hi>) to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
this favour of Don <hi>Sancho,</hi> if it be your pleaſure: And as for Donna
<hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora,</hi> it is enough that ſhe is a Woman, and therefore of the
ſame curioſity of ſeeing Novelties, as well as of the ſame 
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:175400:49"/>Sex with me, and thereore I need not doubt of her
conſent.</q> 
                  <q>Our chance in this is very ſiniſtre (replied Don
<hi>Sancho</hi>) to be intreated where we ought to be Suppliants, For I have in
<hi>Toledo</hi> an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair of very important concern, which I can conveniently
diſpatch whilſt I tarry here; and I aſſure you, Sir, that my care of my
own Concerns in this was ſo ſmall, that if Donna <hi>Margareta</hi> had not
deſired to ſtay here, I had paſſed on with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mentioning it, for fear
of loſing ſuch charming Company.</q> 
                  <q>We have been very unhappy (anſwered Don
<hi>Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi>) in this, that through all this Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney my Wife and I
have had no more opportunity to manifeſt the amity and affection we have for
you, ſince you could doubt of our granting you that which my Wife made no
queſtion of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining without difficulty of you.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Their Diſcourſes had proceeded further, for Don
<hi>Sancho</hi> (being an excellent Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier) had his Anſwer ready, if Donna
<hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora</hi> had not ſaid, 
<q>The fault is in my Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles want of Courage; for he is ſo
baſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that I that am but a Woman, do often both ſay and do things which
my<pb n="89" facs="tcp:175400:49"/>Uncle would not have the boldneſs to do, for fear of
being troubleſom.</q> 
                  <q>Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (ſaid Don <hi>Sancho</hi> ſmiling) I may chance
find occaſion to be revenged on you both more effectually than you would
perhaps deſire, and make one of you grant me to be a troubleſom Friend, and
the other a hardy man.</q> 
                  <q>Let us for the preſent wave theſe Complements (ſaid
Donna <hi>Margareta</hi>) and mind our way; and, if I be not much miſtaken, I
ſee a great many coming towards us on Horſeback.</q> 
                  <q>It is true (ſaid Don <hi>Sancho</hi>) and it would be
convenient to ask this man that comes here who they are.</q> This Traveller
being asked the queſtion, infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them, that they were Cavaliers of the
Countrey, who were returning from the City, where they had been ſeeing a
Combat of Bulls which had been there that day. 
<q>And for that reaſon (ſaid Don <hi>Sancho,</hi> having
diſmiſſed the Traveller) it were fit to ſend to our Servants to attend
us, that we may return to take Coach; for beſides theſe Cavaliers, we
ſhall meet abundance more People that are coming here on the other ſide;
and it would be a diſparagement to us to be<pb n="90" facs="tcp:175400:50"/>in this
equipage on foot.</q> 
                  <q>This cannot be done (replied the Company) for, Sir, the
Cavaliers you ſpeak of are ſo near us, that it is impoſſible for the
Coach to be here before them.</q> 
                  <q>Then all the means we have to amend this fault (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied Don
<hi>Sancho</hi>) of letting the Coach go ſo far from us, is to ſend them
word that they ſtay near the old Caſtle, which is in the half way to the
City, for it cannot be above a thouſand Paces from thence to the City; and
whilſt theſe Cavaliers paſs by, we may enter into this pleaſant
Foreſt, and take the Air amongſt the ſhadows of the Trees; for we have
time enough, and too much yet to go to <hi>Toledo,</hi> though we ſtay there
an hour.</q> This concluded on, they took a little Path which led them to the
Foreſt, where they were no ſooner entred, but they ſearched for the
moſt convenient and beſt ſhaded place to repoſe themſelves in, where
being ſate, they were moſt delightfully diverted by the charming Notes of
the Nightingale, and the melodious Conſort of the other little winged
Choriſters: But they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diſtinguiſhed from the other Notes one
which founded more of Art than the<pb n="91" facs="tcp:175400:50"/>reſt, which added
ſuch a charming ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to its natural perfection, that the
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Notes of Birds even ſeemed to ceaſe, as did the Diſcourſe
of our Cavaliers and Ladies, to liſten to that Voice, which with moſt
incomparable skill ſung this Song.</p>
               <q> 
                  <lg type="song">
                     <lg n="1">
                        <head>1.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>THe fair Enamel of the Fields,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The pretty Birds ſweet Harmony,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The gentle Blaſts which</hi> Zephyrus
<hi>yields,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Joyn to make time paſs pleaſantly.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <head>2.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Cryſtal Streams which from their
ſource</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Murmuring ſweetly, ſeparate,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And after joyning in their courſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Do raviſhing delights create.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <head>3.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O're verdant Meads and Fields to walk</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>On the ſoft Graſs, in Shades repoſe;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>By gliding Brooks to ſing and talk,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Where ſweeteſt Flow'rs their leaves
diſcloſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="4">
                        <head>4.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>All choiceſt ſorts of Fruits and Flowers</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In Orchards, Fields, and Gardens be,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="90" facs="tcp:175400:51"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="91" facs="tcp:175400:51"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="92" facs="tcp:175400:52"/>
                           <hi>The pleaſant Groves and
ſweeteſt Bowers</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>No pleaſure yield t' unhappy me.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="5">
                        <head>5.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O, what ſtrange ill diſturbs my Peace!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Since what ſuch joys to others brings,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Does make my Sorrows ſtill increaſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And adds weight to my Sufferings.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="6">
                        <head>6.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Flowers, Rivers, Shades, Fountains, &amp;
Groves,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In vain to me your Sweets you lend:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Inconſtant
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>e, another loves,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>On whom alone my Joys depend.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </lg> 
               </q>
               <p>This Song was finiſh'd with ſo feeling a ſorrow, and
ſuch admirable dexterity, that it aſtoniſh'd all the hearers, believing
that this voice proceeded not from any Mortal, but rather an Angel or
Celeſtial Spirit, that willing to delight himſelf in the admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his
own Excellencies, had choſen this Foreſt as the fitteſt place to lay his
Scene, delighting himſelf in his own voice, which the Eccho returned with
advantage at the end of every Verſe: And as they were get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up to turn
their eyes towards the place whence this voice came, they heard 
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:175400:52"/>the ſame Voice make this Complaint.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e are many
chuſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Flowery Meads and
pleaſant Shades for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eir
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement: But, alas! I c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſe a ſeat upon the Bank of this pretty Brook, there to lament
the evils I ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>er. Theſe fair
and ſhady Trees ſeem to me more ſharp and prickly than Thorns and
Thiſtles: The ſinging of the Birds ſeems to me as harſh and
diſagreeable as the noiſe of Screech-owls. Alas! can my eyes behold any
thing that does not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter a ſubject of ſorrow and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, in a
place where I find my ſelf a forlorn Exile, and have no other uſe for my
eyes but to ſhed tears. The Rocks and horrid Precipices, the ſavage
Beaſts, and the Rivers which ſeem to be ſwell'd bigger with my tears, are
faithful wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of my cruel Martyrdom and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting Torments.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words ended the Diſcourſe, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing interrupted by
the ſtorms of ſighs and ſhowers of tears which flowed from the
Complainer. After that Storm was a little blown over, this Diſcourſe
followed the former.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>How piercing are my ſorrows, that <pb n="94" facs="tcp:175400:53"/>ſeem
even to penetrate inſenſible things! The Groves, as concern'd at my
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, ſeem continually to reſound them to the neighbouring Plains:
Theſe Rocks, methinks, ſeem even cleft with their ſorrows, at the
mournful Songs with which I alleviate mine. When I conſider my ſelf plunged
into ſuch an abyſs of ſadneſs, baniſh'd from that light which
formerly ſhined upon me with ſo propitious an influence, into a ſtrange
Countrey, where nothing but miſhaps ſurround me, this is a torment too
inſupportable. And if amongſt this crowd of afflictions Sleep find an
oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to cloſe my eyes, its operation is contrary to what it is
deſigned for; for in ſtead of ſuſpending my cares, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing my
tired Body, my Dreams are ſo full of diſturbance and anguiſh, that my
ordinary moanings and complaints are more ſupportable than the heavineſs I
feel when I awake.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Upon finiſhing theſe words, ſhe begun again to bemoan her
ſelf with ſuch mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fui Language as was able to mollifie the hardeſt
Rock, ſaying, 
<q>To what end ſerve theſe Hands, this lately ſo much
admired<pb n="95" facs="tcp:175400:53"/>Beauty, the Nobility of my Birth, or theſe
reſentments of my misfortune? Since I am unable to be revenged of this
Traytor that has robb'd me of the richeſt Jewel I had, the loſs of which is
ſo much the greater, as it is utterly irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable: A Jewel without which a
Virgin becomes like a Flower ſcorched with the Suns heat, or like the Vine
whoſe tender Branches are pinched and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>illed by the nipping Froſt of a
cold Morning. O thou great Sovereign of of the World, who from thy Imperial
Throne doſt now behold an injuſtice done me, as great as the moſt
diſloyal wretch in the World could commit, ſide with me in the puniſhment
of a crime as offenſive to thy Majeſty as inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to my Honour: O
leave not this fault unpuniſh'd, thou who art the firm ſupport of the
innocent, and the ſcourge of Offenders. But, alas! un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy that I am, what
is it I ſay and wiſh againſt him in whom the Deſtinies have placed all
my happineſs, all my fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity and hopes, and without which my Life is no
more able to ſuſtain the aſſaults of Death, than Snow to reſiſt the
heat of <pb n="96" facs="tcp:175400:54"/>Fire. O ye fair Streams of <hi>Tayo,</hi> whoſe
rapid Courſes lead you to the beauteous City of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> do me the
kindneſs a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to deviate, and traverſing the deſart Rocks of
<hi>Siera Morena,</hi> plunge your ſelves into the ſacred <hi>Betis,</hi>
and with your confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed rumours tell him my ſoul adores, that his
diſloyalty and ingratitude have made me breathe out my ſoul in ſighs upon
your flowery Banks; and you my ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,
turn the current of your ſalt Strea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, which you ſhed day and night, to mix with the freſh ones of
<hi>Tayo,</hi> that if that friendly River do me this firſt and laſt
courteſie, you at leaſt may (which I can never do) kiſs the happy
Countrey of my once dear Lover.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Her mournful plaints and heavy accents ended with ſuch
profound ſighs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward groans, that all the Company roſe to ſee
whether ſhe (for by her voice and diſcourſe they knew her to be a Woman)
that uttered them had not ended her Life with her pittiful Regrets; and peeping
through ſome Branches which ſpread on that ſide whence the Voice came,
they ſaw a Lady ſitting by the ſide of a Rivolet which ſlowed into the
<hi>Taio,</hi> with her Head<pb n="97" facs="tcp:175400:54"/>mournfully hanging on one
ſide, and her Face towards the Water. Her Hair, though hanging careleſs,
and moved at the diſcretion of a gentle Wind, was of ſo lively a colour,
that the richeſt Gold of <hi>Arabia</hi> could not compare with it. She was
clothed in a Robe of black Velvet, embroidered with Flowers of Silver, with a
Star of Gold in the middle of each of them bordered with Cryſtal, which
joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the corners of every Flower in unequal meaſures, being made in the
ſhape of Loops, and button'd with Buttons of the Seed of Pearl: So that it
ſeemed Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had joyned all its ſubtilties in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the
Garment, as well as the Body. This coſtly Habit cauſed as much amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
in the beholders, as the former ſight of her lovely Hair had done. Her Head
was then bended down upon her Knees, which made them all unwilling to part
without knowing who ſhe was, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe, who ſeemed rather a
Divinity than a Mortal, were alive or dead. They were going to divide the
Boughs which hindred them with their Hands, and cut them with their Swords, and
ſo leap the Rivolet, which winding with a great many<pb n="98" facs="tcp:175400:55"/>circlings and turnings, made an Iſlet where the Lady ſate, but
were hindred by the approach of two Women of comely Meen towards the Lady, one
of which came and ſate down by her, and ſaid to her angrily theſe
words:</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>If I conſidered, ſo often as I adviſe you of your duty,
that my words ſerve to no other end but to ſpend my ſpirits, I ſhould
trouble you no more with my Diſcourſe, nor employ my time ſo
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably, to preach to you that are deaf to all I ſay; and all my
Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances and Reaſons, though never ſo good and pertinent, have no
more influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon you than upon a ſenſeleſs crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. I call Heaven
to witneſs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire no pardon for my ſins from thence if it be not
true, that your deſpair and melancholy have reduced me to that ſtate, that
they will at laſt bring me to my Grave, unleſs (taking pity of her that
next under God and your Parents has given you your being) you moderate your
paſſions, ſhewing us once more a chearful and contented look. And won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
not if I take your Intereſts ſo to heart, and that your ſorrow ſo
afflicts me;<pb n="99" facs="tcp:175400:55"/>ſince thoſe from whom you hold your Life,
and I my Livelihood, have obliged me to it by their Bounty. And what good can
you hope for from your ſighs? Can one, think you, find any that will be in
love with misfortunes and diſgraces, for the pleaſure they take in
bewailing them? Think you that your ſad counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and blubber'd eyes will
win more upon your wandering perfidious Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band (for ſo he is as
ſtrictly as Vows can bind) or ſooner reduce him to his duty, than if your
lovely Face take up again its former Arms, with which you vanquiſh'd him
before? No, no, Love is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed by ſuch ſiniſter ways, eſpecially
having the inconſtancy and ingratitude of ſuch a young man for Opponent.
Take example by other Ladies, who are ſo far from ſtriving, like you, to
disfigure their Faces, that they uſe all the Dreſſes, Fards, Perfumes,
Paints, and Pommades, to render themſelves more beauteous, and ſet them off
to the beſt advantage, not ſparing for any thing that may render them more
lovely, the better to win the hearts of their Lovers. You will tell me now,
that Lovers alſo are ſubject to<pb n="100" facs="tcp:175400:56"/>ſighs, and tears, and
complaints; which if I grant you, you muſt allow, that though they do it for
the preſent, they blame themſelves for it afterward, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that it
is better to paſs the time in a chearful enjoyment of what we poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs,
than to plunge ones ſelf into a Sea of ſorrow, which ruines the Beauty,
enervates the forces of the Body, and ſtupifies thoſe of the Soul: For what
reaſon have we to deſpair, ſince what ſeems impoſſible to day, is
very eaſie oft-times to morrow. You might have remarked this in your own
Affairs, which before ſeemed irremediable; but the good reception you have
had with the King makes us now not doubt of that ſucceſs which we could
ſcarce hope for before: And I remember that yeſterday you ſaid you did
not fear but that your Honour was ſafe, and your Buſineſs in a good
eſtate; and now 'tis ſtrange to ſee you ſo changed and afflicted, that
if I knew not your inconſtant and impatient humour, conſidering your Affair
is in ſo fair a condition of ſuiting to your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, I ſhould rather
fear this ſadneſs to be an Augury of ſome future miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, 
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:175400:56"/>than a bewailing of the former.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words were not ſpoken in vain; they wrought the ſame
effect in this affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Lady as Water, which thrown in the face of one in a
Swoon, does by its freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs recall the wandering ſpirits; for they
immediately retrived her from that depth of ſorrow and melancholy into which
the memory of her wrongs had plunged her: for now a modeſt Bluſh ſpread a
rare Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milion over her face, which was pale be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and as ordinarily
ſilence is moſt ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to an afflicted ſpirit, ſhe only ſhewed
her Governante a more chearful countenance than before, telling her, that ſhe
would endeavour always to ſatisfie her deſires, and at the ſame time
called her Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid (which was ſhe that came along be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with her
Governante) to dreſs her Head, during which imployment ſhe often ſtroked
her lovely Hair with her own fair Hand, which reſembled an Alabaſter
ſtone upon a Rock of Amber. O beauteous and dear Nets of amorous Hearts! the
Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrings of Love! O lovely Fingers, capable to play upon our Paſſions
like Virginals, and tune them to any ſort of Muſick.</p>
               <p>Our Company could not then behold<pb n="102" facs="tcp:175400:57"/>the face
of the Lady of the Stars (for ſo we muſt call her till we know her right
name) nor that of her Governante, who had by a long diſcourſe (which they
could not well hear) endeavoured to oppoſe her conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory remonſtrances
to the others grief: Yet they all reſolved, though with regret, to depart in
ignorance, leſt they ſhould be diſcovered by a Troop of Cavaliers and
Ladies which came walking by a Rivolet, and for fear of incurring the cenſure
which the pryers into others concerns merit. They concluded by the
circumſtances and occurrences beforemention'd, that the Lady of the Stars was
a ſtranger, and that the others that were coming were her Friends and
Servants, the moſt of them; and that making ſome ſtay at <hi>Toledo,</hi>
ſhe was come to walk and to divert her ſelf in this plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant place, with
all her Family, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſhun or alleviate the ſorrow which her
ſighs, her tears, and her words had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted her heart to be clogged
withal.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:175400:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>THe Conſiderations laſt mentioned in the foregoing Chapter
cauſed the departure of our Company out of the Shade where they were,
returning the ſame way they came, hoping to meet ſome body by the way, of
whom they might learn the Name of her whom all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany had ſuch a
deſire to know: And whilſt they were walking gently to the place where the
Coach attended them, every one made their particular judgment and remark upon
the Lady of the Stars, all but Donna <hi>Leonora,</hi> who ruminating upon what
ſhe had ſeen and heard, found her ſelf ſomewhat ſurprized at this
rencoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and therefore liſtned attentively to the reſt, without
deſcanting on it in one word, as the Company did. Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi>
ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſomewhat melancholy; approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her to know the cauſe. Don
<hi>Sancho</hi> and Donna <hi>Margareta</hi> ſeeing his intention, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to
mend their pace, and go a good way before, to give them the means of a private
entertainment, in talking of things<pb n="104" facs="tcp:175400:58"/>which might tend to
their future pleaſure and contentment. Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> ſeeing
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hereby at liberty to diſcover to Donna <hi>Leonora</hi> the
ſufferings which her Beauty had impoſed on him, after having asked her how
ſhe did, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>er her
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſure of ſpirit did not proceed from that of her Body, fell to
beholding her with more contemplative eyes than a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puchin</hi> or
<hi>Chartreux</hi> would do a Portraict of Devotion. He had already begun to
accoſt her with more than <hi>Mercurian</hi> elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, but his
Diſcourſe was interrupted by the abundance of ſights and ſobs, which by
the hardneſs of their paſſage ſeemed to be drawn from the very bottom
of his breaſt; but his Love recalling his Courage, and rallying his
diſperſed Spirits, he took the boldneſs to take hold of her curious Hand,
and preſſing it ſomewhat harder than before, he ſaid with the beſt
grace poſſible theſe words following.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>It is the common courſe of men of underſtanding, when they
find either Body or Mind oppreſſed by any Malady, firſt to find out a
Perſon proper and able to heal them, and then to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to him
for a Remedy, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe<pb n="105" facs="tcp:175400:58"/>a Cure, though accompanied
with the ſharpeſt Corroſives. Now, Madam, it is no longer time to
diſſemble, ſince your Beauty hath reduced me to that ſtate, that I can
find no way inſtrumental to my cure but by thus caſting my ſelf at your
feet, humbly to implore your pity, who alone can fit a Plaiſter to my Wound.
The ſcorching Rays of your Celeſtial Eyes have kindled ſuch a Flame in my
Heart, that nothing but ſome refreſhing drops of Pity can prevent the
reducing of it to Aſhes, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently my Body to the Grave. My
baſhfulneſs, and the fear of offending you, have hitherto reſtrained my
Tongue from diſcovering the inward pain I have endured ever ſince I firſt
ſaw you; and though I was always the moſt unwilling man alive to
diſpleaſe you, yet was I ſtill as unable to ſuppreſs the Civil broils
which Love and Fear raiſed in my Breaſt, till at laſt the former having
quite ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued the later, has brought me (like the poor haraſſed Countrey
which has long been the Seat of War) to joyn with the Conqueror, becauſe
unable to reſiſt him, and ſo, forced by his Commands,<pb n="106" facs="tcp:175400:59"/>I thus make uſe of this happy occaſion, to lay open my Wounds and
Torments to you, not deſpairing of a Cure from your Goodneſs, or that
Diſtemper which you have been the cauſe of. The very irrational Animals
teach us this by their example, who feeling themſelves hurt, do by a natural
inſtinct by their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainings diſcover it to men, to draw
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance from their pity. Theſe Reaſons, Madam, have made me
deſirous to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard your diſpleaſure, to know from your Sentence whether
I muſt live to ſerve you, or die to appeaſe your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure: And if
your curioſity make you deſirous to try the influence which the Rays of
your Divine Beauty have up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Spirit, approach but with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of pity my
ſad and afflicted Breaſt, and you ſhall ſee that the Sun does not more
gild and enliven the ſad and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Fields with his warmth and light,
when parting from his nocturnal Horizon he returns in the Morning to our
Hemiſphere, than a pleaſing look from your charming eyes would infuſe
into my languiſhing heart.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Donna <hi>Leonora,</hi> though more invited to 
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:175400:59"/>laughter than pity by ſo pleaſant and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant a
Diſcourſe, yet comporting her ſelf the beſt ſhe could, and turning
her eyes very modeſtly on one ſide, ſhe ſpoke with a low voice theſe
words following.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>There is no confidence to be put in Men of this Age, for (as
we may ſee by the late Example of the fair afflicted Lady) their treachery
and infidelity does now ſeem to be arrived at the laſt ſtage of its
greatneſs; ſo that every Woman that ſhews her ſelf favourable to their
prayers, and condeſcends to their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties, finds at once her
inconſiderate facility, and great ſimplicity in heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to their
deceitful words, rewarded with ſhame, contempt, and diſdain.</q>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <q>O puiſſant Love (replied Don <hi>Sebaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>) give
me a perſwaſive ſpirit, that autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing my Allegations with the
ſtrongeſt Oaths, and grandeſt Exaggerations, I may leave this fair
Incredulous ſatisfied of the reality of the torments I ſuffer for her. No,
Faireſt, the revolution of the Stars, the accidents and inconſtancy of
Fortune, nor all the rigorous cruelty (my Dear Lady) which you can poſſibly
invent againſt me, though they be Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <pb n="108" facs="tcp:175400:60"/>violent
and ſtrong enough to beat down and ruine the firmeſt affection, ſhall
never be able to efface your Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits printed in my heart, nor the lively Image
of your Perfections which Love hath there engraven; but contrarily, ſuch
unhappy miſcariages will ſtill frame new deſigns of vanquiſhing the
greateſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities, till at laſt (like <hi>Hercules,</hi> more
advantaged by the difficulty of his undertakings) I thereby win the Palm from
all the other Lovers of this Age.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Donna <hi>Leonora</hi> hearing theſe words, was forced to
reſtrain her laughter more ſtrongly than before, finding it ſtill more
earneſt to break priſon, and would have anſwered him again, had ſhe not
been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by the fear ſhe had of not being any longer able to act
well a part ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper to her Sex: Therefore knowing that bare Complements
would not ſerve on this occaſion, ſhe had recourſe to her Eyes, which
are fitter inſtruments of deceit than the Tongue in ſuch an affair; ſince
often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a Servant ſeeing his Miſtreſſes Eyes fixed on him, or
ſtealing glances at him, does with joy conceive a hope that thoſe Eyes are
the Meſſengers of Love, which<pb n="109" facs="tcp:175400:60"/>are but the Spies of his
Imperfections: Beſides, the Tongue cannot ſo eaſily utter choice or
pathetick expreſſions to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for the mind being taken up with
the thoughts of ſomething that is moſt pleaſing to it, makes the Tongue
unable to belie the Heart, binding it up from its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer liberty, and thereby
diſabling it from ſaying what it would: But the Eyes the mean time are
unconcerned in that paſſion.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> ſeeing himſelf ſo firmly viewed
by thoſe Eyes which had before been Burning-glaſſes to his Heart,
imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Love to be already victorious, and thefore deſirous to lay hold
on the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſtretched out his Arms to embrace that Body which had the
night before been both active and paſſive in others far more agreeable.
Donna <hi>Leonora</hi> ſhewing a force and addreſs with ſomewhat more
than a Female ſtrength, eſcaped ſo nimbly from his Arms, that Don
<hi>Sebaſtian</hi>'s ecſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of joy almoſt depriving him of
ſenſe, he amorouſly kiſſed and embraced the Air. 
<q>O bold Lover! (ſaid Donna <hi>Leonora</hi>) are theſe the
means to win my favour? No, no, Services and Civilities, courteous
entertainments and generous deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments<pb n="110" facs="tcp:175400:61"/>are the ways
whereby Ladies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are obtained, and not with ſuch raſh and daring
attempts as this.</q> But ſeeing his aſtoniſhment, ſhe continued thus,
with a more favourable look; 
<q>For this time, Seignour Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> I pardon
you, on condition you fall no more into the like offence; and let me entreat
you that we may mend our pace, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take our Company, leſt my Uncle
ſhould ſuſpect ſomething of what is paſt. As for the reſt, leave it
to time, which will convince me (though you be never ſo ſubtle) whether
your Diſcourſes proceed from a real love, or a fained affection, or only to
give ſcope to your Wit, and try the ſtrength of my Judgment.</q>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <q>My death (anſwered Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi>) ſhall
ſatisfie you in that immediately, if you have neither faith, nor pity of one
who loves you more than himſelf.</q> 
                  <q>No, no, fear not dying of this diſtemper (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied Donna
<hi>Leonora</hi>) for your Phyſician will rather try all Experiments which
ſhall be judged neceſſary for your reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</q> 
                  <q>O my deareſt hope and life (ſaid Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi>)
if you keep your word I ſhall account my ſelf the happieſt Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier 
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:175400:61"/>in <hi>Europe.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <q>Content your ſelf for the preſent with what I have ſaid
(anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Donna <hi>Leonora</hi>) for I ſhould be as ſorry my rigour
ſhould be inſtrumental to the death of ſo brave and generous a Cavalier,
and one whoſe exemplary ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility has obliged me, as I ſhould be
unfortunate if my Uncle ſhould know the care I take for his ſafety: And let
theſe two Motives oblige us to break off this Converſation for the
preſent.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> notwithſtanding the laſt words of
this Diſcourſe, was ſo intranced with joy for the former, and even
tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported out of himſelf, to have received an anſwer ſo much better
than he could hope for, that had ſhe not recalled him to himſelf by twice
or thrice ſpeaking to him, he had been metamorphoſed into a Stone, like
another 
<note n="*" place="margin">Whom <hi>Mercury</hi> turn'd into a
Stone for diſcovering his Theft.</note>
                  <hi>Battus;</hi> but recollecting his
ſpirits, after ſuch ſhort acknowledgments as his ſudden ecſtaſie
would allow, they marched more nimbly than before to overtake their Company,
who were ſtaying by the way, and talking with ſome Coachmen and Servants
whom they ſuppoſed to belong to the Lady of the <pb n="112" facs="tcp:175400:62"/>Stars,
which indeed proved to be true, and ſo was that which they before imagined of
her; and one of thoſe Servants gave them this account. 
<q>Gentlemen, we are Servants to one of the greateſt Lords of
<hi>Toledo,</hi> by whoſe command we conducted this ſtrange Lady (which you
ſaw within the Foreſt) into that place, which for its pleaſure and
divertiſements ſeems to be a Terreſtrial Paradiſe, that ſhe and all
her Family might recreate themſelves amongſt thoſe pretty Flowers and
clear Streams.</q> 
                  <q>And can you not tell me her Name? (ſaid Donna
<hi>Leonora.</hi>)</q> 
                  <q>No (ſaid the Coachman) but I know ſhe is of great Quality,
becauſe the King being at <hi>Toledo</hi> when ſhe arrived, ſhe waited on
him to requite Juſtice for an Injury that has been done her by ſome Grandee
of this Kingdom; and it was reported at Court, that his Majeſty had received
her very graciouſly, and had no ſooner read a Letter which the Infanta,
Governeſs of <hi>Flanders,</hi> had ſent him in her behalf, and heard from
her the Particulars of the Cauſe for which ſhe deſired Juſtice, but he
diſpatch'd away a Party of his Guards to ſeize upon him ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained 
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:175400:62"/>of, though he be very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at Court; for the
King declared, that Greatneſs ſhould be no more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from Juſtice than
Poverty; and whatever place they have near him, that his Favour ſhall be no
bar to his Juſtice. For her Beauty, it is beyond compare, and none that have
yet ſeen her but ſay, they have never before beheld the like, and that it
is almoſt impoſſible ſo much Perfection ſhould be poſſeſſed
by one leſs than immortal.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Here the Coachman ended his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe, being interrupted by
a young man of good faſhion who ſtood by, and ſaid, 
<q>If, Gentlemen, you have a deſire to know this beauteous
Stranger, as by your Diſcourſe I judge you have, you may eaſily do it if
you pleaſe to lodge in our Houſe, where, beſides your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in
ſeeing this Lady, you will find an Inn which, not only in reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but in
effect is one of the beſt in all <hi>Caſtile.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <q>In what Quarter of the Town is it? (ſaid Don
<hi>Sebaſtian.</hi>)</q> 
                  <q>It is (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the young man) in the middle of the firſt
Street which you ſhall come at after you have paſſed the
<hi>Cocodober.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:175400:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>They all agreed to go
thither; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diſmiſſed the Coachmen and the other Servants, they
poceeded on their way. They ſoon got to the Ruines of the Old Caſtle where
their Coach at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended them, whereinto being entred, they quickly arrived at the
City, and paſſing through the Bridge-gate, went to lodge at the Inn we
juſt now ſpoke of, where we will leave them to take up their Quarters, and
return to the Lady we left in the Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:175400:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>THe duskiſhneſs of the Evening had already begun to gain
upon the Light, and Night begun to unfold her dark Veil to ſpread over the
face of the Earth: The Gallants begun to return home, ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the
Pleaſures of the foregoing Day: The jolly Shepherd with his Whiſtle begun
to ſummon his Flocks, loaded with Wooll and Fleſh, to their Folds; and the
Traveller, though wearied with the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of the day, doubled his pace, to
avoid ſecurely in his Inn the incommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the night; when this fair
Lady of the Stars departed from the pleaſant place where we left her, her
Governeſs having firſt by her ſolid perſwaſions and ſage
coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels retired her from the abyſs of ſorrow into which ſhe had
plunged her ſelf, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſaid, It is time for us to return to the City,
and I am of advice, that, for the better variety of Recreation, <hi>Dorida</hi>
ſhould ſing to her Guittar ſome pleaſant and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſing Song, which
may make the way we have to go to the Coach ſeem ſhorter. 
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:175400:64"/>I will do what you pleaſe, Madam, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<hi>Dorida;</hi> and to teſtifie my joy to ſee my Lady ſo well recovered
of her me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy humour, I will ſing you of the Adventures of a
<hi>Portuguez</hi> Draper, to whom his Miſtris had given an Aſſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
which ſucceeded unfortunately: And though the words of it are none of the
ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableſt in the mouth of a Maid, yet I will venture on it, Madam, if you
pleaſe to give me permiſſion. I give it you (replied the Governante) for
I partly know the effect of it. Give me my Guittar (ſaid <hi>Dori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi>)
and for once I will make bold with Modeſty. Having taken and tuned it, ſhe
plaid ſo dexterouſly on it, that ſhe ſtruck an admiration into all that
heard it: But when ſhe ſung, it was hard to judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her Vocal or
Inſtrumental Muſick were more delightful. The Song (which was one of the
ſame fame in <hi>Spain</hi> as thoſe of <hi>Robin Hood</hi> in
<hi>England</hi>) was of a <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guez</hi> Draper, who coming to
<hi>Caſtile,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came enamour'd of a pretty young Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that was lately
married to a certain Villager of the Countrey called <hi>The Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha;</hi> and
one day as he was ſelling her ſome Cloth, he opened to her his Cloth 
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:175400:64"/>and Affection together. She who was as cunning as any of
her Neighbours, ſeemed to receive it kindly, but immediately told her Husband
of it, who (as crafty as ſhe) ordered her to give him an Aſſignation to
come and enjoy her, which ſhe failed not to do, nor he to come accordingly.
He was no ſooner unclothed, and one foot in the Bed, but the Husband, who was
hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den hard by, accompanied with four or five Friends, entertained him ſo
unhoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably with horrible blows, that though he was naked, and the Weather
cold, he was glad that he could get alive out of their hands, and ſo ſcape
home with his Limbs unbroken, though deſparately bruis'd.</p>
               <p>The Verſes run pleaſantly in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> though
without Ryme, without which neither <hi>French</hi> nor <hi>Engliſh</hi> ones
have any grace; and <hi>Dorida</hi> ſung them ſo grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, that all the
Company was ſo well pleaſed with the Baſtinadoes of the
<hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guez</hi> Draper, that it was a good while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could give
over laughing; but the Night drawing on, and they being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at the place
where the Coach at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended them, they were forced to end their divertiſements,
and every one to take their<pb n="118" facs="tcp:175400:65"/>places in the Coach; and the
Boot being pluck'd up, the Coachman drove ſo ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, that in leſs than
a quarter of an Hour they got to the Inn, where Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> and
his Company were before arrived, and after much inquiry in the Houſe, not
able to learn the Name of the Lady of the Stars; were all retired to their
ſeveral Beds.</p>
               <p>Let us leave them to their Reſt, and whilſt they ſleep,
ſlip back to <hi>Viſo,</hi> to ſee what the matter is there; for I have
heard ſuch a noiſe, methinks, there, within theſe three days ſince we
left it, that I fear For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune has been playing ſome of her wonted freaks, and
changed all their pleaſures into ſadneſs; which, if it be ſo, you
ſhall know preſently in the next Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Third Part.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:175400:65"/>
            <head>THE AMOROUS TRAVELLERS, OR THE
<hi>Night-Adventures.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>PART IV.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Queſtion not but your memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is good enough to retain the
Story I told you of Don <hi>Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi>'s Cloke, which he left with
<hi>Catalina</hi> at <hi>Viſo</hi> (on another account than <hi>Joſeph</hi>
did his with his Miſtris) as a recompence for the Courteſie he received of
her, or at leaſt to exempt her from the Chaſtiſement her Husband would
have given her, if he had not left it to bear off the Blows. The ſame day
that Don <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtian</hi> parted from <hi>Viſo, Roderigo</hi> (a man 
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:175400:66"/>as extremely covetous as wicked, being far more deſirous
of a full Purſe than a clear Conſcience) went out alſo towards <hi>Sancta
Cruz</hi> to ſell the Cloke; where ſo ſoon as he was arrived, and had
given the Inn-keeper charge of his things, he went into the Town to find a
Broker of ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand Clothes, or, to ſpeak more plainly, a worſe Rogue
than himſelf, to help him to a Chapman for his Cloke, or elſe to buy it
himſelf. It was not long before he found one of his Acquaintance, to whom
(after the accuſtomed Complements be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Perſons of their quality) he
told him in ſhort the cauſe of his Journey. Get you home to your Inn
(ſaid the other) bring you the ſubtileſt Taylor in the World, who ſhall
in the turning of a hand ſo metamorphoſe and diſguiſe it, that the
Owner himſelf ſhould never know it. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derigo</hi> well ſatisfied
with the Broker's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, returned to his Inn, where, as he was entring, he
found himſelf ſeiſed on by two Serjeants, and immediately after heard the
voice of another, of ſomewhat greater authority than the reſt, which
animated them, as the Captain of a Galley does his<pb n="121" facs="tcp:175400:66"/>Slaves,
ſaying, Hold him faſt, my Mates, and take ſpecial care he eſcape not;
for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the marks given us of him, this is queſtionleſs the Thief
we ſeek for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Roderigo</hi> ſeeing himſelf taken, and called by his
right name, remained ſo aſtoniſh'd that he knew not where he was, and
being to anſwer to the Interrogatories put to him, his fear made him
ſtammer ſo at every word, that it made all the by-ſtanders think him
guilty. Wherefore bringing him to his Chamber, whither preſently all the
Serjeants and <hi>Algnazils</hi> of the Town en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, partly to aid their
Companions if need were, and partly to ſteal all they could conveniently lay
hands on; they preſently ſtripp'd poor <hi>Roderigo</hi> to his Shirt, and
ſearch'd him from Head to Foot, to ſee if they could find any thing of that
which had been ſtoln; but ſeeing that all their diligence was in vain, not
having found about him above fifteen or twenty Reals, of which the
Commiſſary made himſelf Maſter, they went preſently to ſeiſe on a
Bundle, which by chance they eſpied at the corner of the Chamber, and
open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, they found there Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi>'s Cloke. I'le loſe my
Head, ſaid the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſary,<pb n="122" facs="tcp:175400:67"/>if this be not a
Highway-man; his very looks, and this Cloke, which without queſtion he hath
tobb'd ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of in theſe Mountains, betray him. Uſe me civilly,
Maſter Commiſſaty, (ſaid <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derigo,</hi> now ſomewhat better
encouraged) for I take Heaven to witneſs, that if you ſearch from the one
Pole to the other, you ſhall not find an honeſter man than my ſelf (God
bleſs the King) nor one that makes more profeſſion of Honour: And thank
God that theſe Poultrons hold my hands, for if I were at liberty, I ſwear
by the Ete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal — that I would — O im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent Thief! (ſaid the
Commiffary, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him three or four ſmart blows over the Pate with a
Cudgel) doſt thou ſpeak thus boldly to Juſtice it ſelf? I aſſure
thee, that if thou bridle not thy Tongue better, I will ſend thee to the
Gallows immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately. I hope God will not give thee the power (ſaid the
Priſoner) but I beſeech him to let me live (as I hope I ſhall) to ſee
thee and thy damn'd Companions ſtretch'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Wheel.</p>
               <p>Theſe words put the Commiſſary and his Mates in ſuch a
rage, that for all the Hoſt cried out on them to let him go, and 
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:175400:67"/>he would anſwer for his forth-coming; and although he
that had been robb'd, being there, cried out, Let him go, Sirs; for he that you
torment ſo cruelly is not the man that robb'd me; for all this theſe
enraged Officers (having the Law in one hand and Cudgel in the other) followed
on their mercileſs ſtrokes, and beat him like Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and after dragg'd
him to priſon, all bruis'd and batter'd as he was, without giving leave to
the Clerk to write his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, or draw his Proceſs. The Hoſt being
Friend to <hi>Roderigo,</hi> ſent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently away to advertiſe his Uncle
of his misfortune, who no ſooner heard it, but he came preſently to
<hi>Sancta Cruz,</hi> which was but two Leagues from <hi>Viſo.</hi> Being
arrived, he ſollicited the buſineſs ſo dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, giving ample
teſtimonies of his Nephew's honeſty, that thoſe, joyned with ſome Money
which he disburſed, fetch'd him out of Priſon in two days, with the
reputation of one of the honeſteſt men in <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having diſpatch'd this unlucky Affair, they both returned to
<hi>Viſo,</hi> carrying the Cloke along with them, which had coſt them as
much as it did Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> when<pb n="124" facs="tcp:175400:68"/>he bought it
new. By the way <hi>Ozmin</hi> (for ſo was <hi>Roderigo</hi>'s Uncle call'd)
asked his Nephew whence he had this Cloke which had coſt them ſo much money
and trouble. <hi>Roderigo</hi> was aſhamed to anſwer him; but ſeeing him
perſiſt in and continue his demands, and thinking the buſineſs would
come out firſt or laſt, anſwered him, I acknowledge, Uncle, that my
Wiſe and I have done you wrong in this conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I underſtand thee not
(replied <hi>Oz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min.</hi>) The truth is (ſaid <hi>Roderigo</hi>) my Wife got
this Cloke from one that belonged to the Cavalier that lay at your Houſe in
my abſence. I remember no ſuch thing (ſaid <hi>Ozmin</hi>) for I know not
that there has been a Cloke loſt in my Houſe this two years; and if there
were, I am not ſo old but my memory is good enough to remember it. At this
rate there muſt be ſome Myſtery hid in this Cloke (ſaid
<hi>Roderigo,</hi> not imagining the loſs of his Honour, or his Wifes
Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity) for why ſhould my Wife tell me ſo, if it were not true? I know
not what my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery there ſhould be (ſaid <hi>Ozmin</hi>) but this I am
ſure of, that (thanks be to God) there has been no Cloke loſt in my Houſe
this two year; for if there had, it would have<pb n="125" facs="tcp:175400:68"/>been ask'd
for: Therefore either thy Wife deceives thee (if this be true thou telleſt
me) or elſe thou haſt ſtole it ſomewhere elſe, and wouldeſt do ſo
me. I am bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aſſured of my innocence in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (ſaid
<hi>Roderigo</hi>) than of what I ſhould ſay to it: But if you pleaſe,
Uncle, to be but patient till we get home, I will either know the meaning of
it, or ceaſe to be <hi>Roderigo.</hi> We ſhall know that anon (ſaid
<hi>Ozmin</hi>) and I wiſh I prove a falſe Prophet. Theſe Diſcourſes,
and others they uſed by the way about the Money they had disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
laſted them to <hi>Viſo,</hi> where being entred their Houſe, the firſt
thing they did, <hi>Ozmin</hi> called for his Niece, and the Boy, and Maid, and
taking the Cloke out of a Bag, Which of you (ſaid he) knows of any one of
thoſe that lodged here lately that has loſt this Cloke? Which of them do
you mean? (ſaid the Boy.) Of thoſe that lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here whilſt
<hi>Roderigo</hi> was in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, ſaid <hi>Ozmin.</hi> Do you mean him
(ſaid the Boy) that had a Coat of Tawney-co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour'd Cloth embroiderd with
Gold? The very ſame, ſaid <hi>Ozmin.</hi> It cannot be (ſaid the Boy) for
none of them enquired for any. Look you now (ſaid <hi>Ozmin,</hi> turning 
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:175400:69"/>the Cloke, and viewing his Nephew) did I not ſay as
much? He was going to anſwer, but was interrupted by the Boy (who therein was
even with his Miſtris for his former unjuſt cudgelling) who ſaid very
confidently, Sir, this Cloke belongs to none of the Cavaliers you ſpeak of,
but to the Cavalier who lay here with his Wife the ſame night that your
Nephew <hi>Roderigo</hi> came home from the Countrey. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> is in
the right (ſaid the Maid) I know the Cloke by the Lace and the Lining, for
Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> gave it me to keep when he came in, and it was in my
Maſter's Chamber till his Page fetch'd it away. That's very true (ſaid
<hi>Ozmin</hi>) for going for my own, I found it there. <hi>Catalina</hi>
ſeeing her ſelf convinced by ſo many Witneſſes, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by
remorſe of Conſcience, ſaid no more than if ſhe had been a Marble
Statue, knowing that all her feminine craft and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty could neither
remedy ſo far gone a miſchief, nor contradict ſo apparent a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. The
name of Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> infuſed ſuſpicion into the head of
<hi>Roderigo,</hi> and that made him call to mind, that the day after his
arrival his Wife had her eyes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually fix'd upon him: And ſeeing that 
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:175400:69"/>her very looks diſcover'd her, as well as the
teſtimonies of the Servants, he conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the Cloke was an infallible
proof of her Adultery: Wherefore taking her by the hand, and leading her into
her Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles Chamber, he ſpake thus to his Uncle. 
<q>I muſt now ſpeak a word or two to this impudent Woman, to
have of her an entire relation of this Affair; and I firmly ſwear by
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> That if ſhe confeſs not the truth freely, I will be her
Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner my ſelf, and hang her at the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-window.</q> So having
ſhut the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-door, he begun to recount her ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to her Uncle,
and the crafts and inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhe had uſed to get Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi>
conveyed out of the Chamber (for he was confident they were uſed to that
end.) The poor <hi>Catalina</hi> did nothing the while but weep, ſeeing her
ſelf more than ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convicted: But her Husband more near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
touched with the loſs of his Honour than the ſorrow of his Wife,
tranſported with choler, took a Cord which he found under a Bed in the
Chamber, and ſpoke to her as followeth: 
<q>If thou deſireſt a longer time to live and repent thy
ſins, it is in thy power, if (leaving the cuſtom <pb n="128" facs="tcp:175400:70"/>of
common Offenders, who by impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently denying their offences folliſhly think
to conceal that which is apparent to all the World) thou telleſt me freely,
and without conſtraint, the naked truth of what I ſhall demand: if ſo, I
ſwear and promiſe thee faithfully to pardon this fault, upon condition that
thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver commit ſuch another; otherwiſe thou ſhalt know by the cruel
torments which I have prepared for thee (ſhewing her the Cord) that death
were a thouſand times more deſirable for thee than life.</q> The poor
afflicted <hi>Catalina,</hi> melting her ſelf in tears, begun to look upon
her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band with a countenance ſo ſad and pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that (had ſhe
been guilty of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt crime) it had moved compaſſion in the
cruelleſt <hi>Cannibal</hi> or moſt barbarous <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian;</hi> and after
a while, her ſorrow gave her leave to utter theſe words.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>What would you have me ſay? wretched and unfortunate that I
am! ſince my words, though never ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, will be equally fatal with
my ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: But ſince my Offence has brought me to ſo extreme a
miſery, that which way ſoever I turn me, I ſee none but 
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:175400:70"/>terrible and frightful ſpectacles, which repreſent
nothing but death, and that with the grateſt horrour, let death come then
when it will, it cannot but be very acceptable, ſince it will put an end to
all my ſufferings: Kill then, <hi>Roderigo,</hi> O kill thy unfortunate Wife,
ſince ſhe hath violated that Faith and Promiſe ſhe made to thee, and
which even the moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of Women are bound to obſerve: Let me die
then, ſince I have deſerved it, and revenge with thy own hand the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry I
have done to thee onely. I confeſs I have made uſe of ſo much impudence
in committing adultery with Don <hi>Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> that I have now none
left to deny it; or if I ſhould, there are witneſſes enough, beſides my
own Conſcience, to contradict me; even this very Cloke, if it could ſpeak,
would teſtifie againſt me, and diſcover my guilt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This penitent ſinner here ended her Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe, and her
tongue remaining fixed to the roof of her mouth, and her courage failing her
with her ſtrength, ſhe ſunk down in a ſwoon upon the floor. Her Husband
thereupon ran to her to Poniard her, and had undoubtedly done it if his Uncle
had<pb n="130" facs="tcp:175400:71"/>not detained him, who afflicted with this accident, and
touched with compaſſion at the ſighs and tears of his unhappy Niece,
ſtaid his Nephews hand, and ſaid, 
<q>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate a little thy paſſion, my dear Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, and give
not ſuch ſcope to thy cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; let her live, that is the greateſt
vengeance thou canſt take of her, ſince the apprehenſion of death is a
thouſand times more afflictive to a Criminal than death it ſelf: Be
patient, there is remedy for all, and conſider the beſt way to ſalve thy
Honour. I find my ſelf in this almoſt as much offended as thy ſelf, and
therefore beg of thee that we may no further publiſh our diſgrace,
becauſe yet none knows it beſides our ſelves. And think not light of this
advice, ſince there are many that if they thought their affronts and
diſgraces were ſecret, and unknown to others, would be ſo far from thus
reſenting ſuch a private injury, that they would rather endeavour to get
what money they could of the Agreſſor to keep it ſo ſtill. Then bridle
thy cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and ſheath thy Poniard, and beware of doing that in haſte
which thou wilt have time enough to repent. That we<pb n="131" facs="tcp:175400:71"/>may
therefore conſider of what we have to do, come along with me, and let us
leave this wicked Woman to her tears and lamentations, whilſt we ſtudy a
cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtizement worthy of her offence.</q> With theſe Reaſons and ſome
other he got him out of the Chamber, and locked the door after him, and brought
his Nephew to a Cloſet, where taking a Bag out of a Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, wherein there
might be about ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Reals, he ſpoke as followeth.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>I know that the wiſeſt man in the World would find a hard
task of it, to reſiſt his juſt reſentments of ſuch an accident; but
far harder to pardon his Wife for it: and much more thou, who art naturally of
ſo impatient and chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick a temper. I love you both as my own Children,
having intended you for my Heirs, and as ſuch I would uſe and entertain
you; but ſeeing that from this Affair one can expect nothing but ſome
unhappy ſiniſtre accident which might hazard the loſs of you both, if I
endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour not to prevent it by the removal of one, I have to this purpoſe
invented a remedy, which my long experience in the World has brought into my
mind,<pb n="132" facs="tcp:175400:72"/>which is this, that thou take this money, and a
Horſe which I ſhall give thee (for I can imagine no other cure more proper
for the preſent diſtemper) and go ſerve the King for ſome time in
ſome of his Armies, and I aſſure my ſelf that time will make thee
forget what is paſt, chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when at thy return thou ſhalt find thy Wife
more humble, more tractable, and more diligent to pleaſe thee than before;
for Women in her condition find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves commonly ſo confuſed and
aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that never after they dare ſpeak but with great reſpect, and
moreover ſtudy nothing but to obey, knowing that their fault has made them
forfeit their priviledge of Domeſtick Command.</q> Theſe were
<hi>Ozmin</hi>'s perſwaſions to his Nephew.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Roderigo,</hi> who was of himſelf a jolly Fellow, young
and hardy, having before his Marriage made divers Voyages into <hi>France,
Italy, Germany,</hi> and the <hi>Indies,</hi> and underſtood that kind of
life as well as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, gave an attentive ear to his Uncle; and remembring
himſelf of the time paſt, and his old Camerades, he thought he might now
with Money in his Purſe appear<pb n="133" facs="tcp:175400:72"/>better amongſt them, and
find more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in a Military life, than when his indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency forced him
to expoſe himſelf to a thouſand dangers to get a living. He therefore
took the ſix hundred Reals, and three hundred more which he accepted of in
ſtead of a Horſe, chuſing rather to march on foot with them, than on
Horſeback without them, and ſet out the ſame day, without taking leave of
his Wife, and bent his Courſe towards the <hi>Mancha;</hi> where we will
leave him to his Journey, becauſe the chearful voices of pretty Birds tell us
that the Morning approaches, and that therefore we are expected by the
Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers and Ladies which we left in Bed at <hi>Toledo,</hi> when we returned
from thence to <hi>Viſo,</hi> to take an Account and make you a Relation of
what is paſſed: And I am afraid they are by this angry at me for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging
my Pen ſo long in ſo mean and pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful a Subject, which was before
buſied with others of as great concern as any that can be imagined in matters
of Love.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:175400:73"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>THe Clock had ſcarce ſtruck Eight, when all our Company that
came from the Inn of <hi>Carçuela</hi> were riſen, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept Don
<hi>Carlos</hi> and Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> the torment of whoſe amorous
thoughts ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kept them waking all night, made them glad to make amends in
the morning. Don <hi>Carlos</hi> awaked firſt, and calling to mind his good
fortune the night before at the <hi>Carçuela,</hi> he eſteemed
himſelf the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieſt man alive, and praiſed Don <hi>Sancho</hi> a
thouſand times for his ſubtle invention, whereby he had had the enjoyment
of his Miſtris. The contentments he had alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy received, made him far more
earneſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter others, and made him far more deſirous than before of
another nights enjoyment: But ſeeing the grand difficulties, or rather the
abſolute impoſſibilities which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed it, as well for the
difficulty of continuing his Diſguiſe much longer, as alſo in regard that
the Inns betwixt <hi>Toledo</hi> and <hi>Madrid,</hi> being the beſt in
<hi>Spain,</hi> would never admit of ſuch another device as that 
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:175400:73"/>of the <hi>Carçuela;</hi> this conſideration put
him into ſuch an inquietude, and afflicted him in ſuch manner, as none is
able to judge of but ſuch as have felt the like; particularly, when he
conſidered the delicious pleaſures he had enjoyed in her Arms, when his
eyes beheld her with ſuch infinite delight, and his lips ſucked ſuch
raviſhing <hi>Ambroſia</hi> from hers: It was then, I ſay, when the
paſt joys coming ſo freſhly into his mind, touched him with ſuch
piercing ſmarts, and irreſiſtible paſſions, that they reduced him to
ſuch a condition, that ſometimes he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained without motion like a dead
man, and ſometimes with ſuch ſtrange and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant actions, as if he
had been quite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides himſelf; the poor Cavalier giving ſufficient
teſtimony, by ſuch irregular moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that he was in the height of his
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, and ſuffered as great a torment as one in the higheſt fit and
moſt violent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of a Fever, being without hope that Don
<hi>Sancho</hi> ſhould give a ſecond help to his pain, which thought made
him ſo wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this World, that he was almoſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſend himſelf
by a violent death into the other.</p>
               <p>The ſame morning, after all were up ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept 
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:175400:74"/>Donna <hi>Leonora</hi> who pretended to be indiſpoſed,
Don <hi>Sancho</hi> led out Don <hi>Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> to walk and take the Air
in a great Gallery of the Houſe which looked to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Corodober,</hi>
thereby to give time to Donna <hi>Margareta</hi> to viſit Donna
<hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora,</hi> that the two Lovers might have time to content their
deſires. Donna <hi>Margareta,</hi> that ſhe might not let ſlip ſo fair
an occaſion, as ſoon as ſhe ſaw her Husband go with Don <hi>Sancho</hi>
to the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, went ſtraight to Donna <hi>Leonora</hi>'s Chamber, where
they eaſily found occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to diſmiſs their Attendants: What they did
there, is fitter for you to imagine than me to recite; I ſhall onely ſay,
that if Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> (whoſe impatiency not ſuffering him to
ſtay long in any place, had made him with Prayers to force Don
<hi>Sancho</hi> to return to Donna <hi>Leonora</hi>'s Chamber to viſit her)
if he, I ſay, had deferred his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming but a little longer, he had
undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caught our two Lovers in the fact; for juſt as they opened the
door, they were ſhuffling the Cards to deal about for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Game: But for
all their goods the Fates had ordered it otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> being entred, took a Seat 
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:175400:74"/>and ſate down by Donna <hi>Leonora</hi>'s Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide,
and asked how ſhe did. Donna <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora</hi> for the preſent
counterfeiting ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what a weaker voyce than ordinary, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring by her
carriage to ſhew all the ſweets that Nature had endowed her with, told him
with two or three deep ſighs (Don <hi>Sancho</hi> and Donna
<hi>Margareta</hi> having left the Room) that the love ſhe bore him had
reduced her to that condition, that unleſs his compaſſion and invention
did joyn to give a remedy to her malady, her life would aſſuredly be in
extreme danger; aſſuring him, that all that night ſhe had not cloſed
her eyes, and that her Spirit had not allowed any repoſe to her Body,
whilſt ſhe remembred their ſweet Entertainments and agreeable
Diſcourſes they had had the day before by the way.</p>
               <p>It is not queſtionable whether Don <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtian</hi> were
not overjoyed at this charming Language, not ſuſpecting the Serpent that
lay hid under thoſe ſweet Flowers; but even raviſh'd with content to
ſee all things ſo favourable to his deſigns, he was going to make a long
Narrative of the immeaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable love he bore her: but Donna
<hi>Leono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi>'s Servants interrupted him, and for this<pb n="138" facs="tcp:175400:75"/>time hindered him by their entrance from employing his Rhetorick to
ſo bad purpoſe.</p>
               <p>So ſoon as Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> had left the Room, and Don
<hi>Carlos</hi> ſaw himſelf alone with Don <hi>Sancho,</hi> having
diſmiſſed all the Servants, he bid him ſit down by the Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and
begun this Diſcourſe. 
<q>My dear <hi>Sancho,</hi> if ever Maſter were obliged to his
Servant for the kindneſs he had done him, I am confident my obligations to
thee are greater than ever any have been before; and I queſtion whether if I
ſhould make thee Maſter of all I have, I ſhould ever be able to
recompence thee for the grand Obligations in which thy Services have bound me:
Aſſure thy ſelf that time ſhall make good what I ſay, and if Heaven
ſpare my life, this deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Age, amongſt all her ingratitudes, ſhall
not be able to produce one ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of blame, as my gratitude to thee
ſhall be of praiſe. If I have not hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to made appear to thee in deeds an
effect anſwerable to the generoſity of my words, thou knoweſt the cauſe
ſo well, that it is needleſs for me to employ more time in informing thee
better.</q>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <q>This I intended to ſpeak (my dear <pb n="139" facs="tcp:175400:75"/>Friend) that I might diſcover to thee the infinite affection I bear
thee, as alſo to encourage thee in thy deſigns, and to pray thee as
earneſtly as I am able, to continue what thou haſt ſo happily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun,
becauſe in all Enterprizes if the end prove not anſwerable to the
beginning, the undertaker loſes not onely the glory of what he has already
done, but alſo runs a hazard of having his Reputation ſpoiled by the
mockeries of thoſe that underſtand it. I do not mean, my dear Friend,
(continued Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him) that thou haſt not brought
this Affair dexterouſly to the point I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired and thou promiſedſt,
making me enjoy that which I moſt deſired in the World; but to tell thee
more freely, and ſetting aſide all circumlocutions, I would deſire thee
to ſet thy hand once more to this Affair, and with thy wonted ſubtilty and
addreſs oblige me once more in what I ſhall ſay to thee; for not onely I,
and all I poſſeſs, but even Poſterity, through the Reputation thou wilt
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, will recompence thee with Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality amongſt thoſe of the
moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Wits.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:175400:76"/>Don <hi>Sancho</hi> ſeeing him ſpeak to
him with ſuch grand civility, anſwered him the moſt diſcreetly he could
poſſibly: But Don <hi>Carlos</hi> hurried on by the exceſs of his
paſſion, had not the patience to let him fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his Diſcourſe, but
interrupting him, begun again as followeth. 
<q>The torment that my ſoul endureth, to ſee me
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſeparate from my dear Miſtris without any appearance of a
poſſibility of another ſingle enjoyment, ſwells my ſufferings too big
to be allayed by any thing but death, which will undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enſue, if thy
wit and induſtry do not once more bring me to a nights enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of
her.</q>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <q>That which you deſire, Sir, (replied Don <hi>Sancho</hi>) is
not ſo great a difficulty, but that I could heartily wiſh that ſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
your deſires were no bigger, and that your paſſion would end ſo ſoon
as my invention could ſatisfie it in this: But, Sir, to what purpoſe
ſerves it, if my new Tasks ſtill encreaſe as faſt I finiſh the old
ones; and if in ſtead of being content with the often enjoying of what you
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, you continue in ſuch a diſpoſition, that you are ſtill
ready to begin again,<pb n="141" facs="tcp:175400:76"/>and to play the ſame Perſon ſo
often, that at laſt I fear yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> will grow ſtale, and your
impoſture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſcovered, and at laſt change
into ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter?</q> 
                  <q>I ſwear to thee upon the faith of a Gentleman (ſaid Don
<hi>Carlos</hi>) that to morrow I will take leave of them, if I can content my
deſire but this one night; and find but thou an invention for the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and
I engage to make a pretext for the former. Furthermore, thou ſeeſt we are
near the Court, and in one of the chief Cities of the Kingdom: All theſe
things conſidered, oblige me to part hence; for if I ſhould ſtay longer,
I ſhall be ſure to be known, which I would not be for all I eſteem in the
whole World.</q> 
                  <q>Upon this promiſe (ſaid Don <hi>Sancho</hi>) I engage to
make you lye together this night; and this is the means I ſhall preſcribe:
Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> her Husband is paſſionately in love with you, and
enjoys no other light but that of your eyes, believing you to be of another
Sex: It is therefore neceſſary, for the happy ſucceſs of our Plot, that
you ſhew him the beſt countenance imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and make him believe that
your<pb n="142" facs="tcp:175400:77"/>Flame equals his.</q> 
                  <q>I have done that this morning (ſaid Don <hi>Carlos</hi>) to
ſatisfie his paſſion the beſt I could, knowing we ſhall not be long
together, and that I have not long to humour his vain impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity.</q> 
                  <q>So much the better, (replied Don <hi>Sancho</hi>) it is
convenient to follow on your blow, and finally conclude, that if he come to you
this night, he ſhall find the Door open, conditionally it be done as
ſilently as may be, without ſo much as a word, leſt I ſhould hear, who
you ſhall make him believe do lie in the ſame Chamber with you. And as
thoſe that love ardently do always willingly make themſelves believe what
they deſire, ſo he will make little difficulty to believe all you ſhall
ſay. And further, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelf, that if thouſands of
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles ſhould obſtruct his deſign, the imagination of the intended
pleaſure would make him reſolve to hazard as many lives, if he had them, to
accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh his deſigns. This done, I will treat with a Servant-maid in the
Houſe, who is a good luſty wench, and whom I find to be as tractable as I
can deſire for my deſign, and ſhe I am ſure will not refuſe 
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:175400:77"/>that to a Cavalier, which ſhe is free enough of to
others of meaner rank; ſo that a little Money, and leſs Courtſhip, will
eaſily work upon her good nature. I will therefore give her Money to buy a
pure Holland Smock and fine Night-dreſſing, with ſome rich Perfumes to
ſweeten her Locks, and other parts, and take away the ſmell of the Kitchen.
The appointment ſhall be half an hour after Ten in the Evening; and I will
order her to be as ſilent as you ſhall deſire Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> to
be: and when you judge the hour to approach, it will be neceſſary you leave
the Chamber to go to your Pages, who for that purpoſe ſhall be ordered to
leave open the Door, for fear of making a noiſe; and in the mean time I will
keep my Bed, and expect my Damſel, with whom, being come, I will ſtay a
little while, and then riſe, and pretend my ſelf very ill at the Stomach
with a ſudden qualm, and tell her very low, that I would deſire her
patience a very little while, and I will return to her immediately; and ſo I
will come to you into the Pages Chamber. But firſt it will be neceſſary
you tell him, that for<pb n="144" facs="tcp:175400:78"/>ſome reaſon, which you may
eaſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, you and I have changed Beds, that ſo entring into the
Chamber, he may turn to the left, and not to the right, and ſo he will come
directly to my Bed, where he will find this fair Lady of the Kitchen, with whom
let him paſs the night as contentedly as he can; but in the darkneſs and
ſecreſie that will then be, aſſure your ſelf he will find all Cats
gray: And in the mean time, Sir, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pains or danger, you may arrive
ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at his Wifes Chamber; where having brought you by this device, I
think I may then leave you to your ſelf for the reſt. This being
finiſh'd, I think it may be eaſie to add three or four more Acts to the
Play, if you think it worth the Candle. Which being done, we may eaſily
diſengage our ſelves of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and return ſpeedily home; for I
am afraid my Lady, your Mother, will be in great care for you, hearing nothing
of you, and will have juſt cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of our Proceedings, if we add
not another invention to our former, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe our ſelves of ſo grand an
abſurdity, of ſtaying ſo long from her without wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting 
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:175400:78"/>to her: But as for that, let it be my care, and relie upon
me, that I have not yet ſo exhauſted my Inventions, but I ſhall have one
left for that purpoſe to bring us handſomly off.</q> Here Don
<hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho</hi> ended his Diſcourſe, and Don <hi>Carlos</hi> remained as
ſatisfied as the Soldier, who the ſame day of his ſhewing his Certificate
of the Services he has done on ſeveral occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, receives the full
recompence of his Services, and the accompliſhment of his deſires; or like
a ſick perſon, who by a violent Fever being brought to deſpair of Life,
ſees the fury of it abated on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and himſelf able to walk without
any pain about the Chamber. This reſolution being taken, Don <hi>Carlos</hi>
acquainted Donna <hi>Margareta</hi> with it, whoſe inclinations led her to
approve well of it, and diſpence with her Husbands having a new Bedfellow,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo well ſatisfied with her own. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they ſtudied their Parts
ſo well, that before the Sun had finiſh'd his Carriere, they were all ready
for the Stage.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Fourth Part.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="part">
            <pb n="146" facs="tcp:175400:79"/>
            <head>THE AMOROUS TRAVELLERS, OR THE
<hi>Night-Adventures.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>PART V.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He half hour paſt Ten at Night was ſcarce come, when our
mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary Damſel (deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to know whether the Embraces of a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier or
thoſe of his Servants were more pleaſing, having often taſted of the one,
but ſeldom of the other) left her own Chamber for Don <hi>Sancho</hi>'s, more
trimm'd and perfum'd than a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Bride; or like an old Woman, who, 
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:175400:79"/>careful to ſupply the defects of Age with the induſtry
of her Hands, ſo waſhes, paints, and poliſhes her face, that the
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults of Nature being rectified by the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements of Art, of a wrinkled
deformed <hi>Megara,</hi> ſhe becomes a plump and beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Helena.</hi>
Being come to the Chamber-door, ſhe open'd it ſilently, (it being for that
purpoſe left unlatch'd by Don <hi>Sancho</hi>) and, being entred, ſhe
ſhut it as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and preſently ſhe found the Bed, it not being
the firſt time ſhe had made ſuch Viſits; and could it have been darker
than it was, ſhe could eaſily have done it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daily ſo well
acquainted with the Chamber. Being in the Bed, I cannot ſay, not is it
material to the Story, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſcent of her Perfumes and clean Linen,
overcoming that of her Sweat, might work any effects upon Don <hi>Sancho</hi>'s
Concupiſcence, ſhe having ſpread her Perfumes (and not without reaſon)
over moſt parts of her Body; or whether (like the Beggar that would deceive
his Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach and Senſes, by eating his Bread in the ſmoke of Fleſh-meat)
he might fancy that this were ſome beauteous Lady, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare her Eyes to
Stars (or more properly<pb n="148" facs="tcp:175400:80"/>to thoſe of an Owl) brighteſt
in the dark, and in that imagination break his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which were onely to
ſtalk under her Belly to another deſign: However he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this
quarter of an hour I know not; but this I know, that her attractions were not
ſtrong enough to keep him beyond it: for, ſutable to his deſign, feigning
a qualm, he left her at the quarter of an hours end, and went as ſoftly as he
could poſſibly to his Maſter in the Pages Chamber, where we will leave
them jeſting and laughing at what was paſt, and earneſtly expecting what
was to come, and Don <hi>Carlos</hi> onely ſtaying for the hour of
Aſſignation, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> who alſo expected
his.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> I ſay, who had thought every minute
a year hitherto, till the time came in which he hoped for the full fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of
his dear <hi>Leonora,</hi> in the midſt of his tedious expectatation of the
Clocks ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Eleven, fell into a profound ſleep; but whether proceeding
from the bare ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of drowſineſs, and the aſcent of moiſt Vapours
from the Stomach to the Brain, or by a more immediate influence from Heaven,
which perhaps moved by mercy <pb n="149" facs="tcp:175400:80"/>to his ſpiritual welfare,
as once it was to <hi>Adam</hi>'s temporal, uſed the ſame means to a
contrary end from that which <hi>Adam</hi>'s was deſign'd for, that being in
order to his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying a Woman, and this to prevent it in Don
<hi>Sebaſtian:</hi> Which of theſe to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute it to I know not; but this
chief cauſe of his ſleep, working by the other of drowſineſs, I am the
more inclined to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, when I conſider the effect of it, which was
this.</p>
               <p>Being newly fallen into a ſound ſleep, he fancied in a Dream
that the Clock ſtrook e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leven, (the appointed hour) and he burning with
deſire of the fruition of his Miſtris, leap'd out of the Bed as haſtily
as the little noiſe he durſt make would permit, and being got into the
middle of a great Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, into which moſt of the Chambers of the Houſe
opened, he thought he ſaw a terrible Apparition approach him, at the ſight
of which he was ſeiſed with ſuch hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, that his Hairs ſtood upright
upon his Head; and deſiring to return to his Chamber the ſame way he went
out, he ſaw it appear again on that ſide him. <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> or
<hi>Dion</hi> were not more affrighted when they ſaw, the one in his Tent,
the other in<pb n="150" facs="tcp:175400:81"/>his Gallery, thoſe Phantomes which
<hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> ſpeaks of, than Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally was,
though effectually but in a Dream; and turning his Head on that ſide again
where he had ſeen it firſt, he ſaw near him a Figure wrapp'd in a white
Sheet, the Viſage onely appearing, which made him lay hold on his Sword, with
his Back againſt the Wall, and putting himſelf into a poſture of defence
againſt this airy Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which made ſtraight to him, he fanci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that by
the glimmering light of a Lamp which hung near him, and thereby made the
ſight more diſmal, that it was the Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of his Father lately deceaſed,
whom, after having with deep groans twice or thrice pronounced the word
<hi>Alas!</hi> with a moſt pittiful accent, and a pale and gaſtly viſage,
he thought he heard pronounce theſe words.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>Whether goeſt thou, wicked and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd young man? Alas!
unhappy that thou art, turn thy eyes inwards, and conſider that thou liveſt
not like a Chriſtian, but quite contrary, like a vile and impious Libertine,
daily crucifying by thy ſins him whom thou profeſſeſt to adore, and
from whom thou holdeſt thy<pb n="151" facs="tcp:175400:81"/>being and ſubſiſtence,
who (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thy obſtinacy and hardneſs of heart) hath hitherto
ſpared thee in order to repentance. Conſider how thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt thy Soul,
in indulging thy Body and ſenſual Appetites, daily ſtriving to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wade
<hi>Sardanapalus</hi> in the ſtinking Puddle of beaſtly Luſts, amongſt
unchaſte Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to be by them fitted for a Sacrifice to eternal Flames: If
thou didſt but conſider the terrour of thoſe Flames that there attend
thee, thou wouldeſt not a minute longer continue in this vile and
deteſtable courſe of life, but for ever abandoning theſe execrable
<hi>Megera's,</hi> which have always reduced to extreme miſery, and conducted
to a deplorable end, thoſe that have prodigally conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and unhappily
laviſh'd away with them their time and ſubſtance, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd
themſelves Slaves to them and their bruitiſh paſſions; thou wouldeſt
then, I ſay, change thy way of living, being as thou art a reaſonable
Creature, and profeſſing Chriſtianity, thy aim ſhould be truly
Chriſtian, to attain one day to Celeſtial Beatitude. Finally, forthwith
examine thy Conſcience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail<pb n="152" facs="tcp:175400:82"/>thy ſins like another
penitent <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene,</hi> and delay not to reconcile thy ſelf with God;
for thou knoweſt not how ſhort a time of life he hath allotted thee.</q>
And without more word it vaniſh'd.</p>
               <p>Theſe words, though ſeemingly ſpoken in a Viſion,
wrought a ſtronger effect upon him than the ordinary ones of a troubled
Fancy; for wakening, he found himſelf bathed in ſweat with the
apprehenſion of what had paſs'd, which ſo tormented him, that he
forthwith wept moſt bitterly. His Wife the while, whoſe expectations had
kept her waking, admired at his unwonted emotions in ſleep, and his tears
when wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; but ſaying nothing, expected ſtill that he, thinking her
aſleep, ſhould go and leave room for her Lover: but he, whoſe mind was
fixed on better things, joyning his hands, and fixing his eyes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven,
ſpent the beſt part of the remaining night in ſuch fervent and hearty
penitence and Prayers, that his Wife lying awake and hearing him, it ſtrook
ſuch a holy ſentiment into her ſoul, that ſhe made a firm Vow to
imitate her Husband, as ſhe had done before in wantonneſs, ſo now in 
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:175400:82"/>a firm and through repentance; with which good
reſolution let us leave them expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to disburthen their Souls to their
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, to return to Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> whoſe Head was filled with
worſer thoughts.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Carlos</hi> thinking that (the Clock ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtrook
Eleven) Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> was by this time at the place appointed, went
to the Door of Donna <hi>Margareta</hi>'s Chamber, but finding it ſhut, he
was forced to return, imagining that Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> was not yet come
out: He came again an hour after, but found it as before, which made him think
that either ſome indiſpoſition or ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter accident kept Don
<hi>Sebaſtian</hi> confined to his Chamber; wherefore almoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing
of ſucceſs this night, he went to ſleep upon one of the Pages Beds: But
his other Affair ſtill running in his head, he aroſe and went four or five
times more, ſtill finding the Door ſhut as formerly: So quite giving over
his deſign, he betook him to his reſt. The Damſel of the Kitchen having
alſo attended the return of Don <hi>Sancho</hi> three hours or more, and
ſeeing he came not, ſhe roſe and returned to her Chamber, thinking he had
but mocked her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:175400:83"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>THe Clork had ſcarce ſtrook ſix, when our penitent Don
<hi>Sebaſtian</hi> went to Confeſſion to the Fathers <hi>Teutins,</hi>
where kneeling before a learned and holy Father, he wept, and confeſſed his
ſins, with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and hearty repentance. Having heard Maſs in the
ſame Church, and finiſh'd his Devotions, he came forth to return home, yet
intending firſt to viſit the other Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and to begin at the great
one; but paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing into a Lane that comes into the Street calld <hi>L'
Alcana,</hi> or <hi>The Mercers Street,</hi> he met a Man, who no ſooner
ſaw and knew him, but ſtepp'd to him, and gave him a ſtab with a Poniard
near the left Pap, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe words ſo loud that moſt of the
Street heard him, <hi>Die thou Traytor, that haſt robbed me of my
Honour;</hi> and leaving the Poniard ſticking in his Breaſt, he fled to the
Church.</p>
               <p>All that ſaw this ran to him (as the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom is) and carried
the wounded man to the next houſe: There one look'd at him, another wept, one
ask'd how it came, one<pb n="155" facs="tcp:175400:83"/>ran for a Chirurgeon, another for
Balſom; another, more wiſe than the reſt, ſtopped the Blood by
Charming; a thing permitted by the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inquiſition, by
reaſon of the great profit that comes by thoſe holy Words: And this, I
ſay, is no foppery; for I my ſelf have ſeen divers Perſons aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned
for irrecoverable by the Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which one of theſe Charmers by Prayers
and Oriſons completely healed in leſs than eight days. But all their Charms
and holy Words availed little for Don <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtian,</hi> for it was God's
will he ſhould die of that Wound, as we ſhall ſee by and by.</p>
               <p>The mean time there was ſo confuſed a noiſe and rumour
about the Church, as if a great Army had been ſtorming a Town, which was
valiantly maintained by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants: At laſt one might perceive that all
this Hubbub proceeded from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries, and a Troop of
<hi>Alguazils</hi> who accompanied them, to lend their aſſiſtance to take
the Murtherer forcibly out of the Church, the Prieſts, and many People that
aſſiſted them, protecting him; but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their
reſiſtance, they entred the Church forcibly, and ſeiſed the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer:
but being upon the point of carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<pb n="156" facs="tcp:175400:84"/>him off, the
Prieſts, ſeeing the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Church broken, took heart again,
and, aſſiſted by the People, took him away, and brought him into the
Church again. The Officers on one ſide cried Aid for the King; the Prieſts
on the other ſide, Succour for the Church: The People flock'd in on both
ſides, which ſo augmented the bruit and clamour, that it almoſt ſeemed
to equal that of the Sack of <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> But at length the
Officers Party proving too ſtrong for the other, carried him forcibly away,
and in ſpite of the Prieſts hurried him to Priſon. Upon this Combuſtion
arrived the Governour of the Town, who ſeeing the Criminal was ſecured in
the Gaol, made the wounded man be carried to his Inn, ſutably to his
quality.</p>
               <p>I will not trouble you with a Relation of Donna
<hi>Margareta</hi>'s tears and lamentations, nor thoſe of his Friends and
Relations, at the News of it: I will onely tell you, that having laid him on a
Bed in a low Room, all the People in the Houſe came to ſee him.</p>
               <p>The Lady of the Stars, of whom we have not ſpoken this long
time, had never<pb n="157" facs="tcp:175400:84"/>been out of her Chamber ſince ſhe came
from the Foreſt; but hearing of this Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Accident of Don
<hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> ſhe ran to his Chamber, where ſhe found all in tears
and lamentations; and approaching to the Bed where the poor Don
<hi>Sebaſtian</hi> lay bathed in Blood, but with a chearful Countenance, more
like a ſound man than a dying one, and comforted his Wife in this manner,
(who in the mean time pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of her ſelf, tore her Hair, and
lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably bruis'd her Breaſt and Face) 
<q>What doſt thou do, my deareſt Wife? Is this the comfort
thou giveſt thy dying Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, to add a Wound to his Spirit, far worſe
than that of his Body: Alas! every Hair thou teareſt from thy Head pulls my
very Soul from my Body. Ceaſe thy tears, my Dear, if thou loveſt me; for if
thou kneweſt the ſtate I am in, in ſtead of thus afflicting and
tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting thy ſelf, thou wouldeſt behold me with a chearful look, and
think me ſo much more happy than I ſeem miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as celeſtial
happineſs exceeds that which is earthly; for, bleſſed be God, I have this
morning received Abſolution for all my ſins, and want nothing now 
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:175400:85"/>but the laſt ſacred <hi>Viaticum,</hi> which I beg of
thee as the laſt Office thou canſt do to me, by ſending for the next
Prieſt that can be had, for I cannot long expect his coming.</q>
               </p>
               <p>At theſe laſt words the Lady of the Stars approached to the
Bed, trembling like one in an Ague-fit, and conſidering the wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſon
more attentively than before, ſhe dropp'd down at his Feet, ſaying, Alas,
my deareſt Coſin, to what point have my miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes driven me! This was
all ſhe could ſay, becauſe ſhe immediately fell into a Swoon. The
by-ſtanders ran to her, and taking her up, carried her to her Chamber. The
mean time the Prieſt was ſent for to Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> and having
excluded the Company all but Donna <hi>Margareta,</hi> did the laſt Offices
to him due to a dying man, which he received with great chearfulneſs, and
preſently his ſtrength decaying, being unable to ſpeak a word more
beſides his laſt Farewel to his Wife, and recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of his Soul to
its Creator, gently breathed it out into his Arms.</p>
               <p>I know not how to expreſs to you Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <hi>Margareta</hi>'s
ſorrows and deſpairs, which are as much too great for me to diſcover, 
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:175400:85"/>as they were for her to endure; ſo great, that they
rendred her ſo deplorably diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate, that all that ſaw it feared
ſhe could not long ſurvive her Husband. Let us leave her to her tears,
(ſince our firſt movements are too violent for our ſelves to ſtop, much
leſs for others) to return to the Kinſwoman of the Deceaſed, who
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning from her Swoon wept ſo bitterly, and lamented with ſuch pitteous
accents, that they drew tears from the eyes of all the beholders. This while
her Governeſs, who was gone to Maſs to a Chappel near the Inn, met by the
way with Don <hi>Carlos</hi> and Don <hi>Sancho,</hi> and knew them both, for
all the Diſguiſe of the one. They all ſtaid at Maſs tgether, without
knowing of Don <hi>Sebaſtian</hi>'s miſhap. Don <hi>Carlos</hi> and Don
<hi>Sancho,</hi> after the Maſs ended, hearing of the Accident, haſted to
the Inn. The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Lady of the Stars, after ſhe had known them,
never loſt ſight of them, but carefully dogg'd them to the Inn, and went
ſtraight to her Ladies Chamber with the News, but was there much
aſtoniſh'd to find her in that condition, and asked the cauſe, and how
this Accident hapned; many being preſent, and particularly the 
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:175400:86"/>Governour, who had never left the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber from the time
that ſhe was brought thither in a Swoon: for, as I have ſaid, and now tell
you again to refreſh your memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the Governour had made Don
<hi>Sebaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> be brought into the Inn, to know who and whence he was,
and thoſe of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; but the Beauty of this Lady de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained him all this
while by her Beds ſide, to ſee what would be the iſſue of ſo many
misfortunes. The Governeſs having ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied her curioſity, came and
whiſpered her Lady in the Ear, and told her as low as ſhe could the
Adventure ſhe had met with in the Church. This News ſo comforted her, that
ſhe remained almoſt ſenſeleſs with an exceſs of joy for ſo
unexpected an happineſs; but at length rallying her ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, which had
been almoſt as much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipated by this joy as the former ſorrow, and
fearing leſt delay might ruine an Affair of ſo grand importance, ſhe
asked for the Governour, whom ſhe remembred ſhe had ſeen in the Chamber a
little while before, and he, being not far off, came preſently to her. After
ſome few Diſcourſes, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour commanded two or three of his Guard
to charge the Hoſt to ſee that none<pb n="161" facs="tcp:175400:86"/>ſhould part out
of his Houſe, and to take into cuſtody all the Servants of Donna
<hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onora,</hi> and of the deceaſed Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> and ſo
made all avoid the Room but two Women, himſelf, and the Lady of the Stars;
who ſeeing her ſelf thus private with him, began this Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>I would willingly, Sir, excuſe my ſelf from making you a
Narrative of things ſo little ſutable to one of my Quality; but I know no
other remedy but to lay open my Malady to you, in whoſe hands lies the power
of healing it: On you onely depends my hope, my repoſe, and contentment. Give
me, if you pleaſe, Sir, one moments audience, and having learn'd by the
relation of my Life the Chance that brought me hither, you will have juſt
cauſe to call it deplorably un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Governour deſirous to know whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe Prayers and
Supplications tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, promiſed her his beſt favour and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
and, if need were, to employ all his Friends to that purpoſe. Upon this
promiſe (ſaid the Lady of the Stars) I truſt in the Divine Bounty that
all things will ſucceed happily with me: And having<pb n="162" facs="tcp:175400:87"/>ſtaid a while to take breath, ſhe broke ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence as
followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p> 
                  <q> 
                     <p> 
                        <hi>UBeda,</hi> one of the principal Towns of
<hi>Andaluzia,</hi> is the Place of my Nativity; my Name, <hi>Hortenſia:</hi>
This wounded Cavalier that you ſee brought in here is my Coſin, his Father
and mine being own Brothers. I had not attained the ſecond year of my age
when my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther went into <hi>Flanders,</hi> to command a Regiment of Horſe
under <hi>Ferdinand de Toledo</hi> Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> with whom he
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired ſuch reputation, by the ſignal Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of his Valour and
Courage, that the Duke for recompence of his Services made him
Camp-Maſter-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral. But as the beſt Fortune in the World is mix'd with
bad, Fortune, that never leaves any one long in the ſame ſtate, was
pleaſed to afflict my Father, by taking out of the World her who had brought
me into it, mixing this miſhap with the happineſs he enjoyed in his new
Charge. I had attained the tenth year<pb n="163" facs="tcp:175400:87"/>of my life then when
my Mother finiſh'd hers; ſo that the ſmalneſs of my age made me
incapable of conſidering the greatneſs of my loſs.</p> 
                     <p> The renown of my Beauty, which became an object of admiration
to all beholders, being ſpread about on all ſides, my Father, as a ſage
and adviſed man, judged that ſo rich a Treaſure would be unable to guard
it ſelf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the aſſiſtance of a Perſon able and fit for the
protecting and educating a Daughter of ſo Illuſtrious a Houſe; and
therefore unwilling to truſt me to any others Conduct but his own, he took me
out of the Houſe of his Brother, who was Father to this murther'd Cavalier,
and carried me with him into <hi>Flanders,</hi> and there preſented me to the
moſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene Infanta, our Kings Siſter, and Wife of the Arch-Duke
<hi>Albert.</hi>
                     </p> 
                     <p> In this Houſe I was cheriſh'd and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd of all,
eſpecially of the Infanta. The favours I received ſeemed to be the cauſe
that my Wit became ſo refined, and my Beauty ſo augmented, that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to
the age of fifteen, every one ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired me as the wonder of Nature,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <pb n="164" facs="tcp:175400:88"/>Phenix of
my Sex, and conſequently adjudged me the preheminence above all the Ladies of
<hi>Flanders.</hi> But as all things under the Moon are ſo far like it, that
they are never firm or durable, and like the Waves, are onely conſtant in
incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, Deſtiny had deſigned me this misfortune, that my Father,
loaded with years, and overcharged with age, paid his laſt Tribute to Nature,
ſuddenly ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the bottom of the Grave, when he was arrived to the
higheſt ſtep of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. Ye malignant Stars, what cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty did ye ſhew
me at that time! Would God you had been ſo courteous, as when you took away
the Lives of my Father and Mother, to have bound up mine in the ſame Bundle.
O how happy had it been for wretched me to have then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured Deſtinies
utmoſt rigour, rather than to live to ſee my ſelf thus expoſed to
ſuch a multitude of misfortunes.</p> 
                     <p> But as time remedies all things, and Women (following the Rule
of their natural levity) are apt to forget that ſooneſt which they ought
longeſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, the Year being paſt, and my Mournings thrown off,
with them I loſt<pb n="165" facs="tcp:175400:88"/>the memory of Father and Mother, and
changed my ſorrow and lamentation into mirth and jollity, as more fit and
plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to my Age and Conſtitution, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to liſten to the
Diſcourſes and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jolleries of young Gallants, but always with ſo
reſerved a modeſty, that the moſt critical of my Companions could never
charge me with an immodeſt word or diſhoneſt action: And ſtill, as
Water ſprinkled upon Fire does rather encreaſe than abate its burning, ſo
my coyneſs did more augment the violence of their Flames. Thus I entertained
my ſelf, till Heaven to puniſh my private ſins, and Love to revenge my
ſlighting of ſo many of his attempts, did both conſpire to wound me
mortally with the love of a young Cavalier, Son of a certain Duke of
<hi>Andaluzia,</hi> who was newly arrived at Court: And though a ſeventeen
years experience had taught me how little or how bad Fruit is gather'd from
ſuch like Amours, yet neither that, the multitude of Examples I had found by
reading, nor all the holy Conſiderations and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reſolutions, the
Vows, Prayers, and Faſtings that I made, not the firmeſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves 
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:175400:89"/>I could invent, were able in the leaſt to efface the
Image of Love that was fixed in my Heart. The many glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of my Eyes did
ſtill diſcover the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of my Soul, and his in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence
returned them with intereſt. Theſe intercourſes, and many others which
paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed betwixt us, did kindle our Affections into ſo violent a flame,
that at laſt, van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh'd by his fair Promiſes, obliging Letters, and
ſolemn Proteſtations, back'd with his ſighs and tears, and ſerious Vow
of marrying me, I committed to his diſpoſal that unvaluable Jewel which all
the Riches of the <hi>Indies</hi> can never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive: but this Traytor had no
ſooner taken poſſeſſion, but he deſerted his Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, and
leaving the Court, returned to his own Countrey. The condition I then ſaw my
ſelf reduced to, and the extremity of my reſentment of ſuch an injury,
are as far beyond my words to expreſs, as then my patience to ſuſtain: My
Nails revenged upon my Face, and my Fingers upon my Hair, the injury which
their enticements had brought me to, and my tearing of my Clothes ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to
teſtifie that they had been inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental <pb n="167" facs="tcp:175400:89"/>to my
ſufferings. I curſed a thouſand times my ill fortune, and as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
accuſed my raſh reſolution: I was even blinded with the tears, and
choaked with the ſighs which daily iſſued from my ſorrowful eyes and
afflicted heart. I addreſſed my ſecret complaints to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, not daring
to diſcover them to any beneath it, and privately joyned both my Reaſon and
Imagination, to ſee if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them could find a path to eſcape theſe
miſeries. The beſt expedient I could light on was, to go caſt my ſelf
at the Infanta's feet, and recount the injury which this ingrateful and
perfidious man had done me; who at firſt extremely blamed me, but at laſt
ſhewing her his Letters and Contract written by his own hand, ſhe undertook
my Cauſe, and writ to the King her Brother in my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, ſending me
accompanied with two Cavaliers and two Women, to demand Juſtice at his hands.
Coming to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> I underſtood that his Majeſty was here at
<hi>Toledo,</hi> where I arrived the very day that he departed hence; and my
fortune was ſo proſperous, that the ſame day the King reading my Letters,
and<pb n="168" facs="tcp:175400:90"/>underſtanding my Complaints from my own mouth,
diſpatch'd away a Party of Horſe of his own Guards, to ſeiſe the
Perſon of him that had ſo injured me; but Fortune now has at once proved
ſo favourabe and ſo contrary to my happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that ſhe has this day
put my Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my into my hands, and my poor Coſin into thoſe of Death; for my
Governeſs has juſt now told me, that one of thoſe Ladies that came along
with him is the ſame Don <hi>Carlos</hi> in diſguiſe, for whom my eyes
have ſhed ſuch floods of tears.</p> 
                     <p> You ſee, Sir, the deplorable Hiſtory of my Life, and 'tis
from you I now deſire advice how to comport my ſelf in this Affair: And
fear not, Sir, but the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs you ſhall do me ſhall be amply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded
by the Arch-Duke, the Serene Infanta my Roval Miſtris, and by the King
himſelf, whoſe Office it is to ſee Juſtice done to ſuch injured
Innocents as my ſelf.</p> 
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Governour heard all this attentive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and took ſuch
compaſſion of this affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Lady, that taking her by the hand, he ſpoke
to her the moſt courteouſly he could imagine, ſaying, 
<q>Leave this Affair (Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam)<pb n="169" facs="tcp:175400:90"/>to my
management, and I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you, that without either bruit or proceſs I will
accompliſh all your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns; and if I ſhould be ſo unhappy as not to
obtain of your Husband (for ſo I may call him) that which I demand, I will
carry him Priſoner to the King, there to receive the juſt chaſtiſement
of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude; and ſo doing, I ſhall accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh the deſires of
his Majeſty and the Infanta his Siſter, to whoſe liberal hands I am
obliged for all I poſſeſs: Beſides all this, I was ſo happy once as
to have a particular amity with your Father, being Captain when he commanded
the beſt part of the Army in <hi>Flanders.</hi> But I wiſh your Governeſs
be not deceived, becauſe it is ſcarce poſſible for any man to be
Maſter of that Beauty which both theſe Ladies poſſeſs.</q> 
                  <q>Scruple not at that, Sir, (replied Donna <hi>Hortenſia</hi>)
for he I ſpeak of is one of the moſt accompliſh'd Cavaliers for Beauty
that is under the face of the Heavens, and, diſguiſed in a Womans Habit, is
able to deceive the moſt crafty and ſuſpicious Man alive.</q> 
                  <q>I will go, Madam, by your permiſſion, (ſaid the
Governour) and talk to him<pb n="170" facs="tcp:175400:91"/>immediately.</q> 
                  <q>If you pleaſe to do ſo, Sir, (replied the Lady) you will
much oblige me; but I conceive it neceſſary my Governeſs firſt
deſcribe to you the faſhion of his Habit, and the colour of his Clothes,
leſt you ſhould miſtake another for him.</q> 
                  <q>He (ſaid the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) that wears the white Damask Gown
wrought with Silver is Don <hi>Carlos:</hi> and I do not at all queſtion it;
for I ſaw him at Maſs this Morning with Don <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho</hi> one of his
Gentlemen.</q> 
                  <q>We ſhall know him preſently (ſaid the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;)</q>
and thereupon left the Chamber of Donna <hi>Hortenſia,</hi> and went to that
where were Donna <hi>Margareta,</hi> Donna <hi>Leonora,</hi> and Don
<hi>Sancho;</hi> and without ſaluting them, or making the leaſt ſemblance
of doing ſo, but looking with a ſevere coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance (aſtoniſh'd at the
Beauty of theſe Ladies) upon Don <hi>Sancho,</hi> he ſpoke to him with a
haughty voice, and rigorous words, as followeth: 
<q>'Tis you muſt either tell me preſently who moved you to
aſſaſſinate ſo barbarouſly this poor Cavalier, or expect the
Hangman to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract it from you by torture.</q>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <q>I know not, Sir, (anſwered Don <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho</hi>) 
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:175400:91"/>why you ſpeak to me in this manner, ſince the nobler a
Cavalier is, the more civility and courteſie ought he to expreſs both in
words and actions; and after the Information made, and Witneſſes examined,
if there be found any one that depoſeth againſt me, from the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer
himſelf, to him that is leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, let my Head be cut off backward
like a Traytor: But withal, if I be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely cleared, that which you have
already ſaid is unjuſt. The King has not put this Authority in your hand to
uſe it ſo imperiouſly, and with ſuch arrogance; but onely to
chaſtiſe offenders, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the Innocent.</q> 
                  <q>Gentlemen, (ſaid the Governour) avoid the Room a while; and
you (ſaid he to his Guards) go along with them, whilſt I ſpeak to this
inſolent and raſh man.</q> So ſoon as all were gone, the Governour began
to examine Don <hi>Sancho.</hi> and ask him abundance of Queſtions, to which
he anſwered the beſt he could; and after his Examination he made him leave
the Chamber, and his Guards bring Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <hi>Margareta,</hi> charging them not
to let her ſpeak with Don <hi>Sancho,</hi> or Donna <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora;</hi> and
having queſtioned Donna <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gareta,</hi>
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:175400:92"/>he ſent
her away as he had done Don <hi>Sancho,</hi> ſtill giving the ſame charge
to the Guards. Laſt of all he made Donna <hi>Leonora</hi> be brought, to
whom, after many Demands and Anſwers, he made this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe
following.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>It is no wonder if the ordinary ſort of People of this Age
are ſo inclined to Vice, ſince Perſons of Quality, without either fear of
God, or reſpect of the World, are naturally ſo averſe from Vertue. In
former times Nobility was diſtinguiſh'd, as firſt of all created, by a
more than ordinary Vertue: but now, on the contrary, it flies that, and glories
in Vice. This that I ſay is ſo unqueſtionably true, and ſo
notoriouſly known, that through all <hi>Spain</hi> it is brought into a
cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, and practiced, as Theft was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly amongſt the
<hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> as a Gallantry. Wonderful miſcarriage! that we who
command almoſt the third part of the World, and whoſe Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is
ſpread through all the reſt of it, ſhould have ſo little rule over our
ſelves, that in ſtead of being (as we boaſt) more vertuous than others,
we ſhould be ſo much more vicious, daily committing<pb n="173" facs="tcp:175400:92"/>ſuch baſe unworthy actions, that the Nations that are ſubjugated
by us, are moſt impatient under the yoke of men ſo much their inferiours in
Wiſdom, Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Vertue. That a Noble young Duke, whoſe Valour ought
to promiſe as many Victories as <hi>Alexander</hi> obtained, ſhould ſo
far forget himſelf and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, as to follow after a Woman,
diſguiſed in a Habit ſo vile and abject as that which you now wear, and
to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge your Pleaſure, to abdicate the Nobility of your Sex, and to range
your ſelf amongſt thoſe who, in the judgment of all wiſe men, are
eſteemed an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection or miſtake in Nature.</q>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <q>Pardon me, Sir, if I ſpeak too freely; and that having
knowledge of your fault, in ſtead of praiſing it, as your Paraſites
ordinarily do, I blame and reprove it, ſince both my Charge and Conſcience
oblige me to it; and if I ſhould fail in that devoir, I ſhould more
juſtly incur the title of Puſillanimous, than now that of raſh or
unmannerly. I ſpeak not of the death of this Cavalier your Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade, ſince
not having yet made a full ſcrutiny into it, I know not whether 
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:175400:93"/>your hands are ſtained with it, or no. If not, (as I
deſire they may not) all things may eaſily be remedied. That which you have
to do at preſent, is to return to <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> (to which I counſel
you as your Friend and Servant) and there eſpouſe the Daughter of
<hi>Gonſalvo de Mendoça</hi> Camp-Maſter-General, whoſe Honour you
have raviſh'd under promiſe of Marriage; and thus accompliſhing your Word
which you have given her, and that Promiſe you have made her in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, you
will cover or deface the infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my you incur by ſo unworthy an action, and at
the ſame time acquire the Title of the moſt generous and vertuous Prince in
<hi>Spain:</hi> otherwiſe I muſt command you in the King's Name immediately
to quit this Habit for your own, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company me to attend his Majeſty, and
there, according to the duty you owe him, do by fair means or foul that which
by love and civility you are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to. This you cannot avoid, ſince the
moſt Serene Infanta has writ about it to the King her Brother. To think to
deny what I have ſaid, is in vain, ſince Don <hi>Sancho</hi> your Gentleman
has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd<pb n="175" facs="tcp:175400:93"/>it; and beſides, I have had the honour
to know you a great while.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>IT is not to be queſtioned whether Don <hi>Carlos</hi> was at
once ſeiſed with fear and aſtoniſhment, hearing the Governour ſpeak
ſo freely, and thereby underſtanding that his Majeſty had been fully
informed of the Affair by the Infanta; and he knew the Kings of <hi>Spain</hi>
exact ſo complete an Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience from their Subjects, and Juſtice has ſo
impartial a hand over the Grandees, that in my remembrance there was a
memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble act to that effect at <hi>Madrid,</hi> where one of the greateſt
Dukes of the Kingdom, for cudgelling an <hi>Alguazil,</hi> was deeply fined by
the Preſident of <hi>Caſtile.</hi> Theſe kind of Examples ſtop the
moſt raſh and hardy Courages, and makes them moderate their own Choler by
ſeeing the puniſhment of others, thereby ſtopping the current of their
fiery Youth, and accuſtoming them to obey the Laws, by the ſtrict
obſervation of which the State is aggrandized, and the Princes Authority
maintained.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:175400:94"/>Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> as well accompliſhed
and crafty as he was, and endowed with an excellent Judgment, ſeeing
himſelf brought to ſuch a nonplus, redoubles the forces of his wit by the
preſence of danger, and ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf to the preſent Occurrences,
and knowing that good Language would work better effects than all the Menaces
and Rhodomontadoes he could invent, to him who would be more provoked than
daunted with them, laying aſide his effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate behaviour, with which he had
hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto treated with the Governour, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun this Diſcourſe with the
greateſt affabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and courteſie imaginable.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>To deny, Sir, that the Age in which we live is the moſt
perverſe and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that ever was, and that Nobility it ſelf is as
corrupt and wicked as the vile Populacy, would be a ſignal abſurdity; the
daily Examples we ſee are ſufficient teſtimonies: And it would be an
aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of my Crime, and a defamation of Vertue, to juſtifie Vice, in
being ſo inconſiderate as to vindicate the fault which I ought rather to be
aſhamed of, in taking a Habit ſo unbecoming a Perſon of my Quality: But I
think there are<pb n="177" facs="tcp:175400:94"/>few dare take up the firſt Stone
againſt me upon this ſubject, ſince the moſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous man in the World
has not always been able to reſiſt the aſſaults of Love; and I
queſtion whether you can produce one ſince the Celeſtial Globe has rolled
over the Heads of Mortals, that has not one time or other been ſubject to it:
I avoid Examples, which are ſo nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, that to undertake to enumerate
them, would be to enter a Labyrinth from which I ſhould never diſentangle
my ſelf: I onely entreat and conjure one thing of you, for her ſake whom
you love beſt, not to refuſe me a favour I would beg of you, and then I
ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude my Diſcourſe in few words.</q> 
                  <q>I vow and promiſe you, upon the Faith of a Gentleman, ſaid
Don <hi>Antonio</hi> (for ſo was the Governour call'd) to do what you
deſire, provided it be a thing that intrench not upon my Honour or
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</q> 
                  <q>It neither ſhall prejudice the one nor the other, replied
Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> ſmiling. Speak then what you deſire, ſaid Don
<hi>Antonio,</hi> that I may give you ſome proofs of the Service I have vowed
for<pb n="178" facs="tcp:175400:95"/>you.</q> 
                  <q>I onely ask, ſaid Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ever Love
had a Juriſdiction over your Spirit?</q> 
                  <q>Yes, ſaid Don <hi>Antonio,</hi> and in ſuch manner, that
often tranſported by this frantick paſſion, my extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, both in
words and actions, have cauſed laughter in all that knew me; and to this very
hour I feel its effects.</q> 
                  <q>If perhaps (ſaid Don <hi>Carlos</hi>) you were yet
deſirous to enjoy your Amours, would you think it an unpardonable crime to
make uſe of that Habit your ſelf which you blame ſo rigorouſly in me,
if you were aſſured of the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of your deſires in the
enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Miſtris.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Governour, after a ſhort time of ſilence, thought it
convenient to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it, fearing that a denial might be a wrong to one
whom his Soul adored; and therefore he thus anſwered him ſmilingly: 
<q>I ſhould not onely, Sir, for her ſake take upon me this
Habit which you wear, which is ſuitable to a Lady of the beſt Quality, but
even that of a Kitchen-wench, to enjoy her who is Miſtris o my Heart, and
whoſe Eyes have kindled<pb n="179" facs="tcp:175400:95"/>thoſe Flames in my Breaſt
which daily conſume it.</q> 
                  <q>Then, Sir, (replied Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> ſmiling) you have
much wronged me by your accuſation, ſince you by this ſeem to
poſſeſs as much good fellowſhip as another: And further, you ought to
conſider, that the ancient Poets, who have always adored <hi>Jupiter,</hi> as
he on whom the vaſt Machine of the Univerſe depended, have yet introduced
him in a Womans Habit to enjoy his fair <hi>Caliſto,</hi> and otherwhiles
have given him the ſhape of a Bull to embrace his beloved <hi>Europa.</hi> I
have preſumed, Sir, to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with this Diſcourſe, to put you in
mind that the faults committed through exceſs of Love may juſtly claim a
privilege of remiſſion above other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences: And, by what I underſtand,
you, that cenſure with ſuch liberty the miſcarriages of others, may
juſtly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo a reprehenſion for your own. But laying aſide theſe and
many other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which might be pertinent in order to my vindication, as
to the point in queſtion, I ſhall now inform you, that I am not onely
willing to accompliſh the<pb n="180" facs="tcp:175400:96"/>Matrimonial Vow I made to the
Lady you ſpeak of, but alſo to part hence to morrow morning to beg pardon
of his Majeſty for the fault I have committed, and permiſſion for a
Journey into <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> to ſeek the deareſt Object of my Soul: And
I aſſure you, that what I have already done, was not with a deſign to
deceive her, nor falſifie my Faith; but onely in order to the obtaining
permiſſion of his Majeſty and my Mother for our conjunction in the Sacred
Union. But all that now remains to trouble me is, the apprehenſion that this
youthful acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould come to the Kings Ear, the prevention of which I
would willingly purchaſe with half of what I poſſeſs.</q> 
                  <q>If, Sir, you promiſe me (ſaid the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) to
accompliſh what you have ſaid, I will engage to procure that his Majeſty
ſhall never know it, and that thoſe of this Houſe ſhall never publiſh
any thing to your diſadvantage, on condition that you be not found culpable
of the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this Cavalier, Husband of Donna <hi>Margareta.</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <q>I promiſe you, upon the Faith of a Gentleman, (replied Don
<hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los</hi>) <pb n="181" facs="tcp:175400:96"/>to perform all this that you deſire;
and let my Head pay the forfeiture, if the Murtherer do in the leaſt charge
me with this Aſſaſſinate, or any of my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticks.</q> 
                  <q>Ah, Sir, (replied the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour) how cordially ſhall I
embrace you if this be true that you have ſaid! And if you pleaſe to
accompany me but a little way, I ſhall ſave you a Journey into
<hi>Flanders,</hi> to ſeek that which you ſhall find nearer hand.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe words ſtrook Don <hi>Carlos</hi> into a great
aſtoniſhment, being unable to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend what Don <hi>Antonio</hi> meant
by this Diſcourſe, but however he followed him into the Chamber of Donna
<hi>Hortenſia,</hi> whom they ſound ſate upon her Bed, upon a Cuſhion
of Crimſon Damask embroide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Gold, having round about her abundance of
Violets, Jeſſamins, and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. At firſt Don <hi>Carlos</hi> did not
know her, partly becauſe her Head was turned on one ſide, and partly for
the alteration which was cauſed in her Face by the griefs and afflictions
ſhe had lately ſuffered, being but newly returned from a Swoon: But turning
her Head to anſwer the Governours<pb n="182" facs="tcp:175400:97"/>Salute, ſhe was
preſently known to Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> who even raviſh'd with joy, ran to
her to embrace her, with ſuch violence that it was beyond her power to hinder
it, and preſently he ſpoke to her as followeth. 
<q>O my deareſt Life, ſweeteſt Pledge of my Heart, I here
caſt my ſelf at your Feet, that you may take what vengeance you pleaſe
upon ſo unpardonable a crime. Why do you not anſwer me, my Soul? Why turn
you from me? But alas! What is it I demand? What do I ſay? Or what can I
think, that had not the diſcretion to guard ſo ineſtimable a Treaſure
when I had it in my poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? O that over-ruling Providence, who
ſoundeth the bottoms of our Hearts, and knoweth the depth of our Intentions,
whoſe influence upon my Spirit has made me a thouſand times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent my
ingratitude to this incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lady, which I have now the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to
embrace, would vouchſafe to touch hers alſo, and cauſe her, by bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
my offence in eternal oblivion, once more to bleſs me with that affection I
have ſo juſtly forfeited. And why this<pb n="183" facs="tcp:175400:97"/>averſion
(ſaid he) my better Genius?</q> And theſe words he accompanied with the
tendereſt Careſſes he could invent, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times kiſſing her Roſie
Lips, ſometimes her lovely Cheeks, which had newly changed Deaths pale Livery
for the moſt lovely Scarlet, and ſometimes her Hands more white than Ivory,
with a violence too ſtrong for her reſiſtance. All that were preſent at
this Interview were tranſported with joy, and particularly the Govenour
remained more ecſtaſied with the pleaſure he took at our two fair Lovers
reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than <hi>Archimedes</hi> when he traced the Lines in his Study
which defended the Walls of <hi>Syracuſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Like as green Wood laid on the Fire conſumes all its
moiſture before it inflame, and after that is ſpent, takes Fire and burns
like dry Stubble: So this Lady, whoſe Humidity had all this while been
diſtilling through her fair Eyes in pearled drops, after its evacuation her
Heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun by little and little to take hold of the Fire of Love; till at
laſt being come to a total Conflagration, ſhe caſt her ſelf on his
Neck, and embraced him with the<pb n="184" facs="tcp:175400:98"/>ſame Arms with which a
while before ſhe had defended her ſelf againſt him; and with all the
deareſt teſtimonies of an intire affection, called him her Soul, her Life,
her Happineſs, ſealing each word with a hundred Kiſſes.</p>
               <p>Stay here thy flight, my Pen; for my Eyes are ſo dazzled with
this raviſhing object, that they will no longer ſerve me to form theſe
Letters, nor my Hands to regulate thoſe Lines I ſhould trace upon this
Paper.</p>
               <p>It is not to be doubted whether or no the Governour were ſtill
more rejoyced with the incomparable Amity of our two Lovers, ſeeing all his
deſigns thereby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper to his deſire. He approached to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them; but
it was after the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſhame upon their Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, they having
begged pardon of him for their incivility, ſince the ſudden tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport of
ſo unexpected a joy had made their Devoirs to him give place to the
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments of their own good Fortune. But Don <hi>Antonio,</hi> who was as
courteous as diſcreet, and moſt advantageouſly endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all the
Accompliſhments befitting<pb n="185" facs="tcp:175400:98"/>a Cavalier of his condition,
anſwered them with ſo civil and obliging language, promiſing them to
employ all his Power and Authority in their ſervice, that both out Lovers
were brought to acknowledge that Divine Mercy had regulated their miſhaps and
diſorders by a ſignal Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that by his ſage and prudent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct
they might happily arrive to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of their deſires. And for
a further confirmation of their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, after they had all three
conſulted together about what they had to do, having called Don
<hi>Sancho,</hi> who was by this time Friends with the Governour, the Governour
having cleared him from the aſperſion he had laid upon him of having
diſcovered his Maſters Secrets, he ſpoke as followeth.</p>
               <p> 
                  <q>Since you have already done me the Honour to put the Conduct
of this Affair into my Hands, thereby judging me capable, by my experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in
the Intrigues of Worldly Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, to manage it to the beſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, my
advice is, that without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſpute you all enter into two 
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:175400:99"/>Coaches, which I will ſend you for that purpoſe this
Evening, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come my Priſoners in my Houſe: As for the reſt, leave it
to me, and I queſtion not but the extreme deſire I have to ſerve you,
will inſpire me with the means of conducting your Affairs to the Point
deſired.</q> Having ſaid this, he took leave of them to go to his Lodging,
leaving our two Lovers in the poſſeſſion of all the joys
imaginable.</p>
               <p>Don <hi>Carlos</hi> already touched with Don
<hi>Sebaſtian</hi>'s lamentable end, and repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf of his
fore-paſt Life, had ſo far moderated and cooled the Love he bore to Donna
<hi>Margareta,</hi> that he had no further remembrance of her than what his
Charity obliged him to, conſidering that it was not in the poor Ladies pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
to avoid what had hapned, had ſhe been as chaſte as <hi>Lucrece.</hi> On
the other ſide, his indifference for Donna <hi>Horten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> which had
hitherto been ſo great, was now converted into ſo lively Flames, that it
ſeemed to him that Heaven had tranſplanted all the Accompliſhments he
before ſo much admired, from Donna<pb n="187" facs="tcp:175400:99"/>
                  <hi>Margareta</hi> to
her. Alſo Donna <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gareta,</hi> whoſe repentance was firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun by
her Husbands devout Prayer, was now become ſo complete a <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene,</hi>
that the continual Currents which from her beauteous Eyes watered her Roſie
Cheeks, ſeemed ſufficient to have waſh'd clean the moſt defiled ſoul,
whilſt her ſighs made an Earthquake in her Body. She ſtill called upon
her dear <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> who was already bathing in the Floods of
unſpeakable Joys, which he poſſeſſed from the Beatifick Viſion.</p>
               <p>Reader, ſtay here a while the ſpeedy current of thy
thoughts, to take a ſhort conſideration of the volubility and
vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſitude of Mundane Affairs. He that is to day over head and ears in
Feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Plays, and Dances, and immer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in an inundation of Delights,
ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the richeſt Canopies over his Head, and Gold and Silk under his Feet;
liſtning to no Diſcourſe but that which tends to Mirth and Laughter; and
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Cups and Ladies takes his fill of the moſt exquiſite
delights which<pb n="188" facs="tcp:175400:100"/>
                  <hi>Bacchus</hi> or <hi>Venus</hi> can make
him Maſter of; him we ſee to morrow with his Affairs changed into ſo
Tragical a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, that in ſtead of theſe incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Grandeurs, all
his Accoutrements are but a poor thin Shroud, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellops his miſerable
Corps; his ſtately Lamps and Candleſticks of Gold and Silver, with which
before he was uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally attended, now changed into four dim Wax Tapers, which
burn unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably about his wretched Carcaſe; and all his rare Muſick and
raviſhing Notes changed into the pitteous Lamentations of his Friends and
Kindred, with which they mournfully attend his Obſequies. He loves to day
that which he will hate to morrow, and he abhors this day that which he will
paſſionately love the next. I could enlarge far enough upon this Subject,
were it not a wrong to my Diſcourſe and the Readers patience, which I will
endeavour to ſatisfie by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to my Narrative.</p>
               <p>The Evening was no ſooner come, but the two Coaches which Don
<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio</hi> had promiſed our two Lovers ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived <pb n="189" facs="tcp:175400:100"/>at their Lodging, into which they all entred, after a long trouble
which they had undergone to perſwade Donna <hi>Margareta</hi> to leave the
Company of her dead Husband for theirs. Her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction had reduced her to ſo
pitteous a condition, and her ſtrength was ſo abated by the exceſs of her
ſorrows, that ſhe had ſcarce enough left to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain her ſelf: at
laſt, partly by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance, and partly by compulſion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that
ſtaying alone in the Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome tragical event might happen through her
ſorrow, ſhe ſo far com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with their intreaties as to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany them,
after having left in charge with ſome Women, which the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour had ſent
to that purpoſe, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhrowd the Body of her dead Husband, and to ſee
performed all the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies requiſite to a Cavalier of his Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, till
and things were prepared for his Funerals.</p>
               <p>Being arrived at the Governour's Houſe, Donna
<hi>Clorinia</hi> his Wife, with her two Daughters, and a Niece of hers, all
endowed with an excellent<pb n="190" facs="tcp:175400:101"/>Beauty and incomparable
Civility, went out to receive them, and to teſtifie their joy which was
cauſed by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which was done them by their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival. An hour was
ſpent in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements and Careſſes uſual in ſuch ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters;
and after that they bent all their Diſcourſe to the comforting of Donna
<hi>Margareta,</hi> and repreſenting to her whatſoever they thought
conducing to the moderating her reſentments, and alleviating her ſorrows;
till at laſt their ſound Advice did ſo far fortifie and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage her,
that her Countenance te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified that her heavineſs was ſomewhat abated,
which gave no ſmall content to the Company, who attending the hour of
Bed-time, endeavoured to divert her the beſt they could, by entertaining her
with things moſt ſuitable to paſs the time contentedly.</p>
               <p>Bed-time being come, Don <hi>Antonio</hi> took Don
<hi>Carlos</hi> and conducted him to his Chamber, Donna <hi>Clorinia</hi> his
Lady doing the like to Donna <hi>Margareta</hi> and Donna <hi>Hortenſia,</hi>
and ſo every one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired to their ſeveral Lodgings, where 
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:175400:101"/>we will leave them, till the Sun with his reſplendent
Rays begin another Courſe in our Hemiſphere, and reſerve the remainder of
our Narrative for the ſixth and laſt Part of this Book.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Fifth Part.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:175400:102"/>
            <pb n="193" facs="tcp:175400:102"/>
            <head>THE AMOROUS TRAVELLERS, OR THE
<hi>Night-Adventures.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>PART VI.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Sun was already pretty well elevated, and his ardent Rays
begun to annoy the Labourer of the Field, that he was forced to quit his Cart
for his ordinary repoſe, when Don <hi>Antonio</hi> ſent Don <hi>Carlos</hi>
a Suit which had been newly made for a Son of his about the ſame Age with Don
<hi>Carlos,</hi>
                  <pb n="194" facs="tcp:175400:103"/>whoſe return from <hi>Italy</hi> he
daily expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. The Habit was of pure Gray <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>govian</hi> Cloth, with a
Doublet of Cloth of Gold: The Coat was open on both ſides, all over-ſpread
with Stars of Gold, and interlaced with a Golden Twiſt, wrought with ſuch
curious artifice, that it compoſed the rareſt Knots that Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Induſtry
could invent. The Suit being ſo rich and magnificent, the Cloke, Hat, Ruff,
Sword, and all the reſt of the Accoutrements were ſutable, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him
as well as they would have done him they were deſigned for: And if before in
his Female Habit he ſeemed a <hi>Venus,</hi> in this his Maſculine one he
was no leſs an <hi>Adonis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I leave it to the judgment of thoſe Ladies that have already
loved, or at preſent do ſo, whether his dear <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſia</hi> were not
highly pleaſed to ſee him ſo advantageouſly habited, and in a faſhion
which ſeemed to her ſo much more agreeable than that which he had lately
caſt off: So that no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er able to diſſemble the exceſs of joy which
ſhe took in ſeeing the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment<pb n="195" facs="tcp:175400:103"/>of her
deſires, and her ſelf poſſeſs'd of what ſhe lov'd more dearly than
her life, ſhe lovingly embraced him, beſtowing on him an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of Kiſſes, which brought no leſs ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to her ſelf than
appetite to the Governour's Wife and Daughters, who were all ſo taken with
the ſight of this lovely young Duke, that each of them could heartily have
wiſh'd the ſame li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, if Modeſty, the cruel Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of that Sex,
had not kept back and reſtrained them.</p>
               <p>We will leave them all in this plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant humour (except onely
Donna <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gareta,</hi> not yet well cleared of the grief cauſed by ſo
irreparable a loſs) and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Murtherer of Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi>
whom we left in Priſon, who was no ſooner extended upon the Rack, but he
cried out to ſlacken the Cords, and that he would truly anſwer to all they
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him: Which they having done, he told them his name was
<hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derigo Carcia,</hi> Son of <hi>Pedro Carcia</hi> Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant of
<hi>Viſo;</hi> that he had married a Niece of <hi>Ozmin Gutierres</hi> an
Inn-keeper<pb n="196" facs="tcp:175400:104"/>of <hi>Viſo,</hi> called <hi>Catalina de la
Croix;</hi> and that having had certain and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent proofs of her
diſhoneſty with Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> ſhe having confeſs'd that he
had lain with her the Night he lodged at <hi>Viſo,</hi> he had with his
Poniard given her a Recompence for her Treachery and Diſloyalty, (which
indeed was true; for after he had received the Money of his Uncle for his
Charges of going to the Wars, thereby to wear away the ſenſe of this
diſhonour, the Devil had tempted and incited him to return to
<hi>Viſo,</hi> and kill his Wife, which he did accordingly.) After which he
confeſſed, that intending to go to <hi>Flanders</hi> to ſerve his
Majeſty in the Low-Countrey Wars, his evil Genius had conducted him to this
City, where being arrived, and deſirous to ſee the Great Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his
departure, he had by the way met with Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> and
tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with extreme Choler, and pricked forward with a furious appetite
of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, ſeeing before his eyes the ſole cauſe of his misfortune, and
not able to bridle his reſentment of the injury,<pb n="197" facs="tcp:175400:104"/>he
leap'd to him and ſtabb'd him.</p>
               <p>This was all his Depoſition, and all which the Torments could
extract from him, though ſo extremely violent and cruel, being given in the
preſence of the Governour, that he was ſcarce car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried off alive: For which
cauſe the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour preſently ſet at liberty all Don <hi>Carlos</hi> his
Domeſticks, and Donna <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gareta's,</hi> and early the next morning
ſent the wretched <hi>Roderigo</hi> to the Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, to prevent any Trouble or
Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the City; for the Archbiſhop had ſent his Interdict, and
Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated the Governour (as the cuſtom is when the Secular Power
infringes the Eccleſiaſtick, as it had done here by taking the Criminal
forcibly out of Sanctuary.) And herein they proceed with great ſeverity; for
this Interdict hath ſuch efficacy, that there can no Maſs be celebrated in
any Church till it be taken off. But the Judge pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding equitably in ſuch
Affairs, makes Inquiſition whether the Offender killed his Adverſary by
Treachery, or on equal terms; and if he find that he dit it 
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:175400:105"/>fairly, he is obliged to ſend him back to Sanctuary;
but if the Murther was perfidiouſly committed, then the Judge ſends him to
the Gibbet, and after makes his dead Body be carried to the Church (as the
Governour here did with <hi>Roderigo.</hi>) After this the Biſhop is obliged
to take off the Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, by reaſon of the ſcandal it would bring
to the Pariſhioners; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeeing the Judge has proceeded fairly,
and according to Law: And therefore this is but a thing of courſe; for what
reaſon is there that Churches ſhould ſerve for a Refuge to Perſons ſo
hateful to God and deſtructive to Man as are Murtherers and
Aſſaſſines.</p>
               <p>After Juſtice had been executed on <hi>Roderigo,</hi> and all
the Services due to the dead had been performed to Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi>
they paſſed ſome days in Sports and Recreations, Don <hi>Antonio</hi>
ſparing no coſt that might conduce to the contentment of his new Gueſts;
but Don <hi>Carlos</hi> ſeeing himſelf more rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly treated than
ordinary by his dear <hi>Hortenſia,</hi> did daily conſume himſelf 
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:175400:105"/>with a languiſhing deſire of other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacies than
thoſe he enjoyed before Company; for thoſe were all the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies he
could obtain from her till they were authorized by the indiſſoluble Bonds
of Matrimony, which made him paſs his time with ſuch ſorrow and
melancholy, that thoſe things which ſerved for a divertiſement to others,
were but an augmentation of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content: Wherefore no longer able to
endure the exceſs of his paſſion, one day he took Don <hi>Antonio</hi>
aſide, and brought him to walk with him in a Garden which Don
<hi>Antonio</hi> had in a Place called the <hi>Cigarral,</hi> ſcituate in the
moſt pleaſant and fertile place that is near the City of <hi>Toledo;</hi>
where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arrived, they entred into a ſpaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Walk, bordered with many
Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binds and Jeſſamins, and ſhadowed with Fruit-Trees ſo thick and
expand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they were proof againſt the Suns moſt penetrating Rays in
the hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Summer; where our Duke having a while entertained himſelf upon
vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Subjects, at laſt told Don <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio,</hi>
                  <pb n="200" facs="tcp:175400:106"/> 
                  <q>That the moſt paſſionate deſire that diſturbed his
Breaſt, was to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh his Marriage with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt expedition
poſſible; and withal, earneſtly begg'd his conſent and
aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that he might without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delay go to preſent
himſelf and his dear <hi>Hortenſia</hi> at Court to his Majeſty, that he
might thence obtain Letters to the Dutcheſs his Mother, to ſollicite her
conſent to, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence at the Marriage.</q> Don <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio</hi> highly
applauded his deſign, and cloſed with him in his reſolution.</p>
               <p>They were no ſooner returned to the City, but Don
<hi>Carlos</hi> communicated his intention to his Miſtris and Don
<hi>Sancho,</hi> and at the ſame time ordered his Equipage to be ready to
depart within three days.</p>
               <p>It is impoſſible for me to repreſent to you the extreme
contentment which all his Friends and Servants received from that deſign,
principally the fair <hi>Hortenſia,</hi> who was ſo much the more
overjoyed, when ſhe remembred the troubles and miſeries ſhe had endured, 
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:175400:106"/>and conſidered the unſpeakable joy ſhe now
poſſeſſed: And ſtill acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Divine Goodneſs, from which
ſhe obtained all theſe Benefits, ſhe for a grateful acknowledgment
continually elevated her Eyes to Heaven: And as the rigours of a tedious.
Winter make the Spring far more delightful, ſo all the traverſes of her
inconſtant Fortune made the pleaſures of her aſſured Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs more
delicious.</p>
               <p>All things being prepared for their departure, and themſelves
ready to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Coach, Donna <hi>Margareta</hi> would have taken leave
of them; but Don <hi>Carlos</hi> and Donna <hi>Hortenſia</hi> did
ſeriouſly declare, that they could not conſent to her departure: And
though our beauteous young Dutcheſs had ſome cauſe of Jealouſie, having
a ſtrong ſuſpicion of what had paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, yet this never
abated the force of her affection: And though Don <hi>Carlos</hi> had
ſeriouſly excuſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by profeſſing that he had changed his
Habit for another intent, which for many Reaſons was fit to be kept 
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:175400:107"/>ſecret, yet their Amours having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been ſo
publickly known, and ſhe having ſeen many manifeſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of it,
ſhe inwardly gave little credit to his Proteſtations; yet being infinitely
ſage and diſcreet, the better to content him, ſhe made no ſemblance of
it, but ſeemed to credit all he ſaid. Add to this the love ſhe bore to
her deceaſed Coſin Don <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> having both been educated
together in their tender age, and by whom Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <hi>Margareta</hi> had a Son;
and further moved with the pity which one ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily bears to the afflicted,
and the Vertue ſhe had always remarked in her Perſon, all this made her
bear her an intimate affection; and that the more, when ſhe conſidered that
ſhe was the cauſe that Donna <hi>Margareta</hi> loſt ſo advantageous a
Match as that of Don <hi>Carlos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe Conſiderations made ſuch an effort upon her
Soul, that fearing that all the entreaties of Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> Don
<hi>Antonio,</hi> and Donna <hi>Clorinia</hi> his Wife ſhould not be able to
prevail<pb n="203" facs="tcp:175400:107"/>with her to accompany them, ſhe fell to making
ſuch Careſſes to her, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing her ſo lovingly, and conjuring her
with ſo many tears, that at length her entreaties ſurmounted the others
reſolution, and prevailed with her to go along with them, accompanied by all
her Train.</p>
               <p>Being arrived at <hi>Madrid,</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, that would
never abandon them till he had finiſh'd what he had ſo happily begun,
preſented them to his Catholick Majeſty. Things there ſucceeded ſo
happily, that the King and Queen, well pleaſed at their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival, made them
all the beſt Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment they could expect or deſire. All the Grandees
then at Court flock'd into the Room, aſtoniſh'd at the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty, but far
more at the Beauty of our two Lovers, to ſee ſo many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in Mortal
Creatures. The Queen, who had not all this while been able to remove her Eyes
from the fair <hi>Hortenſia,</hi> with the ſole ſight of whom ſhe was
ſo highly ſatisfied, thought her pleaſure could not but be 
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:175400:108"/>much augmented by a nearer approach, which
conſideration made her ſo far diſpence with that of her Royal Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur,
that ſhe tenderly embraced her, and kiſſed her twice or thrice, and at
that time entertained an affection for her, which never ended but with her
life.</p>
               <p>At the ſame time the King, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Duke's graceful
behaviour, could not refrain from embracing him, and teſtifying by his
Careſſes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent he took in his ready obedience to his Commands, he in
requital re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced him with his Friendſhip. And to make it appear to
Poſterity, that the Services of thoſe who have ſpent their Blood, or
hazarded their Lives in their Kings Service, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their Countrey and
Faith, as the late <hi>Gonſalvo de Mendoça</hi> had done, ſhould not
remain without a Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence ſuitable to their Merits, 
<q>I give you (ſaid he to the Duke) fifty thouſand Ducates,
to help to buy your Marriage-Clothes. And to let the Infanta my Royal Siſter
ſee, that<pb n="205" facs="tcp:175400:108"/>what is pleaſing to her is ſo to me, I
intend that the Nuptials ſhall be at my Charges, and that with a
ſumptuouſneſs and magnificence ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Splendour of the
<hi>Spaniſh</hi> Court.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This ſaid he made him 
<note n="*" place="margin">As the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees of <hi>Spain</hi> do
before the King.</note>put on his Hat; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one told him that the
Dinner was upon the Table, the King took him by the hand, and placed him at the
Table with himſelf: The Queen did the ſame to Donna <hi>Hortenſia;</hi>
ſo that our two Lovers had this day the Honour to dine at the ſame Table
with their Catholick Majeſties.</p>
               <p>In the mean time having ſent a Courrier to the Dutcheſs
Dowager, the Duke's Mother, to advertiſe her of what was paſt, and to beg
her Company, all things were prepared for the Nuptials, and that with ſuch
care and diligence, that in leſs than eight days all things were made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
for that Solemnity. All the Great Perſons and Cavaliers about the Court 
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:175400:109"/>had prepared their Habits and Liveries for the Game
called <hi>de las</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">An ordinary Paſtime in <hi>Spain</hi>
upon great So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities, where the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers combat with Tilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-ſtaves
made of Canes.</note>
                  <hi>Cannas,</hi> and thoſe ſo rich and magnificent,
that Art with diverſity of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours ſeemed to have ſurmounted Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it
ſelf, which wrought an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in all the beholders.</p>
               <p>The old Dutcheſs, Mother of Don <hi>Carlos,</hi> arriving at
<hi>Madrid,</hi> received all the contentment imaginable, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily accounting
that day the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of her whole life; and the joy was the more
raviſhing, after her fears and ſorrows for her Son in his abſence,
fearing leſt ſome ſudden miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hap had been the occaſion of that and
his ſilence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Madrid</hi> had never ſeen within her Walls greater
Magnificences than theſe: The King, the Queen, the new-mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Couple, and
the whole Court were ſo richly Habited, that the ſole Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidery of their
Clothes was valued at above ſix hundred thouſand Crowns. I cannot
aſſure you of this for truth,<pb n="207" facs="tcp:175400:109"/>nor dare I depoſe it
for a verity, leſt ſome Critick catch hold of it for a lie: And beſides,
I cannot make out abſolute proofs of all I have ſaid in this Narrative, nor
ſuch plain Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as are uſed in Mathematical Rules and Figures;
and I think it is fitting for a Writer to embroider his Diſcourſe (as they
did their Habits) with a little deſcanting and enlargement. But to
return.</p>
               <p>All theſe rejoycings ended with the day; our new-married
Couple, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Cuſtom, were condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to their Chamber, and to a
Bed ſomewhat ſofter and better accoutred than are ordinarily found
amongſt the Inns of <hi>Sierra Morena,</hi> or that of the
<hi>Carçuela.</hi> I ſuppoſe it unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to tell you what
they did there; for I believe you know as well as my ſelf. The next Morning
their Friends came to viſit them in Bed, and made themſelves merry with the
Jeſts uſual upon that Subject: but our two Lovers filled with pleaſure,
and even ecſtaſied with the Delights<pb n="208" facs="tcp:175400:110"/>of the Night
paſt, ſuffer'd all this Raillery as patiently as Gameſters that have won
a great Sum at Play would do thoſe of the by-ſtanders.</p>
               <p>About fifteen days after, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour Don <hi>Antonio</hi>
took leave of them to return home; and Don <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los</hi> having thanked him
for all the Civilities he had received of his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality, made him a Preſent
of eight curious Horſes. The fair <hi>Hortenſia</hi> was no leſs
munificent in her Preſents to Donna <hi>Clorinia</hi> and her Daughters, than
Don <hi>Carlos</hi> had been to Don <hi>Antonio,</hi> who would not have
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of the Preſent but by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of Don <hi>Carlos</hi> his
entreaties, which he uttered with an accent that ſufficiently teſtified his
reſentment of his Civilities, telling him that he would ſeem to deſpiſe
his Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in refuſing this ſmall teſtimony of it.</p>
               <p>He then left <hi>Madrid</hi> to return to <hi>Toledo,</hi> where
we will leave him to his Journey (which I have heard ſince was very
proſperous) and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn<pb n="209" facs="tcp:175400:110"/>to Donna <hi>Margareta,</hi>
becauſe it is now time to ſpeak of her, whom we muſt conduct to a ſafe
Port (before we draw out Ship into the Dry Dock) where ſhe may happily paſs
the reſt of her days in all the Pleaſures and Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that a Lady of
her Age and Beauty could deſire; that afterwards my Pen wearied with writing,
and my Spirit tired with ſo long a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe, may have ſome time to
repoſe, and prepare themſelves for another ſubject.</p>
               <p>The beauteous Donna <hi>Margareta,</hi> feeling her ſelf
ſomewhat disburthened of her troubles, and now able to ſupport the weight
of her afflictions without the help of her former Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, demanded leave one
day of Donna <hi>Hortenſia</hi> to depart, and, in recompence of her former
Favours, made her an offer of her future Services, with all the
ſubmiſſion and civility imaginable.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="210" facs="tcp:175400:111"/>The fair <hi>Hortenſia</hi>
underſtanding by theſe words that ſhe on whom above all others ſhe had
fixed her affection, intended to leave her, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whoſe company ſhe was
not able to live contentedly, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed at all, more than a Body deprived of
its Vital Faculties, begg'd her longer ſtay with ſighs and tears enough to
mollifie a Tygre, ſaying, that without her ſhe was the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerableſt
Creature alive. Don <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los</hi> immediately arriving, and ſeeing his
dearer Half thus afflicted, ran to her, fearing ſome ſtrange acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent had
hapned, and taking her in his Arms, learn'd from her own mouth the ſubject of
her forrows; 
<q>No, no, (ſaid he) my Dear, I will procure her to ſtay, if
all my Eſtate, my Supplications, and thoſe of my Friends can have any power
to perſwade her to it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Donna <hi>Margareta,</hi> who never thought before that her
departure<pb n="211" facs="tcp:175400:111"/>could bring ſo ſenſible a grief to the
Dutcheſs, repented of what ſhe had ſaid, and to ſhew the zeal ſhe had
to her Service, ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed her to ſtay with her as long as ſhe
deſired: Whereupon Don <hi>Carlos</hi> ſaid, 
<q>You will wrong the Friendſhip, Madam, that we bear to you,
if you think any longer by your departure of croſſing our deſigns, which
are to procure you a Husband ſutable to your Quality and Merits; for it is
nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther juſt nor reaſonable that a Beauty like yours ſhould fade and
conſume it ſelf unprofitably.</q> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this the two Ladies embraced one
another; and by their Kiſſes and extraordinary Careſſes teſtified the
exceſs of their Amity.</p>
               <p>Donna <hi>Margareta</hi> remembring what had paſs'd betwixt
her and <hi>Valerio,</hi> the Page of her deceaſed Husband, when by a
ſtrange accident (as you have heard in the beginning of this Hiſtory) he
had enjoyed her, and<pb n="155" facs="tcp:175400:112"/>conſidering that to live
honeſtly, and to paſs the reſt of her Life in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Wedlock (without
which the moſt reſerved and modeſt Woman muſt have an eſpecial
Providence from Heaven to live in Chaſtity) ſhe thought it neceſſary
for the diſcharge of her Conſcience to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry him; which being diſcovered
to her Confeſſor, he not onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and praiſed her pious
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, but alſo enjoyned it as neceſſary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Valerio</hi> was of higher Blood than Fortune, being the Son
of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Gentleman of <hi>Oſmus,</hi> whoſe Eſtate had been very
much impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the loſs of a great Sum of Money, which being Imbarqued
up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a <hi>Weſt-India</hi> Plate-Ship, had been taken by the Low-Countrey
Rebels Fleet; and he being thereby much impoveriſhed, and having many more
Children to provide for, had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented this, being a well-bred and rarely
accompliſh'd Youth, to wait<pb n="213" facs="tcp:175400:112"/>upon Don
<hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> at his Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age with Donna <hi>Margareta</hi> at
<hi>Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> who had always a great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to him for his dexterity
and wit, till at laſt fortune raiſed him to this Happineſs.</p>
               <p>Donna <hi>Margareta,</hi> as I have ſaid, having taken this
reſolution, impart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to Don <hi>Carlos</hi> by one of her Gentlemen; but
he at firſt, not knowing the cauſe of her Reſolve, did much reſiſt
it, wondering to ſee a Lady of her Quality deſiring to be married to a
young man who not long before was Page to her Husband: But at laſt, ſeeing
her reſolution immovable, he conſented to it, and gave him for a Portion
ten thouſand Ducats on his Marriage-day, making him Superintendent of his
Houſe.</p>
               <p>And thus having brought him to this happineſs, in the
enjoyment of the fair Donna <hi>Margareta;</hi> and Don <hi>Carlos</hi> in that
of his dear <hi>Hortenſia,</hi>
                  <pb n="214" facs="tcp:175400:113" rendition="simple:additions"/>we will leave
them there in all the felicity they could enjoy or hope for, to conſider from
the Occurrences of this Narration the Viciſſitude of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Affairs, the
Deceits and Wiles that are daily practiced in the World, the Changes of
Fortune, and the Misfortunes that daily purſue Unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Actions.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:175400:113" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
